<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ryzen on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/ryzen/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ryzen on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/ryzen/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Selecting Charmeleon&#39;s Upgrades</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/selecting-charmeleons-upgrades/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/selecting-charmeleons-upgrades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After months of planning and price tracking, I have finished upgrading
several major components in my Linux workstation. What started
as a planned cpu and ram upgrade, eventually ballooned to also include a new
motherboard and a secondary gpu. Let me explain&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/pre_upgrades.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Inside charmeleon before upgrades&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/pre_upgrades.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Charmeleon Internals before the upgrades&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over two years ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/charmeleon-desktop-design/&#34;&gt;built and designed
charmeleon&lt;/a&gt;, my Linux desktop computer. In
that post, I explained how I wanted to upgrade charmeleon over time, and
designed it with that in mind. Since the initial build, I have only made a
few minor enhancements: I added a nvme ssd and &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/rx580-upgrade/&#34;&gt;upgraded the
gpu&lt;/a&gt; after the original one stopped working. The next
change I hoped to make was adding more RAM. However, as I started down that path,
things became a bit more&amp;hellip; complicated&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;part-selection&#34;&gt;Part Selection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ram&#34;&gt;RAM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/ripjaws_ram.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Two 32GB sticks of DDR4 3200 ram in&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/ripjaws_ram.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;RAM upgrade: 2x32 GB of 3200Mhz DDR4, CL 16&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An easy upgrade I prepared for during the initial build was RAM. My
motherboard had 4 slots with a max capacity of 64GB. So, I made sure to
populate it with 2x16gb sticks instead of 4x8gb ones, so the capacity could
be effortlessly doubled when RAM became cheaper. But, the release of Ryzen
3000 cpus changed things. Overnight, a Ryzen 3000 serries processor paired
with my motherboard could support up to 128gb of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made me wonder if I should instead fill those blank spaces with the
&lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; max dimm size sticks. The only problem was, if I wanted to upgrade RAM
to the new max size, I also needed to upgrade to a newer CPU. Oh, and also
buy twice the anticipated capacity of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spoiler alert: I did also buy a new cpu. More on that below.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I settled on a Ripjaws V 2x32GB 3200Mhz kit with 16-18-18-38
timings. There wasn&amp;rsquo;t a 2x32gb pair that matched the model of my original
RAM, and but this one had all the same timings while still being cheaper than
other alternatives. A total of 96GB of RAM is definitely overkill for most
uses (arguably, even my own). However, I tend to run large, automated VM
deployments and use my &lt;code&gt;/tmp/&lt;/code&gt; dir as a large scratch folder, so the
extra overhead is nice to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDR:&lt;/strong&gt; I always planned to expand my RAM. Ryzen 3000 allowed an even higher
max RAM capacity with my MB, but I would have to also upgrade my CPU. I upgraded both,
and now have 96GB of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cpu&#34;&gt;CPU&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/ryzen9_box.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Ryzen 9 3900x Box&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/ryzen9_box.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;CPU upgrade: Ryzen 9 3900x, 12 core/24 thread cpu&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;original&lt;/em&gt; plan when I built charmeleon was to get the 2600, and later
upgrade to a 8 core 2700x or a 3000 cpu that was rumored to have even more
cores. I made sure my motherboard had good VRMs for the cost, so it could
support a future upgrade with more cores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Months after 3000 cpus launched, I was set on getting a 3900x.
However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a new cpu yet and I knew AMD was going to be releasing
the &amp;ldquo;4000&amp;rdquo; cpus in the Fall. I figured I would wait until they were
released, and then buy a new one, or a discounted 3000 serries one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the 5000 series cpus were released (AMD skipped 4000 on the desktop), I
thought the 5900x would be perfect. Unfortunately, like ever other tech
release of 2020, it was nearly impossible to buy one. I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like
waiting even longer, and I don&amp;rsquo;t actually &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; the increased performance.
The new gains are particularly observed in gaming&amp;hellip; but I&amp;rsquo;m rocking a
rx580 and am clearly gpu bottlenecked anyway 😆. I can &lt;em&gt;manage&lt;/em&gt; just fine
with slower single core speeds&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the 5900x not available anytime soon, I became tempted by some
crazier options&amp;hellip; like the 3950x. The 3950x is an amazing cpu, and honestly
I&amp;rsquo;d still love to have one. However, even if I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; get it on sale&amp;hellip; I
knew it would still cost a ton and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t justify the price difference. While a
16 core cpu is amazing, a 12 core still easily covers my needs. The money
&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;saved&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; on the price difference could then be used to get the bigger ram
upgrade I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I looked back at the 3900x and wondered if it would go on sale. It did
occasionally, but seemed like there might start to be shortage issues with
people jumping to &lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt; after not being able to get a 5900x. The next time I
saw it go on sale, I snagged one just as they sold out again. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get it
for the cheapest it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; been, but the sale was quite close to the all
time low. And it was &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; cheaper than what it has remained at ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDR:&lt;/strong&gt; I planned to upgrade to a higher core count CPU. After
waiting, I wanted a 5900x, but you can&amp;rsquo;t buy them. After being tempted by the
3950x, I purchased the more reasonably priced 3900x on sale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cpu-cooler&#34;&gt;CPU Cooler&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/noctua_box.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Noctua nh-u14s box&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/noctua_box.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;CPU Cooler upgrade: Noctua NH-U14s&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the summer I upgraded all the fans in my case to Noctua ones and love
them. At the time, I wanted to also get a new cpu cooler to match, but with plans
to upgrade my cpu soon, I figured I would wait and order both at the same time so
I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to go through the hassel of repasting the CPU twice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I switched what specific model I wanted once or twice, after being confused
about compatibility. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want the massive NH-D15, but &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; want a
cooler that used a 140mm fans instead of 120mm ones. I much prefer the lower
sounding &amp;ldquo;woosh&amp;rdquo; of larger fans. After I confirmed it would fit in the
Meshify C with my RAM, I selected the NH-U14s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDR:&lt;/strong&gt; I wanted a new CPU Cooler with a 140mm fan. I love Noctua.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;motherboard&#34;&gt;Motherboard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/mb_box.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;x570 Aorus Elite Wifi Box&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/mb_box.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Motherboard upgrade: x570 Aorus Elite Wifi&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the CPU and RAM, I never intended to get a new motherboard when
building Charmeleon. When I was thinking about getting a 5900x, I knew my
B450 thomahawk wouldn&amp;rsquo;t get the required bios upgrade until January&amp;hellip; and
even then, only maybe. I also knew the upgrade might not be reversible which
I didn&amp;rsquo;t like, so I started to look at B550 and x570 boards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While researching, I realized x570 fit my needs a bit better when compared to
my b450, and even newer b550 boards (which I think &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; people should probably
get). The x570 paired well with the other upgrades I was making. Particular
features I liked compared to the b450 tomahawk were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gen4 PCIe support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better iommu groupings for VFIO passthrough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often had a second m.2 (or more)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More &lt;em&gt;usable&lt;/em&gt; sata ports (2 of mine were disabled because they shared lanes with my m.2),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;wifi (mostly for bluetooth)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In general, more pcie lanes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked at motherboards for months while waiting for Ryzen 5000 to be
officially announced. After some time, I concluded that I wanted a x570
Gigabyte Aorus board, but wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure which one. The Aorus Master was one of
&lt;em&gt;the defacto recommend&lt;/em&gt; boards for VFIO builds, but it was very expensive.
Much of what made it so good however seemed to still be present in the
cheaper Aorus models. In particular, the Aorus boards had great iommu
groupings and support,
&lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a bios feature which allowed either x16 slot to be selected as the
primary gpu. This makes it easier to boot into a secondary gpu, saving the
beefier one to pass through to VMs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back and forth for weeks trying to decide between the elite wifi, pro, ultra&amp;hellip;
and sometimes even the master. When I started making
purchases, the elite wifi went on sale and I decided to grab it. It had
everything I needed, and most of the upgraded features on the other boards I
either wouldn&amp;rsquo;t use or were just small nice to haves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDR:&lt;/strong&gt; Looking at Ryzen 5000 CPUs had me looking at newer motherboards.
Even after dropping back down to a 3000 CPU, I still wanted a motherboard
upgrade for better VFIO support and expandability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gpu&#34;&gt;GPU&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/gpu_box.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;rx550 box&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/gpu_box.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Second GPU: RX 550 4GB&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a motherboard that better supported vfio passthrough, I wanted to get a
smaller gpu that I could use for host machine&amp;rsquo;s graphics. I read that the rx550 and
1030gt were both good, sub $100 gpus often used for the host.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t thrilled about using a nvida gpu on a linux host, but I loved how
small it was (although that could translate more fan moise). In comparison,
the 550 seemed to be slightly more powerful, was amd, and well rated. In
fact, I had read several gpu passthrough guides using the rx550 and passing
through a rx580 (my current gpu). So, I purchased the 550.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDR:&lt;/strong&gt; I wanted an easier time with VFIO GPU passthrough. Having a second
card for the host or a second VM makes this easier. The rx550 is a common card
for this use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/post_upgrades.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Inside charmeleon after upgrades&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/selecting-charmeleon-upgrades/post_upgrades.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Charmeleon Internals after upgrades&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I am extremely happy with my selections. It is surreal how powerful of a
machine can be built with a modest budget these days. With the upgrades,
Charmelon&amp;rsquo;s specs now stand at:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ryzen 9 3900x [3.8 GHz (4.6GHz Boost), 12 Cores, 24 Threads)
Noctua NH-U14s CPU Cooler
Aorus Elite Wifi x570 Motherboard
96 GB (2x16GB, 2x32GB) DDR4-3200 Mhz, CL 16 RAM
Sapphire Radeon Pulse RX 580 8GB GPU
Sapphire Radeon Pulse RX 550 4GB GPU
500 GB Samsung 970 EVO NVME SSD
500 GB Samsung 850 EVO SATA SSD
120 GB Kingston SSD (Dedicated windows VM)
EVGA SuperNOVA G4 650w 80+ Gold, fully modular PSU
Fractal Design Meshify C Dark TG ATX Mid Tower Case
2 x Noctua NF-A14 PWM 140mm Fans
1 x Noctua NF-F12 PWM 120mm Fan
Fedora 33 (KDE Plasma)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only have these changes drastically improved the performance of my
workstation, but they have allowed me to run virtual machines at the next
level. When passing hardware directly to my VMs, I cannot tell that the
computer I&amp;rsquo;m sitting at is virtualized. This lets me treat my workstation as several computers in one, and I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it for now! I still want to get a second nvme drive, but other than that
I think upgrades to Charmeleon will slow down for a bit&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing my new Ryzen Workstation</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/charmeleon-desktop-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/charmeleon-desktop-design/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years (particularly after moving to the &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/my-t470/&#34;&gt;T470&lt;/a&gt;
as my main device), I have been anticipating what my next desktop
workstation build will look like. For a period of time, I was convinced that
I would build a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.techspot.com/review/1155-affordable-dual-xeon-pc/&#34;&gt;muti-socket, used xeon
build&lt;/a&gt;. Then, in 2017
AMD released their &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryzen&#34;&gt;Ryzen&lt;/a&gt;
series CPUs&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-a-desktop&#34;&gt;Why a Desktop?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/chameleon-desktop-design/kadabra-cpu-usage.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Full system monitor on Laptop&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/charmeleon-desktop-design/kadabra-cpu-usage.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My T470 has been a little tight on resources.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../post/sold-my-bonobo/&#34;&gt;My&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/my-t470/&#34;&gt;laptops&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/my-new-used-x230&#34;&gt;have&lt;/a&gt;
served the majority of my needs these last few years, but I have been feeling
a bit restricted when trying to do more demanding workloads.
While I still side with a &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;use low-powered, portable computers, and remote
into more powerful ones when needed&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; mentality, I enjoy having &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of those
power computers being my physical, main workstation desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;workstation-goals&#34;&gt;Workstation Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/chameleon-desktop-design/ryzen-logo.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Ryzen Logo&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/charmeleon-desktop-design/ryzen-logo.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My T470 has been a little tight on resources.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While building a new workstation may be fun, I have particular goals I want it
to achieve. Additionally, it seems like 98% of online build guides are for
designing &lt;em&gt;gaming&lt;/em&gt; desktops&amp;hellip; which is not exactly what I want. So, the
features I wanted in &lt;em&gt;my build&lt;/em&gt;, likely deviate from much of the
&lt;em&gt;suggested&lt;/em&gt; guidance found online, which tends to focus entirely on gaming
performance (more FPS). Here is the breakdown of what I was looking for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;more-cores&#34;&gt;More Cores&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend to have workloads that benefit from multiple cores (and threads). For
example, I run a bunch of virtual machines, often at the same time. While my
server&amp;rsquo;s 4 core Xeon handles day to day VMs just fine, it is nice to have a
workstation with several cores to spin up a virtualized cluster across. Beyond
VMs, I compile code, compress/decompress file packages, and occasionally encode
audio/video files. These are all tasks that love having many threads at their
disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;lots-of-fast-ram&#34;&gt;Lots of (&lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;) Ram&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When running VMs, the amount of available RAM is usually more limiting than the
number of cpu cores. For example, when running 6 VM&amp;rsquo;s, my server&amp;rsquo;s 4-core Xeon
will typically be 15-35% utilized, whereas it&amp;rsquo;s 20GB of RAM is nearly full.  If
I want more cores, I should supplement it with lots of RAM. In addition&amp;hellip; I
use electron apps (Slack, Spotify,  etc.) and modern web browsers&amp;hellip; so yea&amp;hellip;. more RAM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a Ryzen build, the RAM also needs to be &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;.  More than other CPU
architectures, Ryzen CPUs actually &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g0SDr3EHHmY&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;run better&lt;/em&gt; with faster
RAM&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;fast-storage&#34;&gt;Fast Storage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This main goal of this build is for it to be a multi-tasking beast. If I am
running several VMs and a bunch of applications, utilizing a stack of &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; RAM
to move data around&amp;hellip; I need good &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; storage with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Bh_f0uof7Jw&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=359&#34;&gt;MOAR
IOPs&lt;/a&gt; to
support of these operations, which will all be competing for disk access. While I
wouldn&amp;rsquo;t mind having space to eventually throw in a pair 3.5&amp;rdquo; rust drives to configure as a
ZFS data pool, the goal for the initial &lt;em&gt;primary&lt;/em&gt; drive of this
machine is the most IOPs I can &lt;em&gt;afford&lt;/em&gt;. So, I ideally &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; a m.2 NVMe SSD,
but &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a normal 2.5&amp;rdquo; SATA SSD at the very least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;some-gaming-ability&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some&lt;/em&gt; Gaming Ability&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be a &lt;em&gt;gaming machine&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip; I would like to be able to
play the &lt;em&gt;occasional&lt;/em&gt; game. I don&amp;rsquo;t mind playing games with lower graphic
settings on my laptops, but I &lt;em&gt;do mind&lt;/em&gt; that even with the lower settings, the
CPUs nearly max out, which spikes up the temperature.
Increased graphics performance would also better support &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/new-lgud4379b/&#34;&gt;my large
monitor&lt;/a&gt;.  A discrete graphics card would be nice, ideally
an AMD one due to their recent work on improving their open source drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ability-to-upgrade&#34;&gt;Ability to Upgrade&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, I want this computer to be a solid &lt;em&gt;base&lt;/em&gt; that I can upgrade
over the next several years. Upgradability is hands-down &lt;em&gt;the main&lt;/em&gt; advantage
of switching to a desktop over a laptop for my main rig. I want this build
designed so that as my needs grow, I can easily max out the RAM, add storage,
or upgrade the CPU and/or GPU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-build-selections&#34;&gt;Final Build Selections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/chameleon-desktop-design/charmeleon.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Chameleon Picture&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/charmeleon-desktop-design/charmeleon.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 40%; float: right;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After spending weeks researching all the parts on the market and building
probably 50 theoretical builds, I eventually settled on &lt;a href=&#34;https://pcpartpicker.com/user/himmelwr/saved/#view=MhbcYJ&#34;&gt;my final part list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;name-charmeleon&#34;&gt;Name: Charmeleon&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my last desktop build was named &amp;ldquo;Charmander&amp;rdquo;, I figured &amp;ldquo;Charmeleon&amp;rdquo; was
fitting. Also, I&amp;rsquo;m then free to rename it to &amp;ldquo;Charzard&amp;rdquo; in the future if I &lt;em&gt;evolve&lt;/em&gt;
the build to a next-generation Ryzen 7&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cpu-ryzen-5-2600-https-en-wikichip-org-wiki-amd-ryzen-5-2600&#34;&gt;CPU: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikichip.org/wiki/amd/ryzen_5/2600&#34;&gt;Ryzen 5 2600&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/chameleon-desktop-design/ryzen2600.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ryzen 2600&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/charmeleon-desktop-design/ryzen2600.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 40%; float: left;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I initially wanted a Ryzen 2700, it pushed the build out of budget.
Coming from a 4 core/4 thread system&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s likely that I don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; 8
cores/16 threads right off the bat. Honestly, 4 cores/8 threads would be a
noticeable improvement from what I&amp;rsquo;ve been using&amp;hellip; which is why I first
considered the Ryzen 5 2400g. I planned to start with the 2400g and upgrade to
the 2700 and a GPU once I had more cash. However, &lt;a href=&#34;https://forum.level1techs.com/t/finalizing-an-upgradable-ryzen-linux-build/134670/2&#34;&gt;someone on the level1tech
forums&lt;/a&gt;
reminded me that the 2600 was the same price as the 2400g, and I could get that
plus a GPU for not much more cost (considering I don&amp;rsquo;t need an expensive GPU).
After thinking it over, I realized that was my best option, and should
&lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; fit my needs for quite awhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;motherboard-msi-b450-tomahawk-https-www-msi-com-motherboard-b450-tomahawk&#34;&gt;Motherboard: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.msi.com/Motherboard/B450-TOMAHAWK&#34;&gt;MSI B450 Tomahawk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/chameleon-desktop-design/tomahawk.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;B450 Tomahawk motherboard&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/charmeleon-desktop-design/tomahawk.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 40%; float: right;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had selected the MSI B450 Tomahawk after &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lxtrHDJUMt4&#34;&gt;Wendell reviewed
it&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MWGzmbbimPw&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=145&#34;&gt;Several
other&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MMJoLyrWa7E&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=1260&#34;&gt;reviews
confirmed&lt;/a&gt; that it was a solid board, especially for the price. When I was
considering the 2400g, I had to switch to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newegg.com/Product/Product.aspx?Item=N82E16813144188&#34;&gt;MSI B450 Gaming Pro Carbon
AC&lt;/a&gt;, because
the Tomahawk didn&amp;rsquo;t have a display output that the integrated graphics could
properly use with &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/new-lgud4379b/&#34;&gt;my UHD monitor&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s resolution (I need a
display port). When I switched to the 2600, I was able to go back to the
TOMAHAWK, and funnel the cost savings towards getting my GPU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;gpu-sapphire-1024-4gb-pulse-radeon-rx-560-https-www-techpowerup-com-gpu-specs-sapphire-pulse-rx-560-oc-4-gb-b4627&#34;&gt;GPU: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.techpowerup.com/gpu-specs/sapphire-pulse-rx-560-oc-4-gb.b4627&#34;&gt;Sapphire 1024 4GB PULSE Radeon RX 560&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/chameleon-desktop-design/rx560.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The KDE Plasma 5 extend display GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/charmeleon-desktop-design/rx560.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 35%; float: left;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed above, I don&amp;rsquo;t need a killer GPU as I don&amp;rsquo;t play very demanding
games. However, I did want something that could perform at least a &lt;em&gt;little
bit&lt;/em&gt;. So, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=237L9UGQtGk&amp;amp;t=422s&#34;&gt;I picked the rx560 over the
rx550&lt;/a&gt;. At first I planned
to get something like a rx580, which I still might eventually do&amp;hellip; but
I don&amp;rsquo;t think I will &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ram-g-skill-trident-z-32gb-2-x-16gb-ddr4-3200mhz-ram&#34;&gt;RAM: G.Skill - Trident Z 32GB (2 x 16GB) DDR4-3200Mhz RAM&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/chameleon-desktop-design/ram.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The KDE Plasma 5 extend display GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/charmeleon-desktop-design/ram.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 40%; float: right;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to start out with 32GB of RAM, with the ability to easily upgrade to
64GB down the road. This meant that I needed a 2x16GB pack. Additionally, I
needed the RAM to be &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;, but still not &lt;em&gt;overpriced&lt;/em&gt;. Some research showed
that at least right now, &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/lxtrHDJUMt4?t=752&#34;&gt;3200Mhz seems to be the sweet spot, especially for my
particular motherboard&lt;/a&gt;. I originally
picked another kit, but the reviews for it weren&amp;rsquo;t great, so I switched to the
G.Skill kit for only a few dollars more, but with much better reviews. I also
briefly searched for kits with tighter timings, but they were &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; more expensive and not worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;case-fractal-design-meshify-c-dark-tg-atx-mid-tower-https-www-fractal-design-com-home-product-cases-meshify-meshify-c&#34;&gt;Case: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fractal-design.com/home/product/cases/meshify/meshify-c&#34;&gt;Fractal Design - Meshify C Dark TG ATX Mid Tower&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/chameleon-desktop-design/meshifyc.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The KDE Plasma 5 extend display GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/charmeleon-desktop-design/meshifyc.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 30%; float: left; margin-bottom: 10px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted a case that was sturdy, sleek, but not too flashy or expensive. During my
search, the Fractal Design cases kept catching eye. Eventually, I found the
Meshify C TG Dark, which seemed to be universally loved by reviewers. Additionally,
it appeared to have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fractal-design.com/home/product/cases/meshify/meshify-c&#34;&gt;good
thermals&lt;/a&gt;,
which I liked. This was my easiest part to pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;psu-evga-supernova-g4-650w-80-gold-fully-modular-atx-psu-https-web-archive-org-web-20181102223931-https-www-evga-com-products-product-aspx-pn-120-g1-0650-xr&#34;&gt;PSU: EVGA - &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20181102223931/https://www.evga.com/Products/Product.aspx?pn=120-G1-0650-XR&#34;&gt;SuperNOVA G4 650W 80+ Gold, fully modular ATX PSU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/chameleon-desktop-design/psu.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The KDE Plasma 5 extend display GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/charmeleon-desktop-design/psu.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 35%; float: right; margin-bottom: 10px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the power supply, I wanted one that was at least gold rated, and fully
modular. So I searched for the highest rated PSUs fitting those requirements&amp;hellip;
and SuperNova popped up all over the place. At first I picked a 550w model, but
upped to the 650w at the last minute because it was about the same price and
gives me a little more room as I upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;storage-one-of-my-samsung-850-evo-ssds-temp&#34;&gt;Storage: One of my Samsung 850 Evo SSDs (temp)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, storage. For now I am just going to use a spare 250GB Samsung 850 Evo SSD
I had in my test laptop. I plan to eventually upgrade to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.samsung.com/semiconductor/minisite/ssd/product/consumer/970evo/&#34;&gt;500GB Samsung 970 Evo
m.2 NVMe
drive&lt;/a&gt;,
but the 850 will work for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after months of planing and research, my desktop parts have all been
ordered. Hopefully, it meets the goals I set out to solve, and I will be able
to upgrade it over the next few years&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
