<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>security on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/security/</link>
    <description>Recent content in security on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching to Bitwarden</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/switching-to-bitwarden/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/switching-to-bitwarden/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After years of using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.passwordstore.org/&#34;&gt;pass&lt;/a&gt; as my password
manager, I am mixing things up. Over vacation, I started importing all of my
passwords into &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitwarden.com/&#34;&gt;Bitwarden&lt;/a&gt;. With all my passwords
finally transferred, I have now switched to using Bitwarden full-time. Here
are my thoughts so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-switch&#34;&gt;Why Switch?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I start, I want to point out that I had already started my switch &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt;
the large Bitwarden segment on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://linuxunplugged.com/316&#34;&gt;recent episode of Linux
Unplugged&lt;/a&gt;. That was just a re-assuring
coincidence &lt;code&gt;:)&lt;/code&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why did I decide to switch?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;easier-setup&#34;&gt;Easier Setup&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switching-to-bitwarden/bigtwarden-flathub.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Bitwarden on Flathub Page&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switching-to-bitwarden/bitwarden-flathub.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Bitwarden on Flathub&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason is that when configuring a new system, Bitwarden is simply
easier to setup. All I need to do is install a Bitwarden client and login. In
fact, using the hosted service I don&amp;rsquo;t even need to do that. I can just login
using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://vault.bitwarden.com/&#34;&gt;web vault&lt;/a&gt;. Installing is made even
easier by the fact that Bitwarden is packaged as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://flathub.org/apps/details/com.bitwarden.desktop&#34;&gt;Flatpak on
flathub&lt;/a&gt;. So on my
&lt;a href=&#34;https://silverblue.fedoraproject.org/&#34;&gt;Fedora Silverblue&lt;/a&gt; computers, it works
out of the box and already fits in with the design philosophy behind Silverblue
(running all user apps in containers). Perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;mobile-support&#34;&gt;Mobile Support&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switching-to-bitwarden/bitwarden-ipad.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Bitwarden on Flathub Page&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switching-to-bitwarden/bitwarden-ipad.jpg&#34; style=&#34;float: right;width: 250px; max-width: 100%; padding: 5px 5px 10px 10px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months I have been &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/switched-to-joplin-notes/&#34;&gt;switching up the tools I
use&lt;/a&gt;, at least the ones I use &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/back-on-org-mode-for-work/&#34;&gt;outside of
work&lt;/a&gt;. The big driving force behind many of
these switches is better mobile support. While I still prefer to keep as much
data off of my phone as possible, there are some things I need to have on the
go. My password manager is unfortunately one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, as I start to test out different workloads on alternative devices
like my ipad, having a mobil-friendly work flow is a godsend. In fact, trying to
&lt;a href=&#34;../../post/setting-up-pass/&#34;&gt;setup pass&lt;/a&gt; on my iPad is what eventually frustrated
me enough to give Bitwarden a chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setup on both my phone and ipad was dead-simple. Install the app, and login.
Done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;wayland-friendly&#34;&gt;Wayland Friendly&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switching-to-bitwarden/wayland-logo.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Wayland logo&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switching-to-bitwarden/wayland-logo.png&#34; style=&#34;float: left; width: 250px; max-width: 100%; padding: 5px 15px 10px 10px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best features of my pass system was how well it was integrated with
my desktop environment. &lt;em&gt;However&lt;/em&gt;, I want to switch to wayland now more than
ever, but my pass desktop integration is the biggest blocker preventing me from
using it on my machines. I access pass using launcher applications like &lt;code&gt;dmenu&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;rofi&lt;/code&gt;&amp;hellip; but they do not function correctly in wayland. This forced me to
use &lt;code&gt;pass&lt;/code&gt; from a terminal window while in a wayland session. Bitwarden, at
least the limited GUI interactions I&amp;rsquo;ve used thus far, appears to work just
fine in wayland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;easier-to-share-expand&#34;&gt;Easier to share/expand&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, if my wife eventually wants to switch to Bitwarden, I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; we can
share our joint passwords with each other, even being on just the free personal
plan. If not, we can upgrade to the &amp;ldquo;family plan&amp;rdquo; which is currently $1/mo and
allows unlimited collections across 5 accounts &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; optional self hosting. For
shared family password management&amp;hellip; that&amp;rsquo;s a great deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-am-still-learning&#34;&gt;What I am still learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, this is where I list the few things that I &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t like&amp;rdquo;. However,
this still is all new and I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; the majority of my current issues are
solvable, but I just haven&amp;rsquo;t figured it out yet. So it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;ldquo;What I&amp;rsquo;m still
learning&amp;rdquo; section this time (•‿•) .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;better-keyboard-de-integration&#34;&gt;Better keyboard/DE integration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;main feature&lt;/em&gt; I still seem to be missing is better keyboard
support/integration with the desktop environment. The GUI app is nice, and
Bitwarden has &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better support for browser extensions and tools. Yet, I
haven&amp;rsquo;t found a good way to open up Bitwarden (give my master password),
search for an item, and copy the password&amp;hellip; all from the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;video style=&#34;max-width:100%;&#34; controls&gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;../../img/posts/setting-up-pass/passmenu_demo.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;movie.ogg&#34; type=&#34;video/ogg&#34;&gt;
Your browser does not support the video tag.
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;passmenu&lt;/code&gt; lets you easily search and select a pass item.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By comparison, &lt;code&gt;pass&lt;/code&gt; let me integrate with launchers like &lt;code&gt;dmenu&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;rofi&lt;/code&gt;
to efficiently grab my passwords which was &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt;. As mentioned a few
sections above, &lt;code&gt;passmenu&lt;/code&gt; unfortunately falls apart for me these days now that I am
mostly on wayland&amp;hellip; but I don&amp;rsquo;t need a full launcher. Honestly, all I
&lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; is the ability to copy a password (and maybe other fields) using my
keyboard once I have selected an item. I can already search using &lt;code&gt;ctrl-f&lt;/code&gt; +
&lt;code&gt;tab&lt;/code&gt;, and then &lt;code&gt;arrow&lt;/code&gt; my way down the list, but once there I cannot copy
unless I continue to tab through all the options. This is not efficient and
defeats the purpose of remaining on the keyboard in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a highly requested feature, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure someone has hacked &lt;em&gt;some
solution&lt;/em&gt; together&amp;hellip; I just have yet to find it&amp;hellip; or implement it myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is it. &lt;strong&gt;TLDR;&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve switched to Bitwarden and have been using it as my
main password manager for almost a month and I love it. It works on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;
my devices and doesn&amp;rsquo;t give me too many headaches. My only real complaint is
that I wish it had better keyboard support, but I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to figure
out a work-around eventually.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
