<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/</link>
    <description>Recent content on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © Ryan Himmelwright. Site created with Hugo</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 15:15:18 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/pages/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 15:15:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/pages/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a 26 year-old software developer working at a company in Walpole MA, that heavily utilizes Allegro Common Lisp for our applications. I primarily focus on our back-end build and deployment infrastructure, but as with any small company, I wear many hats and jump around assisting wherever I am needed.
Outside of work, I am an enthusiastic Linux user that loves learning about computers, programming languages (especially functional ones), and open source technologies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transitioning Server from Proxmox</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/server-transition-plan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/server-transition-plan/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been planning to move my server from Proxmox to just a normal server install, to give me more control over everything. However, I don&amp;rsquo;t want this to be like the wild west of servers, where it is basically just a desktop with a bunch of crap on it. I like how easy it is to spin up both containers and VMs, and then continue to monitor/manage everything.
So, I am creating a list of things I want to have at least somewhat figured out before officially making the switch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker Quick Start</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/docker-quickstart/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/docker-quickstart/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months (particularly over the holiday season), I started to
explore and learn several technologies I&amp;rsquo;ve had my eye on the last few years.
First on the list: &lt;a href=&#34;https://docker.io&#34;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;. These days, Docker has a massive
ecosystem surrounding it, and can take years to truly master. This post on the
other hand, will &lt;em&gt;hopefully&lt;/em&gt; help you get up and playing with docker containers in
just a few minutes. Lets get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living the Dock Life: My Thinkpad T470</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/my-t470/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/my-t470/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my previous post, I discussed how I sold off my System76 Bonobo laptop, and
 planned to replace it with a new computer. Well, I did&amp;hellip; awhile ago. For the
 last few months, I have been using a Lenovo T470 Thinkpad (with dock) as my new
 daily driver. Here are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sold My Bonobo</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/sold-my-bonobo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/sold-my-bonobo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last fall, I did something I didn&amp;rsquo;t think I would do anytime soon&amp;hellip;. I sold my
main workstation computer. Specifically, my System76 Bonobo Extreme laptop.
Several events over the last year have led me to the realization that my
&lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; computing &lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt; are drastically different than what they were when I
purchased the Bonobo in early 2015. This post will highlight some of those
realizations, and why I ultimately decided to sell my Bonobo laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Happy Hacking Keyboard Pro 2</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/new-hhkb-pro2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/new-hhkb-pro2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After years of using a Happy Hacking Keyboard Lite, I have &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; decided to splurge on a Happy Hacking Professional 2 keyboard. And I love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homelab</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/pages/homelab/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/pages/homelab/</guid>
      <description>This is a page where I maintain the status of the computers in my “Homelab”. I will list my current systems here (potentially with screenshots of my current desktop setup for my workstations).
Computers Ryan (Me)  My Home Workstation Area
 My Main Computer Setup (with lights on) (Kadabra)

- Kadabra (Main Laptop) T470 Thinkpad Intel i5-7200u [2.5 Ghz (3.1 Ghz Turbo), 2 Cores, 4 Threads] 16 GB RAM 500 GB Samsung EVO SSD 14&amp;quot; 1920x1080 IPS Display Solus  Periphery Thinkpad Ultra Dock 40A2 2 x 23.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Website Switched to Hugo</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/website-switched-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/website-switched-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;../website-transition-to-hugo/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I stated that &lt;em&gt;within a few days&lt;/em&gt;, I would officially generate and publish the website using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;. I then proceeded to publish &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; post using Hugo. Close enough. If I remember correctly, I ended that post listing off a few tasks that I wanted to complete &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; switching the site (oops). Well&amp;hellip; they&amp;rsquo;re complete &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;. Here&amp;rsquo;s how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transitioning Website to Hugo</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/website-transition-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/website-transition-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While I have loved using &lt;a href=&#34;http://cryogenweb.org&#34;&gt;Cryogen&lt;/a&gt; to create this website for over a year and a half now, I have started the transition to using another static website generator. Specifically, I have been experimenting with &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;. This post will detail why I am switching, what I have ported over thus far, and what still needs to be completed before generating the official site with hugo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Reverse SSH Tunnels</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/simple-reverse-ssh-tunnel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/simple-reverse-ssh-tunnel/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I was on vacation with my family. While I didn&amp;rsquo;t work a ton on personal projects, I was at least able to spend some time on my TunelBeacon project again. I will write a dedicated post about that project down the road when I am further along. Basically, it will be a simple GUI to create reverse ssh tunnels, that family and friends can startup in order grant me temporary access to their computer when they need support.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to Solus</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-to-solus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-to-solus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, that was faster than I expected. This past weekend, I wiped the Fedora installation on my main computer, and replaced it with Solus. My Fedora install broke, and I needed to use a Fedora Live CD to fix it. I thought that if I had to use a live CD to fix the issue, I might as well just do a clean install. With the idea of a clean install in my head&amp;hellip; I thought (possibly influenced by my recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/posts/dabbling-with-go/#motivation&#34;&gt;motivation&lt;/a&gt; to play with Go), that I might as well do the clean install with &lt;a href=&#34;solus-project.com/&#34;&gt;Solus&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dabbling with GO</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/dabbling-with-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/dabbling-with-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After spending most of this month&amp;rsquo;s dedicated learning time working on &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/posts/solus-to-fedora/&#34;&gt;system&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/posts/creating-a-git-remote/&#34;&gt;server&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/posts/issues-setting-up-ubiquiti-network/&#34;&gt;network&lt;/a&gt; activities,  I have been itching to start some home programming again. To motivate myself, I even considered dabbling with a new programming language&amp;hellip; and with very little internal debate, I decided to just &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org&#34;&gt;Gopher&lt;/a&gt; it (I&amp;rsquo;m so sorry).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating from Solus to Fedora for now</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/solus-to-fedora/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/solus-to-fedora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For awhile, I have been debating the idea of switching back to Fedora (from Solus). At least on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#alakazam&#34;&gt;main computer&lt;/a&gt;. First, let me state this right up front: I am still &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; satisfied with Solus. I think it is one of the best current Linux distros, and I want to still contribute to the project. However, there are a few reasons why Solus isn&amp;rsquo;t the best fit for my needs &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;, and I will highlight them below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a git Repo Remote</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/creating-a-git-remote/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/creating-a-git-remote/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For over a year or so, I have been using a
self-hosted &lt;a href=&#34;https://about.gitlab.com/&#34;&gt;Gitlab&lt;/a&gt; to host all of my private repos.
For a few months now, I have been meaning to migrate my Gitlab repos to bare, minimal
ones, hosted directly on a server. The majority of my code/configs are hosted
publicly on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/himmAllRight&#34;&gt;my Github&lt;/a&gt; page, and it really
doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to maintain a full Gitlab instance for the few (like&amp;hellip;2)
private repositories that I keep. Moving the git repos to new ones right on the server
is actually fairly simple. For such a simple process, all the guides I saw
online went way above and beyond what I needed. So, here are the &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; steps I
did to migrate my repos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Encountered Issues Setting Up Ubiquiti Network</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/issues-setting-up-ubiquiti-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/issues-setting-up-ubiquiti-network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past weekend, I setup my new ubiquiti network. It actually took up a good
portion of Sunday, because I ran into a few minor issues.
Fortunately/Unfortunately, these issues were mostly because it my first time
configuring this type of setup, and there was a lot of trial and error. The basic
network is now all configured and has been running great. It was a good day and I
learned a lot :). In fact, I am confident that if I had to start over from
scratch, the process would take me about 10-15 minutes. Just to be sure, I&amp;rsquo;m
 going to quickly jot down the major pain points I experienced my first time around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Home Network Ubiquiti Upgrade</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/upgrading-network-to-ubiquiti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/upgrading-network-to-ubiquiti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I went back to Pennsylvania for a week to attend my college swim
team reunion, and my brother&amp;rsquo;s high school graduation. While I was away, the
wifi-router Rebecca and I were using decided to die (of course). When I returned, I
setup our old router as a &lt;em&gt;temporary&lt;/em&gt; fix. It was terrible. So, I began
researching how I should upgrade our network. This time around, I am doing this
&lt;em&gt;correctly&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refreshing my i3 setup with i3blocks</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/started-using-i3blocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/started-using-i3blocks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The last couple of weeks I have shifted back to using the i3 window mangers. When I fired it up, my fingers danced across the keyboard, remembering all of the personalized keybindings I have cultivated in my i3 configuration over the years. It is a simple, beautiful setup&amp;hellip; well, beautiful minus one of the components. My i3status bar was looking rather bland and dated, especially compared some of the i3 setups posted by all the cool kids over at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/unixporn/&#34;&gt;/r/unixporn&lt;/a&gt;. I decided it was time for a refresh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exporting Proxmox VMs</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/exporting-proxmox-vms/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/exporting-proxmox-vms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For a long time I have been thinking about replacing my server&amp;rsquo;s proxmox install with vanilla Debian or CentOS, mostly for learning purposes. I would first setup zfs on the new system and import my existing data pools. Then, I would use either a system like ovrit or just plain kvm/lxc to run my VMs and containers. In order to do this though&amp;hellip; I have to first figure out how export my containers and VMs running in Proxmox. As it turns out&amp;hellip; exporting the VMs wasn&amp;rsquo;t very hard&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating the Pi Cluster with Ansible</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/updating-pi-cluster-with-ansible/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/updating-pi-cluster-with-ansible/</guid>
      <description>With Ansible configured on the Pi cluster, it is time to have it do something useful. When working with a clustered system, even the simplest tasks become tedious and time consuming. For example, updating the system. While I could manually update each of the 3 pi nodes, it is not scalable to 10 or 30 nodes, let alone hundreds or thousands. Tools like Ansible, make doing tasks such a supdating clustered systems, trivial again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configuring Ansible on the Pi Cluster</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/ansible-on-pi-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/ansible-on-pi-cluster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/posts/Setting-up-the-pi-cluster/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I pieced together my &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/pages/homelab/#cluster&#34;&gt;pi cluster&lt;/a&gt;, and installed variations of Ubuntu 16.04 Server on each of its nodes. With the cluster built, I quickly needed an easy way to maintain and interact with the system as a whole. This, is where &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ansible.com/&#34;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt; comes in. In this post, I will walk through the steps I took to setup Ansible on my Cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Up My Pi Cluster</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/setting-up-the-pi-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/setting-up-the-pi-cluster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a Raspberry Pi 2, a Raspberry Pi 3, and a Banana Pi. A while ago, I constructed a small tower to house my pi devices. Since then, I have additionally acquired a power source, and some CAT6 cable to connect them all up to a switch. I hope to use the Pis as a mini clustered environment, where I can learn (and play) with some of the &amp;ldquo;Devops&amp;rdquo; technologies/techniques out there. This post will briefly explain the initial setup of &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#cluster&#34;&gt;my cluster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ZFS Snapshot Backups to an External Drive with LUKS</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/zfs-backups-to-luks-external/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/zfs-backups-to-luks-external/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been using &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ZFS&#34;&gt;ZFS&lt;/a&gt; data pools to store data on &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#ninetales&#34;&gt;my server&lt;/a&gt; for some time now. As great as that is, I am ashamed to admit that I have not had a &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; backup system in place (raid/mirrors are not backup). I have a backup solution that I have attempted in the past, but ran into an issue and let it drift to the side. That changes now. It&amp;rsquo;s time to revisit my solution, and complete it to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LIA 1.0 Beta Released</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/lia-1-0-beta-released/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/lia-1-0-beta-released/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have released the 1.0 Beta version for a personal project of mine: the &lt;strong&gt;L&lt;/strong&gt;edger &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;mport &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;ssistant, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/himmALlRight/LIA/&#34;&gt;LIA&lt;/a&gt;. This post will talk briefly about the background of LIA, what it does, and explain the beta release.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Website Theme: Immutable</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/new-theme-immutable/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/new-theme-immutable/</guid>
      <description>When I first started using Cryogen to generate this website, I wanted to create a personalized theme. This desire led me to hack a the default theme into a mutant, which I boringly named &amp;ldquo;ryan1&amp;rdquo; (I anticipated it to be temporary). It looked like a relic, designed from when I first learned how to make a web page&amp;hellip; the early 2000&amp;rsquo;s. Like many all websites from that time, it was not mobile friendly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux from Scratch - SBUs and Binutils</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/lfs-sbus-and-binutils/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/lfs-sbus-and-binutils/</guid>
      <description>Well, after all of the preparation, we are ready to start compiling packages. This post cover compiling all the packages, but it will detail the first build of Binutils, which is arguably the most important package to compile. Why is Binutils so crucial? It determines the SBU time for your build system. What&amp;rsquo;s an SBU? Read on to find out!
SBUs A table of package SBUs and their predicted build time</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux from Scratch - Final Preparation Steps</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/lfs-final-preparation-steps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/lfs-final-preparation-steps/</guid>
      <description>Now that the repeated setup steps have been defined in my previous LFS post, there are a few more preparation steps to complete in order to start building the LFS system. I promise&amp;hellip; we will start compiling soon. If all goes well, this should be the last preparation post.
Downloading Sources When it comes down to it, Linux from scratch is just a bunch of packages, and the Linux kernel, all compiled from source and linked together.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux from Scratch - Repeated Setup Steps</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/lfs-repeated-setup-steps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/lfs-repeated-setup-steps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the Linux From Scratch process, there may be times when the build environment (computer, VM, chroot, whatever) must be restarted. If so, there are a few steps from the setup phase that have to be re-initialized. This post maps out those steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My New Dotfiles Management - Using GNU Stow</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/new-dotfiles/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/new-dotfiles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have maintained a &amp;ldquo;dotfiles&amp;rdquo; repository since I made my github account in 2013. However, overtime it became more of a post-apocalyptic wasteland, cluttered with remnants of obsolete configurations and scraps of scripts. It was no longer the pristine, culled, collection that I desired. I also did not have an efficient method of easily linking the files on a new system. I had to manually make symlinks for each dotfile. I knew there were &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better dotfiles setups out there, but I never got around to it. Until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux from Scratch - Getting Started</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/lfs-getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/lfs-getting-started/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I started using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.archlinux.org&#34;&gt;Arch Linux&lt;/a&gt; a while back, I learn about some of the internals of Linux quickly. Ever since then, I have considered building a Linux From Scratch by following the guidelines outlined in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linuxfromscratch.org&#34;&gt;the book&lt;/a&gt;. Based on my experience with Arch Linux, I&amp;rsquo;m sure that compiling a system from scratch will continue to teach me about Linux at a much deeper level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My New, Used x230</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/my-new-used-x230/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/my-new-used-x230/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I start to do more with a computer on the go, the netbooks I
previously used just are not cutting it anymore. They were great for minimal
use, but couldn&amp;rsquo;t run VMs, over-heated, and didn&amp;rsquo;t have great
battery life. Now that I am going to libraries and other locations to
work on personal and open source projects, I really needed a better
mobile pc setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying out snapd on Arch Linux</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/snapd-on-arch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/snapd-on-arch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The past few weeks I have been listening to all of the buzz about
Ubuntu &amp;ldquo;snaps&amp;rdquo;, but I just recently decided to try this new technology
out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying Out the Plasma 5 Desktop Environment</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/trying-out-plasma5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/trying-out-plasma5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After watching the continued development of the Plasma 5 desktop
environment from a distance, I determined I needed to give it another
try. It was just before version 5.6 was released, and the project
appeared to be finding it&amp;rsquo;s stride. Right up front, I want to come
clean and admit that I have never really liked the KDE/Plasma desktop
environment (more on that below). However, with that said&amp;hellip; I am still
using the plasma desktop on my main computer (months later, and
haven&amp;rsquo;t aborted yet**&amp;hellip;). Here are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Cryogen for Website</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/website-switched-to-cryogen/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/website-switched-to-cryogen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since resurrecting my personal website, I have experimented with several
static website generators. Thus far, I have tried
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kelvinh/org-page&#34;&gt;org-page&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://jekyllrb.com/&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;several&lt;/em&gt; times), and even (almost) made
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/himmAllRight/ryBlog/blob/master/org-blog.el&#34;&gt;my own emacs org-page solution&lt;/a&gt;. Now that I have
started using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://clojure.org/&#34;&gt;clojure&lt;/a&gt; programming language, I have come across
&lt;a href=&#34;http://cryogenweb.org/&#34;&gt;cryogen&lt;/a&gt;. As you may have already guessed, this site is now
being generated using cryogen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back On Arch, After Frantic Distro-hopping</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-on-arch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-on-arch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last few weeks, I have started my CS masters classes, and needed to setup a productive work environment on my portable laptop (&lt;a href=&#34;../../homelab&#34;&gt;abra&lt;/a&gt;). Also, while I love Fedora, the Nvidia stuff was being a pain on my main computer (&lt;a href=&#34;../../homelab&#34;&gt;alakazam&lt;/a&gt;), and I was looking for a replacement there as well. So, after a long, drawn out battle trying nearly all of my favorite Linux distros, I have found myself once again using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.archlinux.org/&#34;&gt;Arch Linux&lt;/a&gt; on both of my personal computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I asked my Groomsmen</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/how-i-asked-my-groomsmen/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/how-i-asked-my-groomsmen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last few months Rebecca (my Fiancee) and I have continued making progress on all the little tasks that we have to complete before our wedding. One of these tasks is asking our intended bridesmaids/groomsmen to be in the wedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25 Days of C</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/25-days-of-c/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/25-days-of-c/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I continue to learn more and more programming languages, I am somewhat ashamed to admit that I have yet to learn C. However, it is not because I am trying to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/focus-account/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/focus-account/</guid>
      <description>Notes on making a locked down account for Focusing:
 No Sudo Disabled su for the account using PAM I needed to add user groups to get the desktop stuff working Plan on using PAM more Need to figure out how to prevent ssh on other accounts to effectively do su  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/lxd-quickstart/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/lxd-quickstart/</guid>
      <description>Notes to eventually write an LXD/LXC quickstart post. Install On Solus, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find it, but then learned it was in the snap store, so I just install it from there and it seems to be working well :)
Images Launch Exec Issues Network I had a slight issue today where my containers didn&amp;rsquo;t have IP address, and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get them to. As such, they didn&amp;rsquo;t have an internet connection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/postgresql/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/postgresql/</guid>
      <description>Notes for Postgresql
Install Just installed from the repos at first&amp;hellip; was in Solus.
Pulling down for latest Went to website and got commands to pull down latest for Centos (I&amp;rsquo;m using an lxc container). The website has you choose what system you are on, and customizes the commands for you, which is nice :) .
Init DB sudo /usr/pgsql-10/bin/postgresql-10-setup initdb  I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure how to do this on Solus, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>