<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>wifi on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/wifi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in wifi on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/wifi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching to a Mesh Network</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/switching-to-mesh-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/switching-to-mesh-network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Not too long ago, I updated our home networking equipment to an Ubiqui
setup. However, we recently moved into a new house and I switched to a
mesh wifi network. No, the switch was not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; to increase wifi
coverage throughout the entire house. The real motivator
(ironically)&amp;hellip; was that I needed a better ethernet connection&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About two years ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/upgrading-network-to-ubiquiti/&#34;&gt;replaced my Linksys wifi
router(s)&lt;/a&gt;
with the tiny-but-mighty &lt;a href=&#34;https://store.ui.com/products/edgerouter-x&#34;&gt;Ubiquity Edge Router
X&lt;/a&gt;, paired with an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ui.com/unifi/unifi-ap-ac-lite/&#34;&gt;Ubiqui AP AC
lite&lt;/a&gt; wifi access point. I loved
it. It handled our web traffic flawlessly, and unlike the previous Linksys
routers, I never had to randomly restart it. It just worked for months on end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the setup &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much in fact, that while I was thrilled to
have a Google Fiber internet connection when we moved to Durham NC
last year, I was a little sad that setting up the edgerouter on the
fiber modem required a little bit of tweaking. I looked into it
but ultimately decided that figuring it out wasn&amp;rsquo;t worth the hassle
for the short period of time which we&amp;rsquo;d likely live in the
apartment. So, I reluctantly used the Google provided box which worked &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;we-moved&#34;&gt;We Moved&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Google fiber was indeed short lived, as my wife and I just moved
into a house this past month. When working with Spectrum to setup our
internet (&lt;em&gt;yea&amp;hellip; I know&lt;/em&gt;), we discovered that while there were coax
plugs in both the living room and master bedroom, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t
actually find any hook-ups to connect the house to the external cable/internet
service line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;cable-line-in-bedroom&#34;&gt;Cable-line in Bedroom&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After searching with multiple techs, we decided just to have them
drill a line into the master bedroom (which is at the back of the
house and allows the connection box to be with the other utility
meters). Our house isn&amp;rsquo;t massive, and having the router in the bedroom
works well enough, except for &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have several servers and desktop computers that &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; an
ethernet connection, either because they don&amp;rsquo;t have wifi cards, and/or
because I use Wake-On-Lan with them. This means that I need an
ethernet connection in my office&amp;hellip; at the front of the house. Now
that the only ethernet router/switch was in the bedroom, and the rest
of the house relied on wifi&amp;hellip;  I needed to figure something out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;power-line-issues&#34;&gt;Power-line Issues&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In past apartments, I had used power-line ethernet adapters to extend
ethernet from a router in a different room to my computers. The speeds
weren&amp;rsquo;t great, but then again, neither was our connection so it wasn&amp;rsquo;t
a huge problem. This time though, I ran some tests&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, while it &lt;em&gt;worked&lt;/em&gt;, this setup wasn&amp;rsquo;t ideal. More importantly, I
found out a few days later there was a massive problem that
&lt;em&gt;completely prevents&lt;/em&gt; me from being able to use the power-line
adapters. The house&amp;rsquo;s electrical panel is between the master bedroom
and the office, which is the worst case scenario. One day, we turned
on the washing machine and our internet went down. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t just the
power-line connections that were effected&amp;hellip; the entire network, wifi
and router was essentially being
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denial-of-service_attack&#34;&gt;dos&amp;rsquo;d&lt;/a&gt; by the
washer. When I unplugged the power-line adapters, it worked
again. Power-line was not an option anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;mesh-network&#34;&gt;Mesh Network&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wondered if there was another way to connect ethernet in my office,
beyond having to drop cat6 cable across the house. I looked into wifi
bridges, but most of the devices were designed for large distances,
and ones for home use were not much better than a power-line adapters
when it came to performance/reliability. While looking at wifi
bridges, a thought occurred to me&amp;hellip; would a mesh network system work?
If the satellite devices had ethernet ports&amp;hellip; maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;netgear-orbi&#34;&gt;Netgear Orbi&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started researching wifi mesh networks, the orbi systems were consistently
rated the highest, and people generally reported that they experienced &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;
performance. When I dug further into it, I learned that this high level of performance was
likely due to the orbi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netgear.com/landings/mesh-network/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;tri-band wifi
technology&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically, in addition to the normal 2.4 and 5 Ghz network bands, the orbi
system has &lt;em&gt;a second 5 Ghz band&lt;/em&gt; dedicated to connecting the orbi router and
satilites together. In other words&amp;hellip; a dedicated wifi bridge :D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started looking at the orbi hardware and saw that there were several
types of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netgear.com/orbi/products.aspx#filter=.satellites-indoor%2C.satellites%2C.satellites-outdoor%2C.satellites&#34;&gt;satellites&lt;/a&gt;.
Some were just wall plugs, but a few had 2-4 ethernet
ports. Perfect. Realizing this, I ended up ordering the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netgear.com/orbi/rbk50.aspx&#34;&gt;RBK50&lt;/a&gt; system, which
contained a 4-port orbi router, and a 4-port satellite. My hope was that
I could set up the router in the master bedroom with our modem, and
then put the satellite in my office on the other end of the house.
I could then connect my hardwired devices, or even a network switch, into the
ethernet ports on the satellite. Problem sovled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have ordered and setup my orbi system, and will write a review post
about it sometime in the future. This post&amp;rsquo;s intention was mostly to
just explain &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I ended up getting an orbi system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people have started to use home wifi &amp;ldquo;mesh&amp;rdquo; systems because they
provide a simple solution to cover an entire house with a strong wifi
connection. While this is a great &lt;em&gt;bonus&lt;/em&gt; I get from having the mesh
system, as this post demonstrates, my &lt;em&gt;main&lt;/em&gt; purpose for purchasing
the orbi was to be a solid &amp;ldquo;ethernet over wifi&amp;rdquo; system in the new
house. So far&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s working great.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Encountered Issues Setting Up Ubiquiti Network</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/issues-setting-up-ubiquiti-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/issues-setting-up-ubiquiti-network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past weekend, I setup my new ubiquiti network. It actually took up a good
portion of Sunday, because I ran into a few minor issues.
Fortunately/Unfortunately, these issues were mostly because it my first time
configuring this type of setup, and there was a lot of trial and error. The basic
network is now all configured and has been running great. It was a good day and I
learned a lot :). In fact, I am confident that if I had to start over from
scratch, the process would take me about 10-15 minutes. Just to be sure, I&amp;rsquo;m
going to quickly jot down the major pain points I experienced my first time around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;trouble-connecting-to-the-edgerouter-x-for-initial-setup&#34;&gt;Trouble Connecting to the EdgeRouter-x for Initial Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The edgerouter needed to be directly connected to a computer during its initial
setup, to make the EdgeOS configuration wizard accessible. The
instructions clearly stated to connect an ethernet cable from my laptop to the
&lt;code&gt;eth0/POE&lt;/code&gt; port on the edgerouter, but I guess I didn&amp;rsquo;t believe them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I plugged the ethernet cable from my modem into &lt;code&gt;eth0&lt;/code&gt;, and my computer
to &lt;code&gt;eth1&lt;/code&gt;. That didn&amp;rsquo;t work. However, once I &lt;em&gt;properly&lt;/em&gt; connected the devices (and
manually set a static IP on my laptop, &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.2&lt;/code&gt; for example), I was able to access
the configuration page in my browser via &lt;code&gt;https://192.168.1.1&lt;/code&gt; (don&amp;rsquo;t forget
the &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;https&lt;/em&gt;). Lesson Learned: manuals are (&lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt;) not out to get you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;setting-up-poe-and-connecting-the-ap&#34;&gt;Setting up POE and Connecting the AP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not actually an issue I encountered, but rather a confusion. I was unsure what the best setup for
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_over_Ethernet&#34;&gt;POE&lt;/a&gt; hardware was. At
first, I had the POE adaptor connected between the edgerouter and the AP,
because I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure if it could optimally power both devices. I found
an
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f7FeYsJqotc&amp;amp;list=PLDBkup9c8YMgZaE50hAjP7rbbVriTlyQf&amp;amp;index=1&#34;&gt;informative guide&lt;/a&gt; that
indicated that the POE adaptor could indeed power both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scheme&#34; data-lang=&#34;scheme&#34;&gt;Modem  --
        |
         --&amp;gt; POE Adaptor --&amp;gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;*eth0*&lt;/span&gt;)  edgerouter-x  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;*eth4*&lt;/span&gt;) --&amp;gt; AP Lite
        |
Power  --
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digram describing the correct link up&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I swapped the cables all around, I had to go into the router
configuration and enable the POE for &lt;code&gt;eth4&lt;/code&gt;. Afterwards, the AP lit up,
indicating that it was connected and powered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;issues-linkingconfiguring-the-ap&#34;&gt;Issues linking/configuring the AP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the problem I spent the most time on. I had to install the
configuration software for the Ubiquiti access point, but the &amp;ldquo;Linux binary&amp;rdquo; was
a .deb, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like extracting the contents of the package so that I
could install it on Solus (yet). So instead, I spun up a few Ubuntu VMs to try
it out, but I over-looked the fact that VMs on my laptop use a
different subnet (192.168.&lt;strong&gt;122&lt;/strong&gt;. *) for the virtual network. I had hoped that
because the VM&amp;rsquo;s network was routed through my laptop, which was connected
directly to the edgerouter, it would still be able to see the access point.
Regardless&amp;hellip; the AP couldn&amp;rsquo;t see the VM and vice versa. Finally, I admitted
that the issues were most likely caused by the 192.168.122.* IP address that the VM was
assigned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By this point, I had also learned that the Linux software is more of a server
service, and not a GUI desktop application. So, I concluded that spinning up a
dedicated VM on my server to host the wifi controller was worth it. Virtual
machines hosted on my server automatically get configured on the main
subnet, so it also resolved my issue. I was able to detect and configure the
access point immediately. This setup made more sense anyway, as I can always
connect to the AP controller by going to the VM&amp;rsquo;s IP on my browser,  just like I
can with my router.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that was all of my setup &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;issues&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;. There was nothing I would consider to
be an actual &lt;em&gt;issue&lt;/em&gt;, just some confusions of an Ubiquiti/POE first-timer. Like
I stated earlier, I am sure I could redo the setup in about 15 minutes without any
issues&amp;hellip; 10 now that I recorded everything in the post!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Home Network Ubiquiti Upgrade</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/upgrading-network-to-ubiquiti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/upgrading-network-to-ubiquiti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I went back to Pennsylvania for a week to attend my college swim
team reunion, and my brother&amp;rsquo;s high school graduation. While I was away, the
wifi-router Rebecca and I were using decided to die (of course). When I returned, I
setup our old router as a &lt;em&gt;temporary&lt;/em&gt; fix. It was terrible. So, I began
researching how I should upgrade our network. This time around, I am doing this
&lt;em&gt;correctly&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The router that died was a Linksys WRT 1900. When I got home, I setup our old
router as a temporary fix. It&amp;rsquo;s a very basic Linksys E1200. After using it for
just a few hours, I remembered why I hated it so much. It is slower than a
snail, and seems to stop working each day or so, requiring me to unplug and
re-plug it daily (I think it is something with DHCP. It keeps trying to reassign
IPs to devices, and then doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to understand how to accept their requests
afterwards). Thus, the more &lt;em&gt;temporary&lt;/em&gt; this solution was, the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I am redoing our network setup, I want to do it &lt;em&gt;properly&lt;/em&gt; this time,
splitting out the router from the wireless access point using &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; hardware and
software. My plan is to get an ubiquity edge-router-x, and pair it with an Ubiquiti
wireless access point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally I wanted to build a small pfsense box to use as a router, but after
digging a little deeper and doing some research, I saw that the EdgeRouter would
more than meet my needs and is a great start to a network upgrade. Additionally,
at $50 (USD), it truly is a great deal. As for the wireless access point, I was
always considering an UniFi device, and I thought the EdgeRouter should
pair rather seamlessly, considering both products are made by Ubiquiti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From what I read, the EdgeRouter is a great router with an okay firewall, while
pfsense is an amazing firewall that can do routing. So, if I want to dig more
into pfsense in the future, I can still set up a firewall box, and connect it in front of
the router.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Modem --&amp;gt; pfsense --&amp;gt; EdgeRouter-x -&amp;gt; devices
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;So&amp;hellip; I think I&amp;rsquo;ve finalized my decision and will purchase the items soon. I
will update when I get them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update (06/24/2017): I have followed through with this
purchase, and the items arrived from Amazon. Expect a post or two about my
experience setting them up (and yes, I added this update before actually
publishing this post)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
