<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gnome on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/gnome/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gnome on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/gnome/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My Three Required Gnome Extensions</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/three-required-gnome-extensions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/three-required-gnome-extensions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnome.org&#34;&gt;Gnome&lt;/a&gt; is the default desktop environment for many
Linux distributions, including my distro of choice,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://getfedora.org&#34;&gt;Fedora&lt;/a&gt;. When Gnome 3 was first released, I had to
install a bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;https://extensions.gnome.org&#34;&gt;extensions&lt;/a&gt; to get a
functional experience. These days, between becoming more familar with the Gnome
workflow, and the Gnome team ironing out the rougher edges of the DE, I don&amp;rsquo;t
need nearly as many extensions to get going. However, there are still three
which I do not think I could live without.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gnome-extensions&#34;&gt;Gnome Extensions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/three-required-gnome-extensions/gnome-extensions.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Gnome Extensions Website&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/three-required-gnome-extensions/gnome-extensions.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Gnome Extensions website&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gnome extensions are installable enhancements to the Gnome desktop environment.
They are obtained by going to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://extensions.gnome.org&#34;&gt;gnome extensions
website&lt;/a&gt; with a supported browser, installing the
plugin, and switching the tab of desired extensions to &amp;ldquo;On&amp;rdquo;. Extensions can
be further configured using the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.gnome.org/action/show/Apps/Tweaks?action=show&amp;amp;redirect=Apps%2FGnomeTweakTool&#34;&gt;Tweaks&lt;/a&gt;
desktop application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-must-have-3&#34;&gt;My Must-Have 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;caffeine&#34;&gt;Caffeine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first required extension is Caffeine, which adds a little coffee cup icon to
the status bar. When the cup is empty, the system behaves as normal. However,
when clicked, the cup &amp;lsquo;fills up&amp;rsquo; and caffeine will prevent the system from
suspending the display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is useful when giving presentations to stop the screen from dimming off
during longer slides, or during Q&amp;amp;A time. I also use this if I have a secondary
computer displaying information, to prevent it from repeatedly logging me out. I
can temporarily pause my sleep settings, without having to actually go
in and change them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;top-icons-plus&#34;&gt;Top Icons Plus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/three-required-gnome-extensions/top-bars.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Gnome top bars with and without extensions enabled&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/three-required-gnome-extensions/top-bars.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The right side of my top bar, without extensions (top),
and with the &lt;em&gt;caffeine&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;top icons plus&lt;/em&gt; extensions enabled (bottom)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many applications still expect an icon to be visible, in a task bar, where the
application can to store settings in. However, Gnome will often hide these
icons, making them less accessible. Top icons plus moves these icons back to
the top status bar, like many people expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use this extension so that I can more easily see and control applications on
my system which &lt;em&gt;assume&lt;/em&gt; the icons to be visible. Top Icons plus also allows me
to choose where on the bar I want them located (left, center, right). I
usually just set them to the &amp;lsquo;right&amp;rsquo; side of the screen, with all the other
junk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sound-input-output-device-chooser&#34;&gt;Sound Input &amp;amp; Output Device Chooser&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/three-required-gnome-extensions/drop-downs.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Dropdown Menu, with and without sound device chooser&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/three-required-gnome-extensions/drop-downs.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Top bar dropdown menu, with (right) and without (left) the
&lt;em&gt;Sound Input &amp;amp; Output Device Chooser&lt;/em&gt; extension enabled&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the &lt;em&gt;Sound Input &amp;amp; Output Device Chooser&lt;/em&gt; plugin adds a drop-down menu
to the top bar where audio input and output devices can be easily switched.
Otherwise, I usually need to do this from the &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; section of the system
settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone that switches between speakers and headphones all day, has 100%
remote meetings, and usually more than one microphone device connected to their
computer, this is probably my most &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt; plug-in. It makes my life
easier, and allows me to react quicker in a meeting if I notice that an
incorrect audio device is selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I still use other extensions, these are the big three. I think default gnome
has gotten surprisingly usable, but I would probably struggle to use it if
these extensions were no longer available to me.  So, to the Gnome team&amp;hellip;
please consider adding the functionality of these items as defaults in Gnome.
If not, I understand. However, if that is the case&amp;hellip; Gnome community, please
don&amp;rsquo;t let these extensions become deprecated! Thanks :)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
