<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Software on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/software/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Software on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/software/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying Out Seafile</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/trying-out-seafile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/trying-out-seafile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In college, I mostly used Dropbox to handle all of my file syncing needs. As I
approached graduation, I setup an Owncloud droplet (which is now a Nextcloud
instance) to supplant my Dropbox usage. While it has worked fairly well, I&amp;rsquo;ve
been watching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seafile.com/en/home/&#34;&gt;seafile&lt;/a&gt; from a distance the
last few years, but haven&amp;rsquo;t taken the time to try it out. I have now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;seafile&#34;&gt;Seafile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-out-seafile/seafilelogo.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-out-seafile/seafilelogo.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 95%; float: left; margin: 0px 15px 0px 0px;&#34; alt=&#34;Docker ps&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Seafile Logo&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As stated on their website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seafile is an enterprise file hosting platform with high reliability and
performance. Put files on your own server. Sync and share files across
different devices, or access all the files as a virtual disk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While self-defined as an &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;enterprise&lt;/em&gt; file hosting platform&amp;rdquo;, there is a
Community Edition that is &lt;em&gt;Free &amp;amp; Open Source&lt;/em&gt;.. which is exactly how I like my
software. So lets get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setup&#34;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to a Nextcloud configuration, to get seafile up and running, a server
 component is first installed. Afterwards, clients connect to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;server&#34;&gt;Server&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The countless number of configurations seafile supports may make setting up the
server component for the first time a bit intimidating. There are several
database back-ends (SQLite, MySQL&amp;hellip;), web servers (Nginx, Apache), and
advanced options (Memcached, LDAP, etc) which can be selected. However, the
seafile developers &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; provide an &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/haiwen/seafile-server-installer&#34;&gt;installation
script&lt;/a&gt; to easily install
both the Pro and Community editions under Linux. Which is what I used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;download&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to download the server application. A link for the
install package can found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seafile.com/en/download/#server&#34;&gt;partway down the download
page&lt;/a&gt;. After Downloading, extract
the contents of the package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;wget https://download.seadrive.org/seafile-server_6.2.5_x86-64.tar.gz
tar xf seafile-server*.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the extracted directory, there are several &lt;code&gt;setup-seafile-*.sh*&lt;/code&gt; scripts.
I just used the basic &lt;code&gt;setup-seafile.sh&lt;/code&gt; one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;dependencies&#34;&gt;Dependencies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-out-seafile/ubuntu-logo.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img
src=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-out-seafile/ubuntu-logo.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%; float: right; margin: 5px 10px 10px 10px;&#34; alt=&#34;Ubuntu Logo&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on which setup script it used, and the state of the host machine,
there may be some missing dependencies. While I am sure there is a nice list of
the required dependencies posted &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip; I didn&amp;rsquo;t look for it. If I am
being completely honest&amp;hellip; I just kept repeatedly running the script, and
installed whichever package it yelled at me for each time. Eventually, the install
worked. On my fresh install of Ubuntu 16.04 server, this meant
installing the following dependency packages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;python-setuptools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;python-imaging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sqlite3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that on an Ubuntu 16.04 server, a simple &lt;code&gt;sudo apt install python-setuptools
python-imaging sqlite3&lt;/code&gt; should do the trick&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;install-script&#34;&gt;Install Script&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the dependencies installed, the script should run through without screaming
for missing packages. However, it &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; ask for a few pieces of information
including &lt;em&gt;server-name&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;server-ip/domain&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;data-dir&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;fileserver port&lt;/em&gt;
to install the fileserver component. Answer accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-out-seafile/seahub-web.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-out-seafile/seahub-web.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; float: left; margin: 0px 15px 0px 0px;&#34; alt=&#34;Docker ps&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Seafile Web Client, Seahub&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After configuring the fileserver, the script will flow right into configuring
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/haiwen/seahub&#34;&gt;Seahub&lt;/a&gt;, the web interface that sits on top
of the fileserver. This part is less needy, and will only require an &lt;em&gt;[Enter]&lt;/em&gt;
press to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end, the script should display useful information about how to
start/stop/reset the servers, as well as what ports each part is running on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;run-start&#34;&gt;Run &amp;amp; Start&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting the servers is done by doing what the script says&amp;hellip; run the
following commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;./seafile.sh start
./seahub.sh start&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the servers running, it may be necessary to configure the firewall to allow
their ports. On Ubuntu 16.04:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;sudo ufw allow &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;8000&lt;/span&gt;/tcp
sudo ufw allow &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;8082&lt;/span&gt;/tcp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. With any luck, clients should be able to connect to the server
(assuming the server is reachable from the client computer&amp;hellip; but that&amp;rsquo;s a
lesson for another day).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: The first time seahub is run, it will need to setup an admin account. So
while it was nice and considerate in the last step&amp;hellip; it will insist on being
supplied a username (email) and password for the new admin account. Again, just
comply.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;client&#34;&gt;Client&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seafile desktop client was trivial to install. It was in the Solus repos, so
I just needed to run &lt;code&gt;sudo eopkg it seafile-client&lt;/code&gt;, and I was done. I also
installed it on my work computers (which unfortunately runs Windows 10), and
even that was simple. I just downloaded and installed the Windows &amp;ldquo;Desktop
Syncing Client&amp;rdquo; at the top of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seafile.com/en/download/&#34;&gt;download
page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-thoughts&#34;&gt;My Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-out-seafile/seafile-client.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img
src=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-out-seafile/seafile-client.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%; float: right; margin: 0px 0px 0px 0px;&#34; alt=&#34;Seafile Desktop Client&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using seafile as a syncing solution for the past few weeks. After
the initial setup, it has been rather uneventful&amp;hellip; which is a good thing. It
just runs in the background, and I don&amp;rsquo;t really think about it. Exactly what you
want with a syncing solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, I haven&amp;rsquo;t fully dug into all of the details of the application
yet. So, if I incorrectly critique something due to my own ignorance that
simply isn&amp;rsquo;t true, I apologize in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-like&#34;&gt;What I Like&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Desktop Client&lt;/strong&gt; - The desktop client is simple. It responds quickly, and is
a nice little command center where I can view how seafile is configured on each
individual system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Select &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; Libraries to sync&lt;/strong&gt; - Seafile libraries allow me to sync only
what I need. Nextcloud had this feature, but it was implemented a little differently. I
had to go to the &lt;code&gt;Nextcloud&lt;/code&gt; folder in the client UI, and then check/uncheck all
of the sub-folders I wanted to sync on my machine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pick &lt;em&gt;where each&lt;/em&gt; libraries sync&lt;/strong&gt; - Even better than being able to pick
&lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; libraries to sync, is having the power to choose &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; each one will
reside. In seafile, the location of each library is completely independent.
For example, I can sync my &lt;code&gt;work&lt;/code&gt; library to &lt;code&gt;~/Documents/Work/&lt;/code&gt;, my &lt;code&gt;Music&lt;/code&gt;
to &lt;code&gt;~/Music&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;emacs&lt;/code&gt; to
&lt;code&gt;~/Documents/Programming/Editors/why/so/many/diectories/emacs/&lt;/code&gt;. On another
computer, I may choose to only sync my &lt;code&gt;work&lt;/code&gt; library to &lt;code&gt;~/Desktop/work&lt;/code&gt; (It
doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be the same across computers). I love this. It lets seafile &lt;em&gt;integrate&lt;/em&gt; with my
workflow, rather than forcing me to make &lt;em&gt;it be&lt;/em&gt; my workflow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encrypted Libraries&lt;/strong&gt; - When creating a new library, it is possible to
make an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seafile.com/en/help/encrypted_libraries/&#34;&gt;encrypted
one&lt;/a&gt;. These libraries
use client-side, end-to-end encryption and require a password. The file
&lt;em&gt;contents&lt;/em&gt; (Note: not directory or file &lt;em&gt;names&lt;/em&gt;) are encrypted on the client
side, and not on the server. This means that even the server admin cannot access the file
contents on the server. This is a feature I&amp;rsquo;d like to see in more applications.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-out-seafile/encrypt-library.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img
src=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-out-seafile/encrypt-library.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%; align: center; float: center; margin: 0px 0px 0px 0px;&#34; alt=&#34;Docker ps&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;When syncing an encrypted library, a password must be entered.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fast Sync&lt;/strong&gt; - I only have anecdotal evidence, but the syncing in seafile
&lt;em&gt;feels fast&lt;/em&gt;. Files seem to pull down very quickly, and setting up my
libraries on a new device doesn&amp;rsquo;t take a very long time. I might have to
actually &lt;em&gt;measure&lt;/em&gt; if it&amp;rsquo;s any better than something like nextcloud, but if I&amp;rsquo;m
happy&amp;hellip; does it really &lt;em&gt;matter&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-don-t-like&#34;&gt;What I Don&amp;rsquo;t Like&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Folders/Nested libraries&lt;/strong&gt; - As far as I can tell, I don&amp;rsquo;t think it is
possible to organize seafile libraries with folders, or a nested library
structure. Admittedly, this is one of those areas that I haven&amp;rsquo;t had to look
too much into yet. However, as I start to increase my seafile usage and the
number of my libraries increases, I could see this being a feature I&amp;rsquo;d really
enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phone Sync Tricky&lt;/strong&gt; - The phone sync (specifically auto photo upload) was
tricky to get working at first. After setting it up, it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to work,
or at least not as promptly as nextcloud does. I took a few photos to test it
out today, it seemed to work &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt;, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think it started syncing
right away. Right now, I don&amp;rsquo;t 100% trust it to work without me thinking
about it. Hopefully this improves with time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;future-plans&#34;&gt;Future Plans&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize, I have been loving seafile, and I think I have only scratched the
surface. I haven&amp;rsquo;t even tried playing with features like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seafile.com/en/help/snapshot/&#34;&gt;History and
Snapshots&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seafile.com/en/help/search/&#34;&gt;Full Text File
Search&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seafile.com/en/help/share/&#34;&gt;Sharing
File&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seafile.com/en/help/file_lock/&#34;&gt;Locking
Files&lt;/a&gt; yet. My plan is to continue
experimenting a bit more, and then switch to it as my main syncing system when I
redo my main server setup in a couple of weeks. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t given seafile a
try recently, I recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
