<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Devops on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/devops/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Devops on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/devops/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a CI/CD &#39;Draft&#39; Website with Jenkins (and Hugo)</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/draft-website-with-jenkins/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/draft-website-with-jenkins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The last few months I have been working more with the open source
automation server, &lt;a href=&#34;https://jenkins.io/&#34;&gt;Jenkins&lt;/a&gt;. While digging into
it, I have been thinking of ways to improve my home build
environment. One idea, was to utilize Jenkins to automatically build
and deploy a &amp;ldquo;draft&amp;rdquo; website, so I can stage new posts/website change
on my home network, before publishing it to the &amp;ldquo;production&amp;rdquo;
website. Here is how that idea was Instantiated&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker Quick Start</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/docker-quickstart/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/docker-quickstart/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months (particularly over the holiday season), I started to
explore and learn several technologies I&amp;rsquo;ve had my eye on the last few years.
First on the list: &lt;a href=&#34;https://docker.io&#34;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;. These days, Docker has a massive
ecosystem surrounding it, and can take years to truly master. This post on the
other hand, will &lt;em&gt;hopefully&lt;/em&gt; help you get up and playing with docker containers in
just a few minutes. Lets get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating the Pi Cluster with Ansible</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/updating-pi-cluster-with-ansible/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/updating-pi-cluster-with-ansible/</guid>
      <description>With Ansible configured on the Pi cluster, it is time to have it do something useful. When working with a clustered system, even the simplest tasks become tedious and time consuming. For example, updating the system. While I could manually update each of the 3 pi nodes, it is not scalable to 10 or 30 nodes, let alone hundreds or thousands. Tools like Ansible, make doing tasks such a supdating clustered systems, trivial again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configuring Ansible on the Pi Cluster</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/ansible-on-pi-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/ansible-on-pi-cluster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/posts/Setting-up-the-pi-cluster/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I pieced together my &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/pages/homelab/#cluster&#34;&gt;pi cluster&lt;/a&gt;, and installed variations of Ubuntu 16.04 Server on each of its nodes. With the cluster built, I quickly needed an easy way to maintain and interact with the system as a whole. This, is where &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ansible.com/&#34;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt; comes in. In this post, I will walk through the steps I took to setup Ansible on my Cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Up My Pi Cluster</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/setting-up-the-pi-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/setting-up-the-pi-cluster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a Raspberry Pi 2, a Raspberry Pi 3, and a Banana Pi. A while ago, I constructed a small tower to house my pi devices. Since then, I have additionally acquired a power source, and some CAT6 cable to connect them all up to a switch. I hope to use the Pis as a mini clustered environment, where I can learn (and play) with some of the &amp;ldquo;Devops&amp;rdquo; technologies/techniques out there. This post will briefly explain the initial setup of &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#cluster&#34;&gt;my cluster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>