<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thinkpad on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/thinkpad/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thinkpad on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/thinkpad/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Authorizing Thunderbolt 3 on Fedora Plasma</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/fedora-kde-tb3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/fedora-kde-tb3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After buying a &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/new-2019-16inch-mbp/&#34;&gt;16&amp;rdquo; MacBook Pro&lt;/a&gt; the other month,
I&amp;rsquo;ve been using a Thunderbolt 3 hub to connect it to my periphery devices.
Luckily, in addition to the macbook, I am able to use the hub with my my work
laptop when working from home. Normally, it works fine. However, last week I
reformatted the work laptop with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://spins.fedoraproject.org/kde/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;KDE Plasma&lt;/em&gt; spin&lt;/a&gt; of
Fedora Workstation 31&amp;hellip; and my TB3 hub stopped playing nicely with it.
Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-issue&#34;&gt;The Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to a NVIDIA Quadro M1000M in my lenovo P50 work laptop, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using
Gnome with Wayland, because that combination seems to have the least amount of
annoying trade-offs. While doing a system refresh, I figured I would see if
things are any different with a clean Fedora 31 Plasma install (they weren&amp;rsquo;t,
but that&amp;rsquo;s beyond this post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Booting into the live cd, and later the installed system, I noticed that my
Thunderbolt 3 hub did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; work while I was in Plasma. That was fine. I
expected it really, because for security reasons Linux distros tend to disable
thunderbolt ports by default.  In gnome, there are now settings to authorize
it (which I guess I had done on my previous install, and forgot about).  In
Plasma however, I needed to install and configure &lt;code&gt;bolt&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bolt&#34;&gt;Bolt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Fedora, &lt;code&gt;bolt&lt;/code&gt; is in the repos (at least in Fedora 31+), so installing it is
easy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo dnf install bolt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once &lt;code&gt;bolt&lt;/code&gt; is installed, it isn&amp;rsquo;t a bad idea to check to make sure it is
running: &lt;code&gt;sudo systemctl bolt&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the status shows that it isn&amp;rsquo;t running for some reason, it can be started
using &lt;code&gt;systemctl start bolt&lt;/code&gt;. Check the status again, and if it it &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; is not
running&amp;hellip; sorry?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With bolt installed, the command &lt;code&gt;boltctl&lt;/code&gt; is available to use. The base command will
show information about attached thunderbolt devices. To see more &lt;code&gt;boltctl&lt;/code&gt;
commands, run &lt;code&gt;boltctl --help&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;authorizing&#34;&gt;Authorizing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; the thunderbolt 3 device, it needs to be authorized. To
authorize a device, first use a plain &lt;code&gt;boltctl&lt;/code&gt; command to get the &lt;code&gt;uuid&lt;/code&gt; of
the device. Next, call &lt;code&gt;boltctl authorize&lt;/code&gt; using the &lt;code&gt;uuid&lt;/code&gt; to authorize it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;boltctl authorize &amp;lt;UUID HERE&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The device should now be authorized. When I authorized mine, some of my devices
started showing up automatically, while others needed to be disconnected and
replugged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;enrolling&#34;&gt;Enrolling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authorizing a device enables it to be used, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t guarantee persistence.
While this may be desired to grant &lt;em&gt;temporary&lt;/em&gt; authorization to a device, many
users tend want their device to &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; work, without having to manually
authorize it. In this case, the device should be &lt;em&gt;enrolled&lt;/em&gt; (like &lt;code&gt;systemctl enable&lt;/code&gt;).
Simply call &lt;code&gt;boltctl enroll&lt;/code&gt;, with the device UUID:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;boltctl enroll &amp;lt;UUID HERE&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once enrolled, the device&amp;rsquo;s UUID will be recorded and added to a database. By
default, the device will now automatically be authorized whenever it is
connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. While the solution isn&amp;rsquo;t very difficult, it can be frustrating to
figure out when it appears that the thunderbolt device simply is not working.
Regardless, I&amp;rsquo;m glad that I now know about &lt;code&gt;bolt&lt;/code&gt; and how to use it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living the Dock Life: My Thinkpad T470</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/my-t470/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/my-t470/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my previous post, I discussed how I sold off my System76 Bonobo laptop, and
planned to replace it with a new computer. Well, I did&amp;hellip; awhile ago. For the
last few months, I have been using a Lenovo T470 Thinkpad (with dock) as my new
daily driver. Here are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-choice&#34;&gt;The Choice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notebookcheck.net/Lenovo-ThinkPad-T470-Core-i5-Full-HD-Notebook-Review.198130.0.html&#34;&gt;T470&lt;/a&gt;
is the 14&amp;rdquo; model of Lenovo&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;business&amp;rdquo; laptop lineup. The T470 series actually
has several variants itself, including the &amp;ldquo;high end&amp;rdquo;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notebookcheck.net/Lenovo-ThinkPad-T470s-Core-i7-WQHD-Laptop-Review.200880.0.html&#34;&gt;T470s&lt;/a&gt;,
that has a slimmer chassis, made from &amp;ldquo;higher quality materials&amp;rdquo;, and a better
screen compared to the T470. There is also the &amp;ldquo;high
performance&amp;rdquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notebookcheck.net/Lenovo-ThinkPad-T470p-Core-i7-GeForce-940MX-Laptop-Review.226802.0.html&#34;&gt;T470p&lt;/a&gt;,
which features a faster, quad-core CPU, but a slightly larger chassis. While
these variants caught my attention, I ultimately decided on the normal T470.
This was partially because I could max the T470 out at 32GBs of RAM (The T470s
can only hit 24GB due to one of the sticks being soldered in), but mostly
because I assumed that the combination of having a lower powered CPU (compared
to the T70p), but a slightly larger case (compared to the T480s) would make it
the optimal choice concerning my heat/noise concerns outlined in the previous
post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-specs&#34;&gt;The Specs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the T470 then&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got my T470 from a vendor on Ebay. It came configured with a 2.5GHz (3.1 GHz
Turbo) i5-7200u cpu, 8 GBs of DDR4 RAM, a 14&amp;rdquo; 1920x1080 screen, and a 500GB Hard
Drive with Windows 10 on it. After checking that it booted up fine, I
immediately swapped the slow HD with the 250GB SSD that was in my x230, and
installed &lt;a href=&#34;https://getsol.us&#34;&gt;Solus&lt;/a&gt; on it. In Solus, everything worked
&amp;ldquo;out of the box&amp;rdquo;, and I would guess other Linux distributions would as well. For
Christmas, I got a new 500GB Samsung EVO SSD to upgrade the 250GB one. In total,
the T470 has less total storage than the Bonobo had, but &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of it is fast SSD
storage. I am getting better at using my server for network storage anyway, so
it all works out &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I still plan to upgrade the T470 in the future, here are it&amp;rsquo;s specs at the
time of writing this post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;T470 Thinkpad
Intel i5-7200u [2.5 Ghz (3.1 Ghz Turbo), 2 Cores, 4 Threads]
8 GB RAM
500 GB Samsung EVO SSD
14&amp;quot; 1920x1080 IPS Display
Solus
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hardware on the T470 is nice, and the technical specs are &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt;, but the
real killer feature of switching to a Thinkpad for my main computer is that I
also purchased the ThinkPad Ultra Dock (40A2). This means that I am able to
&lt;em&gt;easily&lt;/em&gt; take advantage of my periphery devices whenever I am working at my
desk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Thinkpad Ultra Dock 40A2
2 x 23.6&amp;quot; ASUS 1920x1080 Monitors
Happy Hacking Keyboard Pro2
Audioengine A2+ Speakers &amp;amp; Stands
Bose AE2 Headphones
Logitech HD Pro Webcam c920 Widescreen
Blue Yeti Microphone - Backout Edition
Inateck USB 3.0 to SATA Dual-Bay Hard Drive Docking Station
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-like&#34;&gt;What I like&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I&amp;rsquo;ve provided some background information and a summary, I&amp;rsquo;ll quickly
list what I &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;do not like&lt;/em&gt; about my new T470.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cool &amp;amp; Quiet&lt;/strong&gt; - After realizing that I am picky about heat and noise in
computers, one of my biggest goals when replacing my old computer was to find
one that ran cooler and quieter. I think I did well here. &lt;em&gt;This thing is
silent.&lt;/em&gt; Using one of my new favorite command line applications,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://amanusk.github.io/s-tui/&#34;&gt;s-tui&lt;/a&gt;, I have observed that most of the
time when I&amp;rsquo;m writing code, browsing the web, or listening to music, the fans
in the T470 don&amp;rsquo;t even kick on. When I do push the machine a little by
running VMs, or being on a video conference, the do kick up, but even then I
have to put my ear right against the computer to hear anything. At it&amp;rsquo;s
loudest, the T470 is still a very quiet device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Size &amp;amp; Portability&lt;/strong&gt; - I love the size and portability of this laptop. The
14&amp;rdquo; form factor is large enough that I don&amp;rsquo;t feel cramped when using it as a
stand-alone device, but still small enough that I can easily throw it in my
bag and bring it with me. While I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t mind the T470 shedding a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt;
weight (which is mostly from the battery), I find it&amp;rsquo;s thickness perfectly
acceptable for my uses (hear that Apple?). As far as build quality, it is a
solid machine. When I rest my hands on it to type, they feel fully supported
and there is &lt;em&gt;zero&lt;/em&gt; flex. When holding the closed laptop, it feels as though
it could take quite a beating and still be fine. I love that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keyboard &amp;amp; Track-point/pad&lt;/strong&gt; - It&amp;rsquo;s a Thinkpad keyboard, what else do I have
to say? The keys are adequately spaced, have travel (though not as much as my
x230), and feel &lt;em&gt;crisp&lt;/em&gt; when pressed, not mushy. It has a track&lt;em&gt;point&lt;/em&gt; with
physical buttons, which at this point I don&amp;rsquo;t think I could do without (Crap.
Unintentional pun. Oh well, I&amp;rsquo;m leaving it.). While I don&amp;rsquo;t use it often, the
track&lt;em&gt;pad&lt;/em&gt; is also quite nice. I find it to be an ideal size, and has
rubberized texture which prevents my fingers from feeling raw after long use.
I find it hard these days for others laptops to compete with the Thinkpad&amp;rsquo;s
keyboard/track-point setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dock-able&lt;/strong&gt; - I&amp;rsquo;ve already mentioned this above, but I love that the T470 is
dock-able. This is becoming more common with the pervasiveness of USB-C, but
Thinkpads have been in the dock game for years. It works well, and fits my
current computing use-case perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thunderbolt/USB C&lt;/strong&gt; - The big difference between the T470 and the T460
essentially comes down to the Thunderbolt 3/USB-C port on the T470. I don&amp;rsquo;t
use it much &lt;em&gt;so far&lt;/em&gt;, but I hope the industry continues the move down the this
route, and I will be glad to already have the port as they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Battery(s)&lt;/strong&gt; - The battery configuration and life on this laptop is great.
The T470 can get a 3-cell battery that doesn&amp;rsquo;t stick out, or an extended
battery that comes in 6 and 9 cell variations (Note: the 6 and 9 cell are the
same size). The T470 also supports an internal 3 cell battery, that can be
used to keep the laptop powered on while the external battery is swapped. I
currently have the least optimal configuration: A bulky 6-cell external, with
no internal battery. Even so, it easily lasts me throughout the day, and I can
always upgrade it down the road. I love the flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-dont-like&#34;&gt;What I don&amp;rsquo;t like&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I overall love the T470, there are a few things I&amp;rsquo;m not thrilled about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Screen&lt;/strong&gt; - When I first got my laptop&amp;hellip; I thought the screen was
defective. I had read in reviews that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t very &lt;em&gt;bright&lt;/em&gt;, but the colors
were terrible. My screen always looked as if I was using something like
&lt;a href=&#34;https://justgetflux.com/&#34;&gt;f.lux&lt;/a&gt;. After doing some reading, it turns out that
IPS panels (which I had never owned before) can appear warmer in color. That
combined with the low brightness and &lt;em&gt;not great&lt;/em&gt; color accuracy of the T470
panel, made it appear particularly awful to me. I found and configured a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notebookcheck.net/uploads/tx_nbc2/N140HCA_EAB_01.icm&#34;&gt;ICC
file&lt;/a&gt; which
helped, but the biggest fix was time. As terrible as it was at first, I really
don&amp;rsquo;t mind the screen. Yea, it could be brighter with better colors, but now I
think it looks nice, and colors on top of black really pop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Track-point&lt;/strong&gt; - I stated in the section above that the track-point was one of
the features I loved about this laptop. That is true&amp;hellip; but, if I &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to get
picky, the track-point itself is not that great. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to move around with
and it&amp;rsquo;s sensitivity differs depending on which direction it is traveling. At
times it can be a real pain. By contrast, my x230 is very stable and precise.
I wish the T470&amp;rsquo;s track-point was like the one on my x230&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graphics&lt;/strong&gt; - I can&amp;rsquo;t complain too much here because I knew what I was
getting myself into, but&amp;hellip; the graphics performance isn&amp;rsquo;t the best. I know
&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; having dedicated graphics is what allows the T470 to run cool and sip
power, but I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t mind a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; more umph. I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to do heavy
gaming on the T470. If I want to game, I am going to build a gaming computer.
However, I do wish I could play basic games a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; better in the meantime.
(&lt;em&gt;On the bright side&amp;hellip;with the thunderbolt 3 port&amp;hellip; an eGPU is a
possibility&amp;hellip;hmmm&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-plans&#34;&gt;Future Plans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I have been very happy with the T470 as my main computer. I&amp;rsquo;d still
like to upgrade the RAM at some point, and I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; entertained the idea of
trying an eGPU setup&amp;hellip; I might &lt;em&gt;eventually&lt;/em&gt; build a new desktop, but even then,
I would likely have it headless, running VMs and connect to it remotely from the
T470 (except for occasional gaming). That being said, right now, the T470 is
working great as is!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My New, Used x230</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/my-new-used-x230/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/my-new-used-x230/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I start to do more with a computer on the go, the netbooks I
previously used just are not cutting it anymore. They were great for minimal
use, but couldn&amp;rsquo;t run VMs, over-heated, and didn&amp;rsquo;t have great
battery life. Now that I am going to libraries and other locations to
work on personal and open source projects, I really needed a better
mobile pc setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-considerations&#34;&gt;Other Considerations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had been keeping an eye open for a new mobile computer for well over a
year to find out what is out there. I mostly looked sub $300 ubuntu laptops like the Asus 11&amp;rdquo;
celeron (x201e) I got in college. I don&amp;rsquo;t need much HD
space on my portable computer, because I usually use a minimal
OS, and only have my projects (which are git controlled), and sometimes a
&lt;em&gt;little bit&lt;/em&gt; of music. Even with dropping my requirements to computers with
&lt;em&gt;very tiny&lt;/em&gt; HDs (often &amp;lt; 60GB), none of the options seemed all that impressive. They
usually had Celeron processors and little ram. Even worse, they
were not easily expandable. I also briefly entertained the idea of
putting Linux on a chrome book, but they had the same issues that all
the other sub $300 options had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;used-thinkpads&#34;&gt;Used Thinkpads&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I intensified my search, I started to consider other
options. There is one alternative that is very popular among Linux users,
but I always seem to forget about it when looking for a new
device. That option of course, is buying a used Thinkpad and installing
Linux on it. This appeared to be an ideal time to try it out. I
don&amp;rsquo;t mind if there is a scratch or two on a cheap device. This is my
portable computer after all, so I&amp;rsquo;m sure a shinny new device wouldn&amp;rsquo;t stay
pristine for long anyway. So, I started researching used Thinkpads and
loved how much you could get for the money. There were i5 devices with an
acceptable bit of ram and &amp;ldquo;okay&amp;rdquo; hard drives for under my $300 price
point. Better yet, the Thinkpads seemed easy to upgrade .
So, even if the device had a bad battery, or needed a
RAM/HD upgrade, &lt;em&gt;I could could do it&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I eventually narrowed my search down to the X230 or T430s. That year&amp;rsquo;s
model seemed like the perfect mix of still being relatively new, while
also being old enough that many business had started to replace
them, flooding the market and driving the cost down. They also
didn&amp;rsquo;t have the terrible track pad that the x240 and T440s had (without buttons). I
eventually decided on the x230 because the main use of this laptop would be portability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;this-particular-thinkpad-x230-&#34;&gt;This Particular Thinkpad x230 &amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The listing also said that it came with a &amp;ldquo;used 6-cell battery&amp;rdquo;. So I planned
from the beginning to have it replaced. Sure enough, when the laptop arrived,
the battery was completely dead. If I unplugged the laptop, it would shutdown.
So, I ordered a 9-cell battery online to replace it. I added
a 4GB stick of RAM that I took from an older laptop, and replaced the slow HHD
(with Windows pre-installed), with a cheap 120GB SSD I had lying
around. After installing Korora 24 on the new SSD, I had a
nice, portable computer that only cost me about $200 (plus some spare
parts). As advertised, swapping the battery, adding RAM, and replacing
the HD were &lt;em&gt;super simple&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;accessible&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-like-about-it&#34;&gt;What I like about it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Track point&lt;/strong&gt; - I love track points. Using other laptops with
just track-pads is really frustrating now. I completely understand why
people are so crazy about them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keyboard&lt;/strong&gt; - The keyboard really is great. I feels solid and not like
other laptop keyboards. It gives good feedback and is very nice to type on. I know many
people hate this model because keyboard layout changed from the
older models like the x220, but I still think the x230 has a better
keyboard than most laptops.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physical buttons&lt;/strong&gt; - The x230 has a physical mute, volume control, and
mic buttons. This is a feature I enjoy much more than I thought I
would.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upgradability&lt;/strong&gt; - As I have already mentioned, it is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; easy
to upgrade the x230. Right when I got it, I replaced the HHD with an
SSD and added another stick of RAM in under five
minutes. In fact, I have swapped the SSD out temporarily with
a second drive several times now to try out different distros on the
hardware. It is just so easy to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feel&lt;/strong&gt; - I really like how this laptop feels. I&amp;rsquo;ve already
mentioned that I enjoy the solidness of the keyboard, but I also
love the exterior texture of the case. It has a slight rubbery
feel to it that makes it easy to hold.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bang for your buck&lt;/strong&gt; - Getting a used thinkpad really is a
great deal. Even counting the minor upgrades I installed, I was able
to get &lt;em&gt;an actual computer&lt;/em&gt; for around the same price as the
&lt;em&gt;netbook&lt;/em&gt; alternatives I was looking at.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Size&lt;/strong&gt; - This is my mobile computer, so I need it to be
small. While it isn&amp;rsquo;t as thin as my wife&amp;rsquo;s macbook air, it is still
very portable. I actually don&amp;rsquo;t mind it being a little bit thicker,
as I find it to be the perfect size to hold and carry around. It is
a similar size to a few of my programming books and slides into my
backpack very easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-dont-like&#34;&gt;What I don&amp;rsquo;t like&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has a little bit of flex&lt;/strong&gt; - While the laptop overall feels pretty
solid, the screen does have a bit of flex when pressed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolution&lt;/strong&gt; - I really hate 1366x768 on laptops. I don&amp;rsquo;t need 1920x1080, which would be very tiny on a 12.5&amp;rdquo; screen. 1600x900 however&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Track pad (but honestly who cares)&lt;/strong&gt; - The track-pad isn&amp;rsquo;t great. In fact, it can be downright annoying. The bottom of the track-pad curves around the edge of computer, which looks nice, but rubs against my stomach when I am working with the laptop on my lap. This causes the cursor to fly around and do everything but what I want it to do. This would be a much bigger issue on other laptops, but with how much I use the track point, I really don&amp;rsquo;t care. I usually just disable the track-pad all together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers aren&amp;rsquo;t great (but again, not a bit deal)&lt;/strong&gt; - The speakers are very quiet and don&amp;rsquo;t
sound very good. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a huge deal for me because being my mobile computer, I am using
headphones 99% of the time. Still, it would be nice if when I occasionally share a video with someone they could actually hear it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;update&#34;&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have taken so long to publish this post, I am actually now using Arch Linux on the x230. It also runs great :)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
