<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>macbook on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/macbook/</link>
    <description>Recent content in macbook on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/macbook/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My New 16-inch Macbook Pro: Initial Thoughts</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/new-2019-16inch-mbp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/new-2019-16inch-mbp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/macos-challenge/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I &lt;em&gt;mentioned&lt;/em&gt; that I had
purchased a new 2019 16&amp;rdquo; Macbook Pro by the end of my macOS challenge.  I have
had the laptop for over a month now, but I made sure to take notes on some of
my initial thoughts during the first few days. Here are those thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;selection&#34;&gt;Selection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But first, &lt;em&gt;a word from our sponsor!&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt; Just kidding. However, I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; want to
take a minute to talk about how I selected &lt;em&gt;my first&lt;/em&gt; macbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While completing the macOS challenge, I decided I wanted to buy a
macbook for personal use. However, I wanted to hold out and wait to hear if the
rumors of a new scissor-switch macbook pro were true, or if I
should be considering a used 2015 Macbook Pro on eBay. Fortunately, the rumor
turned to fact, and Apple released the new 16&amp;rdquo; Macbook Pro. This news coupled
with a $300-off, Thanksgiving (US) sale, meant that I had a new macbook
shipping to me the first week of December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-base-model-specs&#34;&gt;The Base Model Specs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose the base-spec MBP (the cheapest one) for several reasons. First, it
saved me a bunch of money because 1) Apple upgrades tend to be expensive, and 2)
the base models can be found on sale more easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the &amp;ldquo;low-end&amp;rdquo; base model specs of the 16&amp;rdquo; Macbook Pro were
increased to include 16 GB of RAM, and a 512GB SSD. This meant that it already
had everything I would normally &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to upgrade. So, the specs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;- 2.6 GHz (4.5 GHz Turbo Boost) 6-Core (12 thread) i7 CPU
- 16 GB 2666MHz DDR4 RAM
- 512 GB SS
- 16&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Retina&amp;quot; display w/ True Tone
- New Keyboard design, with touchbar and Touch ID
- Four Thunderbold 3 ports
- Headphone Jack
- New speakers and mic
- Silver
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, I &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; have wanted 32 GB of RAM. But if I think
about it, I &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; need RAM to run clusters of VMs&amp;hellip; which I do on Linux
workstation/servers&amp;hellip; not my laptop. So 16GB should be plenty for the needs of
&lt;em&gt;this machine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;initial-thoughts&#34;&gt;Initial Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, now lets get to my initial thoughts. Remember, these are the
(reformatted) notes I took within about a day or so of receiving the Macbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keyboard&lt;/strong&gt; - Well, I’m surprised. I think I actually &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; like it. The
first few minutes were a little weird, because I was used to the (2014) MacBook
Air (Also, I had been using &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/new-hhkb-pro2/&#34;&gt;my
HHKB&lt;/a&gt; all day). After using
it for about an hour now, I think it feels close to the air (which I like),
with &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; travel. It definitely does not have as much travel as my
Thinkpads, but it is acceptable. The keys feel like they “pop” as I type on
them, with a very satisfying bump. Overall, I very much enjoy the typing
experience. As long as it proves to be sturdy and reliable, I’d say this is
a great laptop keyboard. I am very happy with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trackpad&lt;/strong&gt; - Little weird at first (I had trouble sliding my fingers across
it.  I guess I needed time to oil it a bit lol), but now it seems to be working
well. It is massive, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to register accidental touches much.
Really, there isn&amp;rsquo;t much to say. It does what I need it to, basically &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Screen&lt;/strong&gt; - Wonderful. It’s big, bright and the colors look great. Using
the default scaling still, but actually think it’s big enough. It&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful
screen large enough to get work done, on a still small-ish laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Touch Bar&lt;/strong&gt; - Meh. It&amp;rsquo;s whatever. I have already installed better touch tool
😂. I’ll play with that later to figure out how I can switch the
audio/brightness to buttons instead of slides (the main thing I don’t like so
far), and maybe add weather. In summary, with better touch tool, I don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;mind&lt;/em&gt;
having the touch bar, but probably wouldn&amp;rsquo;t miss it much if it was gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers&lt;/strong&gt; - Amazing. Simple as that. They aren&amp;rsquo;t going to replace a
high-end pair of studio monitors, but are probably the best laptop speakers out
there, and likely better than most cheap desktop ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ports&lt;/strong&gt; - Just charging so far. I like being able to charge on
both sides. Side note: the power brick feels like an &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; brick. It is
solid and heavy, which is fine, but did surprise me a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance&lt;/strong&gt; - As far as I can tell, great. It seems like it can handle
most of the work loads &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; will need it for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;issuesannoyancesconcerns&#34;&gt;Issues/Annoyances/Concerns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heat&lt;/strong&gt; - As I’m typing this, I do notice the metal at the top of the laptop
(above the Touch Bar) is getting quite toasty. In fact, the keys on the number
row are even a bit warm. I understand that this is where the heat is exhausted,
and that the cooling system probably relies on the aluminum body a bit as a
heat sink. I just hope it’s normal. I should note that this heat up happened
while I was installing Xcode&amp;hellip; which seems to be a beast. Once Xcode finished
installing, it did cool down fast. The entire time, the palm rest remained nice
and cool to the touch. Also, the fans never kicked up for this. So it seems
that the cooling system is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good on this laptop. I just wish it would
kick in a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; bit sooner to prevent it from heating up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ports/Adaptor Annoyances&lt;/strong&gt; - Everyone is complaining that there still isn&amp;rsquo;t
an SD card reader, but honestly I could care less. I generally think having
powerful TB3 ports is a good plan, as it allows the user to craft their system
to have whatever ports &lt;em&gt;they need&lt;/em&gt;. For example, I &lt;em&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; usually need an SD
card reader, but I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; use USB3 and HDMI daily. With a dongle/adaptor, I can
have that, and the TB3 connector has enough bandwidth to support it. However, the
annoying part is buying into the TB3 life. I &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to buy an expensive
dongle for my new expensive laptop in order to use &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; with it. Also,
the functionality of the adaptors seems to be hit or miss. I got one that
works okay, but only after having to return the first one I bought because it
just wouldn&amp;rsquo;t connect my devices. Very Annoying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wrists Rest&lt;/strong&gt; - While I really enjoy the solid feel of the aluminum my
hands rest on (and how it tends to stay cool even when the computer is heating
up), the sharp edge of the laptop cuts into my wrist over time. I will admit
that this is something I have experience on other laptops too. Maybe I just
type wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I love this laptop. It is powerful enough to do everything I
need, and I think Apple has done a great job addressing the complaints users
have had with Macbooks over the last few years. Considering the speaker,
microphone, keyboard, and screen upgrades this is an amazing portable
workstation. As much as I love having a full desk setup, the &amp;ldquo;built-in
periphery devices&amp;rdquo; on this laptop are &lt;em&gt;so good&lt;/em&gt;, I really don&amp;rsquo;t mind working
straight from the laptop. Which coming from &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;, is saying something.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
