<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Proxmox on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/proxmox/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Proxmox on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/proxmox/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Exporting Proxmox VMs</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/exporting-proxmox-vms/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/exporting-proxmox-vms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For a long time I have been thinking about replacing my server&amp;rsquo;s proxmox install with vanilla Debian or CentOS, mostly for learning purposes. I would first setup zfs on the new system and import my existing data pools. Then, I would use either a system like ovrit or just plain kvm/lxc to run my VMs and containers. In order to do this though&amp;hellip; I have to first figure out how export my containers and VMs running in Proxmox. As it turns out&amp;hellip; exporting the VMs wasn&amp;rsquo;t very hard&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exporting-proxmox-vm-disk&#34;&gt;Exporting Proxmox VM Disk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Proxmox logo&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/exporting-proxmox-vms/proxmox-logo.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Proxmox VMs are setup on an LVM virtual group, with each virtual drive being a lvm volume passed to the VM. So, I wanted to be able to extract these disks to something I could more easily transfer. I ended up converting the lvm volumes to qcow2 images because it was easy and I&amp;rsquo;ve actually experienced okay performance with qcow2 on my workstations. Additionally, qcow2 being a single file, is easy to move around and I can always convert them to something else on the final system. To export one of the VMs, I ran the command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;qemu-img convert -O qcow2 /dev/pve/vm-108-disk-1 /Data/freebsd-vm.qcow2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was it. It took a few minutes to finish, but honestly that is all I had to do (I&amp;rsquo;m sure I should of taken a snapshot or something then copy that, but this seemed to work fine). When it completed, I copied the image down to my desktop and decided to test it out with virt-manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;importing-the-image-to-virt-manager&#34;&gt;Importing the image to Virt-Manager&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opened up virt-manager and selected the button to create a new VM. At the first prompt, instead of selecting my usual &amp;ldquo;Local install media (ISO image or CDROM)&amp;rdquo; option, I choose to &amp;ldquo;Import an existing disk image&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;import image&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/exporting-proxmox-vms/import-image.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the second menu, I opened up the browse menu to see my already configured locations. From there, I found where I had saved the converted qcow2 image, and selected it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;select qcow2 image&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/exporting-proxmox-vms/select-qcow2-image.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I continued setting up the virtual specs (CPU, RAM, etc.) for the machine just as I would with any other VM setup. When I was done, I started the VM and FreeBSD booted right up. I logged in and compared the installed applications and files with the still running proxmox VM. They were identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all I really have for this post. It was extremely simple to export the VMs. I know I&amp;rsquo;m not fully done yet and still have to import the VMs to the final system, but I&amp;rsquo;ll save that for a later post. Right now&amp;hellip; I have quite a few VM images to convert, so I might as well get started.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
