<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pi on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/pi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pi on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/pi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating the Pi Cluster with Ansible</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/updating-pi-cluster-with-ansible/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/updating-pi-cluster-with-ansible/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With Ansible configured on the Pi cluster, it is time to have it do something useful. When working with a clustered system, even the simplest tasks become tedious and time consuming. For example, updating the system. While I could manually update each of the 3 pi nodes, it is not scalable to 10 or 30 nodes, let alone hundreds or thousands. Tools like Ansible, make doing tasks such a supdating clustered systems, trivial again. In this post, I will walk through setting up an Ansible playbook to update my Pi cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hosts-file&#34;&gt;Hosts File&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first task when using Ansible is to setup the &lt;code&gt;hosts&lt;/code&gt; file. No, not the normal &lt;code&gt;/etc/hosts&lt;/code&gt; file, but the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; one &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; for Ansible, which can be found at &lt;code&gt;/etc/ansible/hosts&lt;/code&gt;. Configuring the Ansible hosts file is fairly straightforward. Groups of computers are defined using &lt;code&gt;[brackets]&lt;/code&gt;, with computer ip/hostnames of the group are listed below. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nice feature of group definitions is that hierical structures can be constructed using the &lt;code&gt;:child&lt;/code&gt; suffix in order to create groups of groups. For example, for my &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab&#34;&gt;homelab&lt;/a&gt;, I like to make an ansible hosts file that splits out my servers based on their distribution, and then group those by their packaging type. This makes it easier for me to do generic updates, which is what I mostly use ansible for (at this point). So, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ubuntu]
mrmime
geodude

[debian]
ninetales

[fedora]
fedora-test

[centos]
tangels

[arch]
meowth
staryu
diglet

[deb:children]
ubuntu
debian

[rpm:children]
fedora
centos&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For use with the cluster, I kept it simple, although I did opt to create rpi/bpi subgroups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[cluster:children]
rpis
bpis

[rpis]
pi0
pi1

[bpis]
bpi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ping-hosts&#34;&gt;Ping Hosts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the hosts file is setup, it can be tested using the &lt;code&gt;ping&lt;/code&gt; module. I tested my &lt;code&gt;cluser&lt;/code&gt; group, as well as the &lt;code&gt;rpis&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;bpis&lt;/code&gt; subgroups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ansible rpis -m ping
ansible bpis -m ping
ansible cluster -m ping&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming the steps of &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/Ansible-On-Pi-Cluster&#34;&gt;the last post&lt;/a&gt; were done correctly, this should work. If not, double check that post and make sure everything looks correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;playbooks&#34;&gt;Playbooks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After confirming that the hosts file is properly configured, I started to dig into playbooks. Playbooks are Ansible&amp;rsquo;s scripting system used to configure, deploy, and orcistrate systems. They can describe ways in which systems should be configured (ex: enable ssh), or outline a set of steps for an IT task (ex: running updates, restarting a server). As stated in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/playbooks.html&#34;&gt;playbook documentation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;post-quote&#34;&gt;
*&#34;If Ansible modules are the tools in your workshop, playbooks are your instruction manuals, and your inventory of hosts are your raw material.&#34;*
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playbook files are expressed using &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/YAMLSyntax.html&#34;&gt;YAML syntax&lt;/a&gt;, which is easy to read, but still powerful. The first step when creating a new playbook, being a YAML file, is to set the header and footer. The header consists of three &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rsquo;s at the top of the file, and the footer ends the file with three periods (&lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;). This indicates the start and end of the document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When writing a playbook to update the pi cluster, I first needed to declare what systems the playbook is used with. To do that, I used the &lt;code&gt;hosts&lt;/code&gt; key, and provided it with the &lt;code&gt;cluster&lt;/code&gt; group name, which is defined in my &lt;code&gt;/etc/ansible/hosts&lt;/code&gt; file, as the value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
- hosts: cluster

...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the hosts are defined, modules can be added to update the nodes. To list the tasks, I used the &lt;code&gt;taks:&lt;/code&gt; key, with the same indentation as the &lt;code&gt;hosts:&lt;/code&gt; keyword. Instead of using a single value, I provided the &lt;code&gt;tasks:&lt;/code&gt; keyword with a list of things to do. The first task I want to do when updating the nodes is to check that they running and connected. This can be accomplised with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/ping_module.html&#34;&gt;ping module&lt;/a&gt; that I used earlier in the post. The ping module will try to connect to each node, verify that a usable python is installed, and return &lt;code&gt;pong&lt;/code&gt; upon success. To add the module, I added &lt;code&gt;- ping: ~&lt;/code&gt;, indented, to the line below &lt;code&gt;tasks:&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
- hosts: cluster

  tasks:
    - ping: ~&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;apt-module&#34;&gt;Apt Module&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After defining the ping module, I started to get a bit fancier. Well&amp;hellip; a little bit fancier. Each node in my pi cluster is running some verison of Ubuntu, which uses apt as it&amp;rsquo;s package manager. If I wanted to ssh into each node and update them manually, the steps I would follow would be to 1) run the command &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get update&lt;/code&gt; to update the repository cache, and 2) run &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get upgrade&lt;/code&gt; to actually install the updates. To recreate these commands in the playbook, I used the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/apt_module.html&#34;&gt;apt module&lt;/a&gt;. To start with updating the repository cache, I added the following lines to my playbook:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;- name: Update APT package manager repositories cache
  become: true
  apt:
    update_cache: yes&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;name:&lt;/code&gt; defines the name of the task, and is the text printed out to the console when executing this step of the playbook. Setting the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ansible.com/ansible/become.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;become&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; key to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; tells Ansible to run the command with privilege escalation (sudo). Lastly, the remaining two lines run the &lt;code&gt;update_cache:&lt;/code&gt; functionality of the apt module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the repositories updated on each node, I can have ansible run the updates by adding the following lines to the playbook (after the cache update ones):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;- name: Upgrade installed packages
  become: true
  apt:
    upgrade: dist&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This set of commands is very similar to the last group. The &lt;code&gt;name:&lt;/code&gt; again provides a description of what the task is doing, and privilege escalation is used again via &lt;code&gt;become: true&lt;/code&gt;. The only difference is that the apt module is using the &lt;code&gt;upgrade: dist&lt;/code&gt; command instead. This will run the updates for any installed packages on the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-cluster-playbook&#34;&gt;Update Cluster Playbook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then had a completed playbook to update the pi cluster:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
- hosts: cluster

  tasks:
    - ping: ~

    - name: Update APT package manager repositories cache
      become: true
      apt:
        update_cache: yes

    - name: Upgrade installed packages
      become: true
      apt:
        upgrade: dist
...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last step is to test it out! Playbooks can be executed using the &lt;code&gt;ansible-playbook&lt;/code&gt; command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ansible-playbook update-cluster.yml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When running the playbook, ansible will first attempt to gather facts about each node, and then begin to run each of the tasks defined in the playbook. At each step, it will print out the &lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt; of each task, followed by the status/result for each node. When it completes, all the nodes in the cluster should be updated. Now you can update three+ computers with a single command! Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configuring Ansible on the Pi Cluster</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/ansible-on-pi-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/ansible-on-pi-cluster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/Setting-up-the-pi-cluster/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I pieced together my &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#cluster&#34;&gt;pi cluster&lt;/a&gt;, and installed variations of Ubuntu 16.04 Server on each of its nodes. With the cluster built, I quickly needed an easy way to maintain and interact with the system as a whole. This, is where &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ansible.com/&#34;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt; comes in. In this post, I will walk through the steps I took to setup Ansible on my Cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ansible&#34;&gt;Ansible&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/posts/setting-up-ansible-pi-cluster/ansible-logo.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 50%; width: 150px; float: left; margin: 0px 15px 5px 5px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ansible is an open source, configuration management and automation system. It is written in Python, and financially backed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.redhat.com&#34;&gt;Red Hat&lt;/a&gt;. It simplifies the management of groups of computers, through the use of modules (standalone units of work. for example, apt, ping, rpm, etc). Ansible is script-able using simple YAML files, known as playbooks, that define a set of orchestration tasks for one or many computers. These scripts can be edited and version controlled, creating a simple &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infrastructure_as_Code&#34;&gt;infrastructure as code&lt;/a&gt; setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setting-up-the-user-account&#34;&gt;Setting up the User Account&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Ansible executes commands on the PIs, it will do so from the user-account (ryan) that I setup in the last post. However, many of these commands will require Root privledges. While I previously setup sudo and added the &lt;code&gt;ryan&lt;/code&gt; account to the &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; group &amp;hellip; it required that I manually enter my password. Ansible did not like this, so I had to update the sudo configuration to allow the &lt;code&gt;ryan&lt;/code&gt; account to run &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; commands with out a password. To do this, I opened the &lt;code&gt;sudoers&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo visudo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and added the following line to the end of the file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ryan  ALL=(ALL:ALL) NOPASSWD: ALL&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I repeated this on each of the nodes, and afterwards was no longer promted for a password when running &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; commands. This made Ansible happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;ssh&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setup-ssh-keys&#34;&gt;Setup SSH Keys&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ansible&amp;rsquo;s main method of communication is via ssh, which by default, prompts me for a password when connecting. Ansible &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hates passwords. So, I had to configure ssh to use keys instead. Honestly, this is proabaly a good step to do regardless, now that the &lt;code&gt;ryan&lt;/code&gt; account no longer uses a password when running &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;. To setup key-based logins, I appended the contents of my &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#alakazam&#34;&gt;main computer&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s ssh public key*, to each pi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;authorized_keys&lt;/code&gt; file. This can all be done using a magic one-line pipe command (x3, one for each pi):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cat ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub | ssh pi0 &amp;#34;cat &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.ssh/authorized_keys&amp;#34;
cat ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub | ssh pi1 &amp;#34;cat &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.ssh/authorized_keys&amp;#34;
cat ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub | ssh bpi &amp;#34;cat &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.ssh/authorized_keys&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*Note: If keys are not already generated, they can be created using the command:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh-keygen&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-only-login&#34;&gt;Key Only Login&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help secure access to the PIs (and to get on Ansible&amp;rsquo;s good side), I configured sshd to disable password logins, and only allow connections from clients with approved keys. To disable password authentication, I opened the &lt;code&gt;/etc/ssh/sshd_config&lt;/code&gt; file, found the line containing &lt;code&gt;# PasswordAuthentication yes&lt;/code&gt;, changed the &lt;code&gt;yes&lt;/code&gt; to a &lt;code&gt;no&lt;/code&gt;, and unncommented it by removing the &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was in the &lt;code&gt;sshd_config&lt;/code&gt; file, I also set &lt;code&gt;PermitRootLogin&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;no&lt;/code&gt;, for good measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I reset the &lt;code&gt;sshd&lt;/code&gt; service and repeated the steps for each pi:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo systemctl restart sshd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, I was unable to login to the PIs from a computer with unauthorized ssh keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/posts/setting-up-ansible-pi-cluster/terminal-play.png&#34; name=&#34;pic&#34; onmouseover=&#34;this.src=&#39;../../img/posts/setting-up-ansible-pi-cluster/blocked-ssh-attempt.gif&#39;&#34; onmouseout=&#34;this.src=&#39;../../img/posts/setting-up-ansible-pi-cluster/terminal-play.png&#39;&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I was still able to loging from the authorized computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/posts/setting-up-ansible-pi-cluster/terminal-play.png&#34; name=&#34;pic&#34; onmouseover=&#34;this.src=&#39;../../img/posts/setting-up-ansible-pi-cluster/accepted-ssh-attempt.gif&#39;&#34; onmouseout=&#34;this.src=&#39;../../img/posts/setting-up-ansible-pi-cluster/terminal-play.png&#39;&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;install-python&#34;&gt;Install Python&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last issue Ansible complained about was that it needed python installed on the Pis. Like everything else, the Bananna Pi already had this setup, but I had to install it on the two Raspberry Pis. It was simple enough:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install python&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;install-ansible&#34;&gt;Install Ansible&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a confession. So, you know how I have been fun and cheery by anthropomorphisizing Ansible, saying that it was &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;happy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;frusterated&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; during the previous steps? That wasn&amp;rsquo;t true. I made it up. Ansible wasn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; installed yet. &lt;em&gt;So&amp;hellip; to install Ansible&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo eopkg it ansible&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;code&gt;eopkg&lt;/code&gt; because I am currently running &lt;a href=&#34;https://getsol.us&#34;&gt;Solus&lt;/a&gt;. You might use &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install ansible&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;sudo dnf install ansible&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;pacaur -S ansible&lt;/code&gt; depending on whatever distro you are using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all for &lt;em&gt;setting up&lt;/em&gt; Ansible. I&amp;rsquo;ll cut this post off here, but in the next post, I&amp;rsquo;ll walk through the steps on how to get Ansible to be useful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Up My Pi Cluster</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/setting-up-the-pi-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/setting-up-the-pi-cluster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a Raspberry Pi 2, a Raspberry Pi 3, and a Banana Pi. A while ago, I constructed a small tower to house my pi devices. Since then, I have additionally acquired a power source, and some CAT6 cable to connect them all up to a switch. I hope to use the Pis as a mini clustered environment, where I can learn (and play) with some of the &amp;ldquo;Devops&amp;rdquo; technologies/techniques out there. This post will briefly explain the initial setup of &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#cluster&#34;&gt;my cluster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;setting-up-the-os-images&#34;&gt;Setting up the OS Images&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before doing anything with the hardware, I had to setup the pi &amp;ldquo;hard drives&amp;rdquo; (micro SD cards), so they could boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ubuntu-for-raspberry-pi&#34;&gt;Ubuntu for Raspberry PI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/posts/Setting-Up-Pi-Cluster/ubuntu-logo.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 50%; height: auto; float: right; margin: 0px 2px 2px 2px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After mucking around with Rapsbian and Hypriot one Sunday, I decided to just go with a plain Ubuntu image for the Raspberry Pis. I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything against these specific OSes, but I am mostly setting up this cluster to simulate what I would do on a &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; system. For me, that often means using a straight OS like Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, Canonical makes special &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.ubuntu.com/ARM/RaspberryPi&#34;&gt;Ubuntu ARM images&lt;/a&gt;, specifically for the Raspberry Pi. I download the 16.04 server version for both the raspberry pi 2 and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.finnie.org/software/raspberrypi/ubuntu-rpi3/ubuntu-16.04-preinstalled-server-armhf+raspi3.img.xz&#34;&gt;raspberry pi 3&lt;/a&gt;. The process to write these images to the microSD card differs slightly from ones I&amp;rsquo;ve used in the past. It still uses &lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt;, but the image is first piped through &lt;code&gt;xzcat&lt;/code&gt;, as such:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;xzcat ubuntu-16.04.2-preinstalled-server-armhf+raspi2.img.xz | sudo dd bs=4M of=/dev/mmcblk0
xzcat ubuntu-16.04-preinstalled-server-armhf+raspi3.img.xz   | sudo dd bs=4M of=/dev/mmcblk0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;armbian&#34;&gt;Armbian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one issue that I have with the Banana Pi compared to the Raspberry Pi, is that it is commonly not supported. It can be hard to find a bananna pi specific image, and the raspberry pi ones usually do not work. For example, while Canonical linked to Raspberry Pi images, it did not mention the banana pie.  This is where &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.armbian.com/&#34;&gt;Armbian&lt;/a&gt; comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armbian is a lightweight Debian and Ubuntu based distribution, that provides builds for various ARM devices. Thus the name, &lt;em&gt;ARM-bian&lt;/em&gt;. One of these many supported devices&amp;hellip; is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.armbian.com/banana-pi/&#34;&gt;banana pi&lt;/a&gt;. I downloaded the Ubuntu 16.04 Server flavor of Armbian for the Banana PI, and copied it to my micro SD card with the command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo dd if=Armbian_5.25_Bananapi_Ubuntu_xenial_next_4.9.7.img  of=/dev/mmcblk0 bs=1M&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hardware-setup&#34;&gt;Hardware Setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/posts/Setting-Up-Pi-Cluster/pi-cluster.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 40%; float: right; margin: 10px 10px 5px 10px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the operating system images have been copied the SD cards, the hardware can be setup. I started by inserting the microSD cards into the PIs, being careful to use the correct card with each device. Unlike the Raspberry PIs, the Bananna PI uses a normal SD card instead of a microSD, so I just left it in the converter card I used to connect it to my computer when imaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After adding the &amp;ldquo;hard drives&amp;rdquo;, I connected each PI to my network switch, via Ethernet. In the future, I would like to put the cluster on it&amp;rsquo;s own mini (managed?) switch so that I can have the nodes on their own private network, but connected to my main network. For now, this works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, plug in the power connectors. Pi devices can be very finicky when not properly powered, so it is a good idea to use an capable USB charging device. I have had trouble in the past with my devices not working correctly due to insufficient power (especially the bpi). I knew this problem would be an even more pronounced with the cluster because I planned to connect a HD to the bpi with a SATA connector. So, I picked up an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Anker-Charger-PowerPort-Multi-Port-Samsung/dp/B00VH8ZW02/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1493860165&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=Anker+power+port+5&#34;&gt;Anker Power Port 5&lt;/a&gt; and it has been working great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, two nice features of the banana pi is that it has a 1 GB ethernet port, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a SATA connector with power. So, to utilize this functionality, and get the most out of the bpi, I ordered &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/JBtek-Connectors-Banana-Supply-Terminals/dp/B00ZP0L0VS/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1493860481&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=banana+pi+sata&#34;&gt;the appropriate SATA connector&lt;/a&gt; from amazon for a few bucks. When it arrived, I connected it to the SATA and SATA power ports on the pi, and then to an old 300GB laptop HD I had laying around (it was the drive that came with &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/my-new-used-x230/&#34;&gt;my x230&lt;/a&gt;). After the drive was connected, running &lt;code&gt;lsblk&lt;/code&gt; on the bpi automatically showed a &lt;code&gt;/dev/sda&lt;/code&gt; device, in addition to the typical &lt;code&gt;mmcblk0&lt;/code&gt; microSD device. I  mounted the drive to a folder using the following command to test it out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo mount /dev/sda1 Data&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the hard drive mounted, I was able to browse its contents and see of all the crap still on it. The combination of the GB network and large HD makes the bpi a great little storage node, which is how I intend to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bootup-and-connecting-via-ssh&#34;&gt;Bootup and Connecting via SSH&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Pis are plugged in, they should automatically boot up. In order to connect to them, I found their IPs from my main computer using &lt;code&gt;nmap&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo nmap -sP 192.168.1.0/24&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;This command may differ depending on your network setup&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Raspberry PIs have &lt;code&gt;(Raspberry Pi Foundation)&lt;/code&gt; in the MAC address lines, and my Banana Pi had &lt;code&gt;bananapi&lt;/code&gt; in the host name. Once I had the IP addresses, I could ssh in using the default usernames and passwords for the images (the user/pass should be listed on the sites). After logging in for the first time, each PI prompted me to change the password (as it should).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;adding-a-sudo-user&#34;&gt;Adding A Sudo User&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When connecting to remote devices, I don&amp;rsquo;t like to be logged in as root, so the first thing I did was setup my user account with sudo privileges, on the two Raspberry Pis (Armbian actually prompted me through these steps the first time I logged into the Banana pi. Kudos to them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add the user, set it&amp;rsquo;s password (important), and then add it to the sudo group, I used the following commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;useradd -m -s /bin/bash ryan
passwd ryan
usermod -a -G sudo ryan&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Yes, I know I can add the user to the sudo group in the `useradd` command, but I prefer to do it with `usermod`. Personal Preference.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. At this point, all of my the PIs are minimally set up accessible. The next steps include updating packages, setting up ssh keys, and configuring &amp;hellip;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ansible.com&#34;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt;. But that will all be in the &lt;em&gt;next post&lt;/em&gt;. See you then!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
