<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>KDE on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/kde/</link>
    <description>Recent content in KDE on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/kde/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Authorizing Thunderbolt 3 on Fedora Plasma</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/fedora-kde-tb3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/fedora-kde-tb3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After buying a &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/new-2019-16inch-mbp/&#34;&gt;16&amp;rdquo; MacBook Pro&lt;/a&gt; the other month,
I&amp;rsquo;ve been using a Thunderbolt 3 hub to connect it to my periphery devices.
Luckily, in addition to the macbook, I am able to use the hub with my my work
laptop when working from home. Normally, it works fine. However, last week I
reformatted the work laptop with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://spins.fedoraproject.org/kde/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;KDE Plasma&lt;/em&gt; spin&lt;/a&gt; of
Fedora Workstation 31&amp;hellip; and my TB3 hub stopped playing nicely with it.
Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-issue&#34;&gt;The Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to a NVIDIA Quadro M1000M in my lenovo P50 work laptop, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using
Gnome with Wayland, because that combination seems to have the least amount of
annoying trade-offs. While doing a system refresh, I figured I would see if
things are any different with a clean Fedora 31 Plasma install (they weren&amp;rsquo;t,
but that&amp;rsquo;s beyond this post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/gnome-tb3-settings.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Gnome Thunderbolt Settings&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/gnome-tb3-settings.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; padding: 5px 15px 10px 10px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Gnome desktop environment now has a thunderbolt pane
in the settings GUI&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Booting into the live cd, and later the installed system, I noticed that my
Thunderbolt 3 hub did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; work while I was in Plasma. That was fine. I
expected it really, because for security reasons Linux distros tend to disable
thunderbolt ports by default.  In gnome, there are now settings to authorize
it (which I guess I had done on my previous install, and forgot about).  In
Plasma however, I needed to install and configure &lt;code&gt;bolt&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bolt&#34;&gt;Bolt&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/bolt-install.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Installing bolt with dnf&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/bolt-install.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; padding: 5px 15px 10px 10px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;bolt&lt;/code&gt; is in the Fedora repos and is easily installed with
&lt;code&gt;dnf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Fedora, &lt;code&gt;bolt&lt;/code&gt; is in the repos (at least in Fedora 31+), so installing it is
easy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo dnf install bolt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once &lt;code&gt;bolt&lt;/code&gt; is installed, it isn&amp;rsquo;t a bad idea to check to make sure it is
running: &lt;code&gt;sudo systemctl bolt&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/bolt-systemctl-status.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;bolt systemctl status&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/bolt-systemctl-status.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; padding: 5px 15px 10px 10px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Checking &lt;code&gt;bolt&lt;/code&gt; is running using &lt;code&gt;systemctl status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the status shows that it isn&amp;rsquo;t running for some reason, it can be started
using &lt;code&gt;systemctl start bolt&lt;/code&gt;. Check the status again, and if it it &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; is not
running&amp;hellip; sorry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/boltctl.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;boltctl&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/boltctl.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; padding: 5px 15px 10px 10px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With bolt installed, the command &lt;code&gt;boltctl&lt;/code&gt; is available to use. The base command will
show information about attached thunderbolt devices. To see more &lt;code&gt;boltctl&lt;/code&gt;
commands, run &lt;code&gt;boltctl --help&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authorizing&#34;&gt;Authorizing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/boltctl-authorize.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;boltctl authorize&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/boltctl-authorize.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; padding: 5px 15px 10px 10px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Authorizing the device&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; the thunderbolt 3 device, it needs to be authorized. To
authorize a device, first use a plain &lt;code&gt;boltctl&lt;/code&gt; command to get the &lt;code&gt;uuid&lt;/code&gt; of
the device. Next, call &lt;code&gt;boltctl authorize&lt;/code&gt; using the &lt;code&gt;uuid&lt;/code&gt; to authorize it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;boltctl authorize &amp;lt;UUID HERE&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The device should now be authorized. When I authorized mine, some of my devices
started showing up automatically, while others needed to be disconnected and
replugged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;enrolling&#34;&gt;Enrolling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/bresetoltctl-enroll.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;boltctl enroll&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/fedora-kde-tb3/boltctl-enroll.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; padding: 5px 15px 10px 10px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Enrolling the device for permanent use&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authorizing a device enables it to be used, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t guarantee persistence.
While this may be desired to grant &lt;em&gt;temporary&lt;/em&gt; authorization to a device, many
users tend want their device to &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; work, without having to manually
authorize it. In this case, the device should be &lt;em&gt;enrolled&lt;/em&gt; (like &lt;code&gt;systemctl enable&lt;/code&gt;).
Simply call &lt;code&gt;boltctl enroll&lt;/code&gt;, with the device UUID:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;boltctl enroll &amp;lt;UUID HERE&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once enrolled, the device&amp;rsquo;s UUID will be recorded and added to a database. By
default, the device will now automatically be authorized whenever it is
connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. While the solution isn&amp;rsquo;t very difficult, it can be frustrating to
figure out when it appears that the thunderbolt device simply is not working.
Regardless, I&amp;rsquo;m glad that I now know about &lt;code&gt;bolt&lt;/code&gt; and how to use it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reset Plasma 5 Monitor Configuration</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/reset-plasma5-monitor-config/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/reset-plasma5-monitor-config/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Extending a laptop&amp;rsquo;s screen to an external display can often be a nightmare.
Sometimes, it might be best to just hit the reset button and configure from
scratch. With KDE Plasma 5, you can. Here&amp;rsquo;s how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;issue&#34;&gt;Issue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I love having a &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/my-t470/&#34;&gt;dock-able laptop&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/new-lgud4379b&#34;&gt;my 43&amp;rdquo; 4k LG
monitor&lt;/a&gt;, getting them configured and agreeing with each other
can sometimes be a headache. Luckily, KDE Plasma 5 (the desktop environment
I&amp;rsquo;ve been using for awhile now) is fantastic and remembers previous display
configurations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when I am playing around with resolutions or multiple inputs,
sometimes I set something that doesn&amp;rsquo;t work&amp;hellip; and it is remembered, causing
more problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fix&#34;&gt;The Fix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, there is an easy fix: just delete the saved profile, and
re-setup the display again. However, I often forget these very simple steps&amp;hellip;
hence, this post (and to help anyone else that needs it, of course :P).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;delete-old-profile&#34;&gt;Delete old profile&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step is to delete the plasma profile that saves the screen settings.
Note, this may remove the profiles for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; previously configured displays,
but I am okay with it for &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; use case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;cd ~/.local.share
rm -rf kscreen&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;extend-monitors-when-docked&#34;&gt;Extend monitors when docked&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/reset-plasma5-monitor-config/extended-monitor.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The KDE Plasma 5 extend display GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/reset-plasma5-monitor-config/extend-monitor.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The KDE Plasma 5 extend display GUI.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After deleting the config, dock or reconnect the laptop to the display. A GUI
with extension layout options should pop up. If it does, select the preferred
layout option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;close-laptop-lid-don-t-disable&#34;&gt;Close laptop lid (don&amp;rsquo;t disable)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After extending the display, I usually try to make the monitor the primary
display and disable the laptop screen. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to work (It causes my
monitor to blank). However, I have learned that if I simply &lt;em&gt;close my laptop
lid&lt;/em&gt; once it is connected&amp;hellip; it does both of those things for me. I always
forget this&amp;hellip; but now it&amp;rsquo;s documented!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;optional-reset-kscreen&#34;&gt;(Optional) Reset kscreen&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After flipping around the displays so much, plasma shell may have gotten a bit
frazzled. If so, just reset it using the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;kquitapp5 plasmashell &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; kstart plasmashell&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to execute this in krunner (alt-F2) so that it runs in the background,
and because I can usually still get to krunner, even if something goes terribly
wrong with plasmashell during the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. While this post is rather short (for once), hopefully it will be useful. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating from Solus to Fedora for now</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/solus-to-fedora/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/solus-to-fedora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For awhile, I have been debating the idea of switching back to Fedora (from Solus). At least on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#alakazam&#34;&gt;main computer&lt;/a&gt;. First, let me state this right up front: I am still &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; satisfied with Solus. I think it is one of the best current Linux distros, and I want to still contribute to the project. However, there are a few reasons why Solus isn&amp;rsquo;t the best fit for my needs &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;, and I will highlight them below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-switch&#34;&gt;Why Switch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Solus and Fedora Logos&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/solus-to-fedora/logos.png&#34;  style=&#34;max-width: 85%;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The Solus (Left) and Fedora (right) Project Logos&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phrase stated on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://getsol.us&#34;&gt;Solus Project homepage&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;ldquo;Solus is an operating system that is designed for &lt;strong&gt;home computing&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo; I find this to be true, and Solus does a great job at it. The Linux community needs a few good, focused, distros. While I have been using Solus for my &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;home&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; computing, the computing tasks I&amp;rsquo;ve focused on recently do not fall into the category of standard &lt;em&gt;home computing&lt;/em&gt; use. Recently, my main top computing activities and goals are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing (okay&amp;hellip; but still)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running all sorts of VMs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying various Server Technologies

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ZFS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KVM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Containerization Technologies (LXC, Docker, &amp;hellip;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ansible and other automation tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning about Clustering

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenMP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Availability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distributed File systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying to get involved with some other Open Source Projects

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fedora (Infrastructure, Dev)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NixOS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, many of the above items are not desktop based, but really
&lt;em&gt;server&lt;/em&gt; based operations. Solus is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a server distribution, as it doesn&amp;rsquo;t
&lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to be one. Which is a good thing. It is focused on its audience. I
just happen to not be in that audience at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, one of my goals for the near future is to transform my long-time Proxmox server into a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.centos.org/&#34;&gt;CentOS&lt;/a&gt; box. Using Fedora on my main workstation does help me get accustom to that environment. It also allows me to more accurately test out ideas before I plan the big move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I had been eyeing up the Plasma desktop, and wanted to try that out again. At the time of writing this post, Solus doesn&amp;rsquo;t fully support the Plasma desktop (yet). However, Fedora &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://spins.fedoraproject.org/kde/&#34;&gt;KDE Plasma Desktop Spin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-switch&#34;&gt;The Switch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Solus and Fedora Logos&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/solus-to-fedora/fedora25.png&#34;  style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Screenfetch on my new Fedora Install&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I eventually (and somewhat sporadically), made the switch to Fedora. I switched
the week before the 26 release, so I decided to start with 25, and then upgrade
later (although I did test out 26 on my other laptop). This let me ensure that
the 26 issues were ironed out before upgrading. I also got to test out the &lt;code&gt;dnf&lt;/code&gt;
system upgrade process. I recorded &lt;em&gt;post-switch&lt;/em&gt; notes during the last few weeks
to document how everything went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Well&amp;hellip; I did it. I switched to Fedora on Alakazam yesterday. I went with the
Fedora 25 KDE spin and did all of the hoops to get that up and going. Not only
is it taking some time to get used to Fedora again, but I am needing to
reacquaint myself with the KDE environment&amp;hellip; it does seem different that other
Plasma setups I&amp;rsquo;ve used in the past&amp;hellip; But I like it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got used to it in no time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alakazam is doing well on Fedora. I&amp;rsquo;ve been enjoying it and think I will stay on
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;updates&#34;&gt;Updates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran some updates that I thought &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be problematic, based
on &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/back-on-arch/#fedora&#34;&gt;previous issues&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered with Fedora. I
made sure to note the results as well. The first notable update was from the
first time I updated the kernel, and the second was  upgrading from
Fedora 25 to 26. Both updates went very smoothly without any issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;kernel-upgrade&#34;&gt;Kernel Upgrade&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am about to do my first Kernel update since being on Fedora again (on
Alakazam). We&amp;rsquo;ll see how the video drivers respond&amp;hellip; To note, I am still on 25
so it hopefully won&amp;rsquo;t be too bad&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;reboot&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No issues whatsoever :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;upgrade-to-fedora-26&#34;&gt;Upgrade to Fedora 26&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/solus-to-fedora/fedora26-upgrade.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Solus and Fedora Logos&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/solus-to-fedora/fedora26-upgrade.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I upgraded my Fedora 25 Plasma Install to Fedora 26&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than some odd issues with the GUI tool, the upgrade from 25 to 26 was
smooth and uneventful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just upgraded Alakazam from Fedora 25 KDE, to Fedora 26 this morning. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t really get the
graphical installer to start, but that could be because I have several desktop environments setup
(Plasma &amp;amp; Gnome), so it may have been confused (I was using the Gnome Software App in Plasma&amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just did the upgrade using the (command line) dnf upgrade tool, like I normally use, and it worked
wonderfully. It even looks like my nvidia drivers stayed and my monitors were configured correctly
after rebooting. The only difference is I don&amp;rsquo;t seem to have the same Plasma animations I had
before, but that is fine, and likely part of the update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that it. Those are my reasons for switching (for now), and the results of my
switch. I am still happy with Fedora, at least on Alakazam, and will likely
remain on it until I have a convincing reason to leave.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying Out the Plasma 5 Desktop Environment</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/trying-out-plasma5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/trying-out-plasma5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After watching the continued development of the Plasma 5 desktop
environment from a distance, I determined I needed to give it another
try. It was just before version 5.6 was released, and the project
appeared to be finding it&amp;rsquo;s stride. Right up front, I want to come
clean and admit that I have never really liked the KDE/Plasma desktop
environment (more on that below). However, with that said&amp;hellip; I am still
using the plasma desktop on my main computer (months later, and
haven&amp;rsquo;t aborted yet**&amp;hellip;). Here are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-history-with-kde-plasma&#34;&gt;My History with KDE/Plasma&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as I said above, &lt;em&gt;I have never really liked KDE (now Plasma)&lt;/em&gt;. In
fact, sometimes I down right &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; it. It is a great project, and I
&lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to like it. It has so many features and is amazing
for power users. I have tried it again and again, desperately wanting
to be swept off my feet, but it&amp;rsquo;s design always kept me bolted to the
ground. The theming made me feel like I was using a Fisher-Price
operating system (which is ironic, because like I said&amp;hellip; the plasma
desktop is probably one of the best power user environments out
there). The bulky features always made it feel childish. So, with that
said&amp;hellip; I have been using using the Plasma desktop on all of my
personal computers for several months. Here are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The theming has come a long way&lt;/strong&gt;. It no longer looks like a
child&amp;rsquo;s toy. Even the default theme is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; appealing. Also, it
has &lt;em&gt;dark themes&lt;/em&gt;, which I am always a fan of.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/plasma-desktop/default-plasma.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Default KDE Plasma 5.6 Desktop&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/plasma-desktop/default-plasma.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I Love the customization.&lt;/strong&gt; I love the level of customization
the plasma desktop allows. I can set transparency, add/remove
panels or widgets, set custom keybindings (very important to me),
and a bunch of other operations very easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/plasma-desktop/settings.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Plasma Settings&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/plasma-desktop/settings.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lets me hide window bars&lt;/strong&gt; One customization I love is the ability
to hide the window bars. I am not a fan of window bars, because I
think they look clunky and just take up space. One feature I like
about many tiling window managers is it is usually very easy to hide
the window bars. However, that isn&amp;rsquo;t always the case in Desktop
Environments, but I was pleased with how easy it was to do it in
Plasma.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It Lets me create an awesome-wm environment, but as a full DE&lt;/strong&gt;
Similar to above, I am able to implement some of the features I love
about tiling window managers like awesome and i3, but with the full
desktop environment. In addition to removing window bars, I like to
easily move and resize windows by hitting the meta or alt key and
left/right clicking the windows. Again, in Plasma this was simple.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I love krunner. A lot.&lt;/strong&gt; I like using application launchers, and
krunner looks nice, is lightning fast, and gets the job done. I
didn&amp;rsquo;t really know much about krunner during previous attempts at
using KDE. This was definitely contributor to why I liked it much
more this time around.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/plasma-desktop/krunner.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Plasma Settings&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/plasma-desktop/krunner.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ability to use old-school animations is fun&lt;/strong&gt; There is not much to say
here. While not very practical, sometimes spinning a desktop cube is
just straight up &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/plasma-desktop/cube.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Desktop Cube&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/plasma-desktop/cube.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fast. Even for a full DE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-monitor support. WTF.&lt;/strong&gt; This was by far the biggest issue I
had. My main computer is a 17&amp;rdquo; laptop that I connect to two 24&amp;rdquo;
displays. However, because it is a indeed a laptop, I sometimes move
it around and be semi-mobile with it. This requires disconnecting the
monitors and going from 1 screen to 3 or vice-versa. Well it turns
out that this is usually a pain in the ass for me in Plasma. First,
I have to configure the monitors one-by-one, hitting &amp;ldquo;apply&amp;rdquo; between
each configuration (it doesn&amp;rsquo;t like when I try to move and place all
3 displays in one swoop). Second, once I setup the screen placement,
the panels often go crazy and can&amp;rsquo;t be found, or I have to play
with them to set them up correctly. Lastly, sometimes the displays
overlap each other oddly, even though they appear normal in the
display settings. The wallpapers almost never set correctly and my
right-click menu is disabled on some screens but not
others. Basically, it&amp;rsquo;s just a hot mess and the most infuriating
problem I faced when using Plasma. If I used a laptop without
monitors, or even a permanent desktop setup, I would be
fine. However, that is not my use case.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/plasma-desktop/wtf-multi-monitor.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Plasma Settings&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/plasma-desktop/wtf-multi-monitor.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Randomly just stops working&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes, KDE applications just
crash and I can&amp;rsquo;t seem to get them back. Widgets seemed to beak
things more frequently, so I just stopped using them. (Again, not a
good solution)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A full DE&lt;/strong&gt; While I said above that it was nice having an
environment that resembled a window manager, but had the benefit of
the full suite of applications that come with a desktop environment,
sometimes it was also a pain. There&amp;rsquo;s just a lot of crap that I
don&amp;rsquo;t use. The obvious reminder of this was when I would run
&lt;code&gt;pacman -Syu&lt;/code&gt;, and see that the massive KDE stack would need
updates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sometimes all the settings can be very confusing&lt;/strong&gt; Having all
these options is great, but sometimes it was
overwhelming. Additionally, the settings felt disjointed and I
didn&amp;rsquo;t know where the settings for some things where.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can finally use Plasma&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very fast and lightweight for all that it is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Still has a bit of stability/polish work to go&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** &lt;i&gt;Update: I took forever to get this post out and I have actually
moved off of Plasma. I just couldn&amp;rsquo;t handle the multi-monitor issues I
had. However, I will definitely be trying out the Desktop Environment
again in the future (I moved to i3-gaps for now. I love my tiling
window managers :) )&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
