<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Notes on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Notes on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © Ryan Himmelwright. Site created with Hugo</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My Emacs Config</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/emacs-config/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/emacs-config/</guid>
      <description>Table of Contents  Repos &amp;amp; Core Packages  Melpa Setup use-package if isn&#39;t already   Core Setup  Basic Stuff Themes   Evil Mode Ivy Key Bindings Writting  Org Mode Markdown   Development  Auto Complete Indentation Parens Git Projects Pretty Code   My Random Functions  Zoom-Window eshell-clear-buffer   Load Other Configs  Work Settings Linux   The Rest  Auto Generated Stuff Theme Load      So I just learned about the org babel stuff, and I think I might save my emacs configuration in an org file like this, and then have emacs just load it with org-babel&amp;#x2026; It deff makes it easier to navigate around the file&amp;#x2026;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transitioning Server from Proxmox</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/server-transition-plan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/server-transition-plan/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been planning to move my server from Proxmox to just a normal server install, to give me more control over everything. However, I don&amp;rsquo;t want this to be like the wild west of servers, where it is basically just a desktop with a bunch of crap on it. I like how easy it is to spin up both containers and VMs, and then continue to monitor/manage everything.
So, I am creating a list of things I want to have at least somewhat figured out before officially making the switch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/emacs-config.md/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/emacs-config.md/</guid>
      <description>&amp;#x2014; title: &amp;ldquo;My Emacs Config&amp;rdquo; date: 2018-03-05 type: homelab layout: homelab-page &amp;#x2014;
So I just learned about the org babel stuff, and I think I might save my emacs configuration in an org file like this, and then have emacs just load it with org-babel&amp;#x2026; It deff makes it easier to navigate around the file&amp;#x2026;
## Melpa
Melpa is the big package repo that nearly everything can be found. It&amp;rsquo;s a must for emacs configs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/focus-account/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/focus-account/</guid>
      <description>Notes on making a locked down account for Focusing:
 No Sudo Disabled su for the account using PAM I needed to add user groups to get the desktop stuff working Plan on using PAM more Need to figure out how to prevent ssh on other accounts to effectively do su  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/lxd-quickstart/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/lxd-quickstart/</guid>
      <description>Notes to eventually write an LXD/LXC quickstart post. Install On Solus, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find it, but then learned it was in the snap store, so I just install it from there and it seems to be working well :)
Images Launch Exec Issues Network I had a slight issue today where my containers didn&amp;rsquo;t have IP address, and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get them to. As such, they didn&amp;rsquo;t have an internet connection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/postgresql/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/notes/postgresql/</guid>
      <description>Notes for Postgresql
Install Just installed from the repos at first&amp;hellip; was in Solus.
Pulling down for latest Went to website and got commands to pull down latest for Centos (I&amp;rsquo;m using an lxc container). The website has you choose what system you are on, and customizes the commands for you, which is nice :) .
Init DB sudo /usr/pgsql-10/bin/postgresql-10-setup initdb  I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure how to do this on Solus, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>