<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Homelab on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/homelab/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Homelab on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © Ryan Himmelwright. Site created with Hugo</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/homelab/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Nginx as a Reverse Proxy to Forward Sub-Domains</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/nginx-subdomain-reverse-proxy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/nginx-subdomain-reverse-proxy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month, Rebecca and I moved to Durham, North Carolina. As a
result, I&amp;rsquo;ve had to re-setup our home network. In years past, I setup
a virtual machine running &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nginx.com/&#34;&gt;Nginx&lt;/a&gt; as a
reverse-proxy (Tangela), and I decided to do that again on the new
network. While it is a simple process, it is one that other people often
ask me about. So, this time&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m taking notes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying Out Seafile</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/trying-out-seafile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/trying-out-seafile/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In college, I mostly used Dropbox to handle all of my file syncing needs. As I
approached graduation, I setup an Owncloud droplet (which is now a Nextcloud
instance) to supplant my Dropbox usage. While it has worked fairly well, I&amp;rsquo;ve
been watching &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.seafile.com/en/home/&#34;&gt;seafile&lt;/a&gt; from a distance the
last few years, but haven&amp;rsquo;t taken the time to try it out. I have now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker Quick Start</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/docker-quickstart/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/docker-quickstart/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months (particularly over the holiday season), I started to
explore and learn several technologies I&amp;rsquo;ve had my eye on the last few years.
First on the list: &lt;a href=&#34;https://docker.io&#34;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;. These days, Docker has a massive
ecosystem surrounding it, and can take years to truly master. This post on the
other hand, will &lt;em&gt;hopefully&lt;/em&gt; help you get up and playing with docker containers in
just a few minutes. Lets get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living the Dock Life: My Thinkpad T470</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/my-t470/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/my-t470/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my previous post, I discussed how I sold off my System76 Bonobo laptop, and
 planned to replace it with a new computer. Well, I did&amp;hellip; awhile ago. For the
 last few months, I have been using a Lenovo T470 Thinkpad (with dock) as my new
 daily driver. Here are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sold My Bonobo</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/sold-my-bonobo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/sold-my-bonobo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last fall, I did something I didn&amp;rsquo;t think I would do anytime soon&amp;hellip;. I sold my
main workstation computer. Specifically, my System76 Bonobo Extreme laptop.
Several events over the last year have led me to the realization that my
&lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; computing &lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt; are drastically different than what they were when I
purchased the Bonobo in early 2015. This post will highlight some of those
realizations, and why I ultimately decided to sell my Bonobo laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Reverse SSH Tunnels</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/simple-reverse-ssh-tunnel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/simple-reverse-ssh-tunnel/</guid>
      <description>Last week, I was on vacation with my family. While I didn&amp;rsquo;t work a ton on personal projects, I was at least able to spend some time on my TunelBeacon project again. I will write a dedicated post about that project down the road when I am further along. Basically, it will be a simple GUI to create reverse ssh tunnels, that family and friends can startup in order grant me temporary access to their computer when they need support.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Encountered Issues Setting Up Ubiquiti Network</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/issues-setting-up-ubiquiti-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/issues-setting-up-ubiquiti-network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past weekend, I setup my new ubiquiti network. It actually took up a good
portion of Sunday, because I ran into a few minor issues.
Fortunately/Unfortunately, these issues were mostly because it my first time
configuring this type of setup, and there was a lot of trial and error. The basic
network is now all configured and has been running great. It was a good day and I
learned a lot :). In fact, I am confident that if I had to start over from
scratch, the process would take me about 10-15 minutes. Just to be sure, I&amp;rsquo;m
 going to quickly jot down the major pain points I experienced my first time around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Home Network Ubiquiti Upgrade</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/upgrading-network-to-ubiquiti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/upgrading-network-to-ubiquiti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I went back to Pennsylvania for a week to attend my college swim
team reunion, and my brother&amp;rsquo;s high school graduation. While I was away, the
wifi-router Rebecca and I were using decided to die (of course). When I returned, I
setup our old router as a &lt;em&gt;temporary&lt;/em&gt; fix. It was terrible. So, I began
researching how I should upgrade our network. This time around, I am doing this
&lt;em&gt;correctly&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating the Pi Cluster with Ansible</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/updating-pi-cluster-with-ansible/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/updating-pi-cluster-with-ansible/</guid>
      <description>With Ansible configured on the Pi cluster, it is time to have it do something useful. When working with a clustered system, even the simplest tasks become tedious and time consuming. For example, updating the system. While I could manually update each of the 3 pi nodes, it is not scalable to 10 or 30 nodes, let alone hundreds or thousands. Tools like Ansible, make doing tasks such a supdating clustered systems, trivial again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Configuring Ansible on the Pi Cluster</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/ansible-on-pi-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/ansible-on-pi-cluster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/posts/Setting-up-the-pi-cluster/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I pieced together my &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/pages/homelab/#cluster&#34;&gt;pi cluster&lt;/a&gt;, and installed variations of Ubuntu 16.04 Server on each of its nodes. With the cluster built, I quickly needed an easy way to maintain and interact with the system as a whole. This, is where &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ansible.com/&#34;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt; comes in. In this post, I will walk through the steps I took to setup Ansible on my Cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Up My Pi Cluster</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/setting-up-the-pi-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/setting-up-the-pi-cluster/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a Raspberry Pi 2, a Raspberry Pi 3, and a Banana Pi. A while ago, I constructed a small tower to house my pi devices. Since then, I have additionally acquired a power source, and some CAT6 cable to connect them all up to a switch. I hope to use the Pis as a mini clustered environment, where I can learn (and play) with some of the &amp;ldquo;Devops&amp;rdquo; technologies/techniques out there. This post will briefly explain the initial setup of &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#cluster&#34;&gt;my cluster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ZFS Snapshot Backups to an External Drive with LUKS</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/zfs-backups-to-luks-external/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/zfs-backups-to-luks-external/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been using &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ZFS&#34;&gt;ZFS&lt;/a&gt; data pools to store data on &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#ninetales&#34;&gt;my server&lt;/a&gt; for some time now. As great as that is, I am ashamed to admit that I have not had a &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; backup system in place (raid/mirrors are not backup). I have a backup solution that I have attempted in the past, but ran into an issue and let it drift to the side. That changes now. It&amp;rsquo;s time to revisit my solution, and complete it to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>