<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ergodox on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/ergodox/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ergodox on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/ergodox/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My new Ergox-EZ Keyboard -- Initial Thoughts</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/ergodox-ez-initial-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/ergodox-ez-initial-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Several weeks ago, I wrote about how I &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/decided-to-get-an-ergodox/&#34;&gt;decided to purchase an
ergodox-ez&lt;/a&gt; split keyboard. In that
post, I omitted any details about what configuration I ordered,
as well my impressions about the board. Now that I have been an
ergodox owner for&amp;hellip; wow, over two months&amp;hellip; I guess this post is
due. Here are my &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;initial&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo; thoughts of the ergodox-ez&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ordering-and-shipping&#34;&gt;Ordering and shipping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/both_boxes.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Boxes my ergdox came in&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/both_boxes.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The boxes the ergodox-ez shipped in&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what ergodox did I order? After a few hours toggling the
configuration tool and endless internal debating, I eventually settled on an
ergodox-ez &lt;em&gt;glow&lt;/em&gt; (backlit keys), with a black body, and black printed, LED
compatible, key caps.  With a narrowed selection of switch options (to maintain
backlit key compatibility), I landed on Cherry MX Browns as my best choice. I
wanted a noticeable tactile bump, but didn&amp;rsquo;t want &amp;ldquo;click-y&amp;rdquo; keys. I prefer a
lower &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Clack&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;, while typing and find the higher pitch of MX Blues annoying.
I decided that I might as well go all in with this keyboard, so I ordered the
tenting poles and black wrist rests as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With everything decided, I placed my order and prepared myself to wait
in anticipated glee for&amp;hellip; an average of 3 weeks shipping time ಠ_ಠ. &lt;em&gt;Luckily&lt;/em&gt;,
I was fortunate and about a week later, I had a large, flat box show up at my
door!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_box_plastic.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Opened the ergodox box&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_box_plastic.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Opening the main box&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything was very well packaged. The keyboard came in one box, and the wrist
rests had their own. The two boxes had the same width, so they could be shipped
as one unit. Lifting the lid on the larger box, I was greeted by the keyboard
looking back at me through a plastic panel, with it&amp;rsquo;s accessories (cables, key
switch pulled, screws) neatly pinned around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;setup&#34;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial &lt;em&gt;physical&lt;/em&gt; setup was quite simple. I took everything out of the
box, connected the two haves of the board together with the included TRRS
cable, and then used the mini usb cable (also included) to connect right half
of the board to my laptop&amp;rsquo;s usb port. I positioned the wrist-rests and tweaked
the tenting poles to some arbitrary position, acting as if I knew what I was
doing.  That was it. After that point, I was able to type&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip; into my
computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;initial-layout-changes&#34;&gt;Initial Layout Changes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_defalut_layout.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The ergodox default layout&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_default_layout.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The default ergodox layout&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;, because I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to just pick up the board
and feel 100% comfortable like one might with a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo;
keyboard. There was definitely a learning curve (more on that later).  However,
the main problem was that I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know the &lt;em&gt;default layout&lt;/em&gt;. The
back-lit QWERTY keys were labeled, but all of the modifier keys on the sides
and in the thumb clusters were not. So, I navigated online to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ergodox-ez.com/pages/oryx&#34;&gt;oryx
configurator&lt;/a&gt; with two goals in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To learn the standard layout that the board shipped with, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To alter some of the defaults with changes I &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; I would want (caps lock as a ctrl, for example)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few minutes of scanning and tweaking, I had my first layout to flash.
I downloaded the file&amp;hellip; and ran into my only &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; issue I&amp;rsquo;ve experienced with the
ergodox&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;issues-with-wally&#34;&gt;Issues with Wally&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_macbook.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Using the ergodox with my Macbook Pro&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_macbook.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Using the ergodox-ez with my MacBook Pro&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was able to flash the firmware using my macbook, for some reason my
Fedora laptops and desktop had issues at first. I would open up
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ergodox-ez.com/pages/wally&#34;&gt;wally&lt;/a&gt; (ZSA&amp;rsquo;s firmware flashing tool), load the
firmware file, and press the tiny &amp;lsquo;reset&amp;rsquo; button on my keyboard with a
paper-clip&amp;hellip; and it would freeze. The back lights stopped their colorful
dancing and key presses rendered no response. The only way
to get the board to respond again was to unplug and replug it back in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had heard that ZSA had good customer support, so I emailed them about my problem.
They responded right away and helped to debug what might be happening.  It
appeared to be some sort of permissions issue, although to this day I&amp;rsquo;m not
100% sure what it actually was. Eventually, it started working. Since then I
have updated most of my computers to Fedora 33, and I use a newer version of
Wally. I haven&amp;rsquo;t had trouble since, even on fresh OS installs. It just works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh well, problem resolved I guess? My main takeaways from the experience were
that 1) wally definitely requires &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; root permissions, and 2) that ZSA&amp;rsquo;s customer
support is wonderful.  Oh, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zsa/wally&#34;&gt;open source
firmware&lt;/a&gt; is the best, but I already knew that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: ZSA has since updated the Linux README instructions to contain the udev
instructions they gave me)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-used-to-and-learning-the-board&#34;&gt;Getting used to and learning the board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously stated, I knew I would have to put some effort into learning how
to type on the ergodox. When I got it, I did a fair bit of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.keybr.com&#34;&gt;typing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.typeracer.com/&#34;&gt;practice&lt;/a&gt; and
used it for work everyday. Within a few days, I was at a passable typing speed,
and after a few more, and I reached a &lt;em&gt;decent&lt;/em&gt; speed. I am not sure if I am any
&lt;em&gt;faster&lt;/em&gt; than on my old keyboard, but I can type fast for much longer (I
could only burst speed-type on the HHKB before starting to cramp up, mostly due to
poor form).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/oryx_trainer.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Oryx Training Tool&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/oryx_trainer.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Oryx Training Tool&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t done any typing practice the last few weeks and I&amp;rsquo;ve started to
notice &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of my bad habits creeping back in. I want to start up
again and might try to use the trainer that is included in the Oryx tool. It is
able to connect to the keyboard to show your layout, and provides several types
of content to type through (code, books, symbols). I might use it to
help determine an optimized coding layer places my most used symbols in easy to
reach places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-like&#34;&gt;What I like&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;customizability&#34;&gt;Customizability&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This board is fully customizable on both the hardware &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; software side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;firmware&#34;&gt;Firmware&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_layout.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Ergodox layout&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_layout.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;One of my custom layer layouts&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being able to tweak the layout of multiple layers means there are an endless
amount of ways I can tailor my keyboard to fit my needs. My tweaking has
slowed down a bit, but I love that I can make quick changes to my layout if I
decide there is a better way to do something. For example, today I realized I wanted to add
a key on one of my alternate layers, so I popped open oryx and wally, and had
the change finished in about a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having an open firmware keyboard is reminiscent of when I &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-on-arch/&#34;&gt;used vanilla arch
linux&lt;/a&gt;. I would go weeks
assuming I had everything required for a typical desktop environment, when all
of sudden, I would try to open a pdf and realize I never installed a pdf
reader&amp;hellip; or a &lt;em&gt;file browser&lt;/em&gt;. Last week while working, I noticed that
my ergodox layout didn&amp;rsquo;t have a &amp;lsquo;delete&amp;rsquo; key. So I quickly added one. Done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: Be aware that I haven&amp;rsquo;t even touched on the advanced layout options,
like macros and long vs short key presses)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;hardware&#34;&gt;Hardware&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/key_switches.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Key switches&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/key_switches.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Testing swapping out a switch with one from my switch
tester&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the firmware, It&amp;rsquo;s nice to know that there is quite a bit I can
    &lt;em&gt;physically&lt;/em&gt; change about my keyboard. Specifically, the key caps can be
    changed and the switches themselves are hot-swappable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve already looked around for some of the parts I could swap out on my board
in a few years if I want to mix things up. For example, I am interesting in
swapping to mx clear switches someday. The problem with clears is the lights
would not (ironically) shine through anymore. I guess that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be too big
of an issue though, because many of the alternative key caps I like are opaque
ツ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anyway&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip; Despite talking about all the hardware upgrades I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; make, I
actually do enjoy it&amp;rsquo;s current configuration. But I do love that I have the
option to change it over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ortholinear&#34;&gt;Ortholinear&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it was more difficult to get used to than I expected, I have found using
an orthlinear layout to be considerably easier to type on. My fingers no longer
fight and trip over each other like Black-Friday shoppers trying to grab the
last hot-ticket item. The &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt; thing about using an ortholinear layout is
that I now want it to become a standard option when buying laptops: ISO or ANSI,
Ortho or Staggard? Unfortunately I don&amp;rsquo;t see that happening anytime soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;split-design&#34;&gt;Split Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/laptop_stand.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Ergodox around a laptop stand&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/laptop_stand.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;A split design keyboard pairs nicely with a laptop stand.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the ortholinear layout, a fully split keyboard is a considerable
ergonomic boost.  I can lay my arms on the desk in whichever way is most
comfortable&amp;hellip; and then position the keyboard to match &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a bonus, the split design pairs nicely with laptop stands, allowing me to
slide the stand closer. This makes it easier to view smaller screens at a
proper height.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;thumb-cluster-keys&#34;&gt;Thumb cluster keys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_wood.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ergodox on wood desk&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_wood.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The thumb cluster of keys has allowed me to better utilize my thumbs, which has been a nice change&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another feature I immediately miss on other keyboards, is thumb keys. It is a
relief to provide my thumbs control over more keys than just the spacebar. The
thumb clusters enable me to offload responsibility for backspace, tab, enter,
delete, and a few other keys from my weakest fingers (pinkies), to my strongest
(thumbs). This makes a huge difference while typing, but is probably the
biggest difficulty I have when switching to a laptop keyboard from my ergodox.
I keep finding myself smashing the spacebar when trying to backspace or enter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-don-t-love&#34;&gt;What I don&amp;rsquo;t love&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, there is not much that I don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; about the ergodox-ez. That
being said, if forced to be picky, here is a thing or two that I don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt;
about it&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-curve&#34;&gt;Learning curve&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/typing_test.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;typing test results&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/typing_test.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Results from one of my typing practices&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest con to getting a keyboard like the ergodox is the learning curve.
It isn&amp;rsquo;t something that you will be able to pick up and immediately start
using.  It will require time and deliberate daily practice to really start to
feel comfortable. If you know this when purchasing, it isn&amp;rsquo;t that big of a
problem, but can be extremely frustrating at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cost&#34;&gt;Cost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is expensive. Especially for a unique board that you might end up hating.
With that said, if the ergodox works for you, the cost isn&amp;rsquo;t as bad as it might
initially appear.  The ergodox-ez is a solid board, with the
ability to customize both it&amp;rsquo;s hardware and firmware over a span of many years.
On top of that, when compared to &lt;a href=&#34;https://kinesis-ergo.com/products/#advantage2&#34;&gt;other &amp;lsquo;ergonomic&amp;rsquo; split
keyboards&lt;/a&gt;, the ergodox is
priced rather fairly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;it-s-difficult-to-switch-back-to-my-hhkb&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s difficult to switch back to my HHKB&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switching to keyboards on my laptops is mostly fine, but for whatever
reason &amp;hellip; I can&amp;rsquo;t type on my HHKB. It feels so squished, and I can&amp;rsquo;t seem to
naturally position my fingers on the correct keys anymore. I&amp;rsquo;m sure if I
dedicate a few hours to using the HHKB this might go away, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t done
that yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_office.jpeg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The ergodox in my home office&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/ergodox-ez-initial-review/ergodox_office.jpeg&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The ergodox-ez in my home office&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I love this keyboard and am very satisfied with my choice. Now that I am used
to it, it feels normal to type on and I don&amp;rsquo;t have to think about it.
The Split design and ortholinear layout make it the most natural feeling
and comfortable board I have used. As a bonus, any layout issues can be stomped
out with a 2 minute config change and flash, ensuring that I should &lt;em&gt;continue&lt;/em&gt;
to love this board even as my preferences change. As long as you are aware of
what you are getting into, I highly recommend the ergodox-ez.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decided to get an Ergodox</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/decided-to-get-an-ergodox/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/decided-to-get-an-ergodox/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the past month, I have been learning to type&amp;hellip; on my new keyboard!  I
decided to purchase an &lt;a href=&#34;https://ergodox-ez.com&#34;&gt;ergodox-ex&lt;/a&gt; and have been using
it ever since. I still &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/new-hhkb-pro2/&#34;&gt;my HHKB&lt;/a&gt;, so why did I get
a new keyboard? And why&amp;hellip; the ergodox?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-keyboard&#34;&gt;Previous Keyboard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/new-hhkb-pro2/got-hhkb.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Getting the HHKB
Keyboard&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/new-hhkb-pro2/got-hhkb.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width:
100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My Happy Hacking Pro Keyboard&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a few years, I have been gladly using a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hhkeyboard.com/uk/products/pro2/&#34;&gt;Happy Hacking Pro
2&lt;/a&gt; keyboard.  Before that, I was
on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://deskthority.net/wiki/HHKB_Lite&#34;&gt;Happy Hacking Lite&lt;/a&gt;, which I
started using while in college. I love the layout of HHK and still think it&amp;rsquo;s
an amazing keyboard. The years I spent on HKBs are why I think &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; keyboard
should have &lt;code&gt;ctrl&lt;/code&gt; instead of a &lt;code&gt;caps&lt;/code&gt; key, or at least switch to two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rationale-for-a-new-one&#34;&gt;Rationale for a new one&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I love my HHKB and have no &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; complaints, there were a few things that
pushed me to start looking at new boards again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-was-getting-the-itch-to-build-one&#34;&gt;I was getting the itch to &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt; one&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial motivation was the slow, growing itch to build a mechanical
keyboard.  It is an itch that I&amp;rsquo;ve felt before. I purchased my HHKB Pro as a
&lt;em&gt;backup&lt;/em&gt; plan when the order for a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://olkb.com/collections/planck&#34;&gt;planck&lt;/a&gt; keyboard kit via  mass.com was
unfortunately cancelled. My &lt;em&gt;original&lt;/em&gt; intention was to learn how to solder (I
even brought a soldering iron), and build the keyboard from scratch. Ultimately buying the
HHKB, I never got to scratch that itch. While I &lt;em&gt;technically&lt;/em&gt; still haven&amp;rsquo;t&amp;hellip;
this is what had me looking at keyboards and browsing
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/MechanicalKeyboards/&#34;&gt;/r/MechanicalKeyboards&lt;/a&gt; again in the
first place&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;wanted-a-program-able-board&#34;&gt;Wanted a program-able board&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;720&#34; height=&#34;405&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5aJ9U5t9oD4?start=557&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The keyboard firmware can be customized on some System76 laptops, as demonstrated during this review.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More important than &lt;em&gt;physically&lt;/em&gt; building a keyboard, I wanted to be able to
&lt;em&gt;programatically&lt;/em&gt; build it. That is to say, play with custom firmware. This is
something that my HHKB doesn&amp;rsquo;t have, but the plank did. The
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mechanicalkeyboards.com/shop/index.php?l=product_list&amp;amp;c=165&#34;&gt;pok3r&lt;/a&gt;,
which I&amp;rsquo;ve considered in the past, also has programmable layers. Even some of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://system76.com/laptops&#34;&gt;System76&amp;rsquo;s laptops&lt;/a&gt; now allow the ability to
remap their keyboards using open firmware (which is awesome!). The
&lt;em&gt;biggest&lt;/em&gt; thing I wanted from a new keyboard was the ability to customize and
program the layers and layouts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-starting-to-learn-proper-touch-typing-i-wanted-to-try-an-ortholinear-layout&#34;&gt;After starting to learn proper touch typing, I wanted to try an ortholinear layout&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in mostly the same space for much of this year, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that my
wrists and arms have really started to tighten up. So, I put my foot down
and decided it was time once again to try and force myself to &lt;em&gt;proper&lt;/em&gt;
touch type&amp;hellip; using all of my fingers. Normally, I slide my hands across the board
and have just a few fingers do the bulk of the work.  This not only creates
unnecessary movement, but also over-strains parts of my hands, building up tension
in my wrists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/decided_to_get_an_ergodox/touch_type_diagram.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;The Minecraft Flathub Page&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/decided_to_get_an_ergodox/touch_type_diagram.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;Proper&amp;rsquo; finger key map for touch typing on a standard
layout&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started typing with proper finger use, I noticed my hands &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; have a
hard time hitting some keys. Particularly the bottom row, especially with my
left hand, gave me trouble. My other fingers commonly blocked the path that the
&amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; finger needed to reach a key. It became obvious why I naturally
adapted to sliding across the board over the years. I wondered if an
ortholinear layout would better allow me to touch type properly, using all of
my fingers. My hope was that the straight grid would let my fingers
slide directly up and down to the other rows, without crossing over and
impeding my other fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-shoulder-pain-increased&#34;&gt;My shoulder pain increased&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last straw, promoting my keyboard urgency to something I &lt;em&gt;needed&lt;/em&gt; to order
&lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, was that my shoulder was beginning to hurt&amp;hellip; all the time. During my
search, I noticed split keyboards and thought they might
help to alleviate some of my pain. The ability to type with my arms
positioned at any width would at least allow me to vary my shoulder angle as
it got sore. So, I switched from looking at DIY kits, to pre-built split
keyboards that I could have shipped and under my fingers much quicker than I
could order and build one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;keyboard-considerations&#34;&gt;Keyboard Considerations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With requirements decided, I started searching for my keyboard. Both of the
keyboards that I considered are made and sold from the same company,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zsa.io&#34;&gt;ZSA&lt;/a&gt;. From what I read online, they were usually highly
recommended, with people rating both ZSA&amp;rsquo;s products and customer service very
well. Personally, I enjoyed reading about their focus on
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ergodox-ez.com/pages/sustainability&#34;&gt;sustainability&lt;/a&gt; and creating open
source products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;moonlander&#34;&gt;Moonlander&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/decided_to_get_an_ergodox/moonlander.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;The Minecraft Flathub Page&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/decided_to_get_an_ergodox/moonlander.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Moonlander&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first keyboard that caught my eye was the new
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zsa.io/moonlander/&#34;&gt;Moonlander&lt;/a&gt;. When I first saw it, it had
&lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; been released. I admired it&amp;rsquo;s floating keys and slim profile.
Apparently, it was designed to be at least somewhat portable, as it comes with
a carrying case. The board seemed to be a fresh new take on the ergodox, with a
clever folding design and some newer features like usb-c.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;720&#34; height=&#34;405&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mWu-_ACpSgY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to dig deep to learn anything about the moonlander as there were only a
handful of people that had them at the time. As I dug, I passively learned
more and more about the ergodox&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ergodox-ez&#34;&gt;Ergodox-EZ&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/decided_to_get_an_ergodox/ergodox_configurator.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;The Minecraft Flathub Page&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/decided_to_get_an_ergodox/ergodox_configurator.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Ergodox-EZ Configurator&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the moonlander, ZSA also builds and sells the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ergodox-ez.com&#34;&gt;ergodox-ez&lt;/a&gt; (and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ergodox-ez.com/pages/planck&#34;&gt;planck
ez&lt;/a&gt;, but I wanted a split board). The
ergodox-ez is a pre-built version of the well-known (to keyboard nerds&amp;hellip;),
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Ergodox-io&#34;&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt;, ortholinear, split keyboard, the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://deskthority.net/wiki/ErgoDox&#34;&gt;ergodox&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved the Moonlander&amp;rsquo;s features and design, but I ultimately
decided to go with the ergodox-ez for a couple of reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Moonlander is brand-new and there wasn&amp;rsquo;t much feedback for it
yet, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LALQsqZP1nA&#34;&gt;whereas&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1GPHiJMS7eo&#34;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/wirecutter/reviews/comfortable-ergo-keyboard/&#34;&gt;is&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://thenextweb.com/insider/2016/03/03/why-this-300-ergonomic-keyboard-might-actually-be-worth-the-money/&#34;&gt;plenty&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rtings.com/keyboard/reviews/ergodox/ez&#34;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mmorpg.com/hardware-reviews/ergodox-ez-this-is-what-powerful-looks-like-2000107228&#34;&gt;information&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://matteeyah.com/ergodox-ez-keyboard&#34;&gt;about&lt;/a&gt; the ergodox-ez.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, because the ergodox has been a popular design for years
now, 3rd-party parts like specialized keycaps sets
can easily be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mass.com/&#34;&gt;mass.com&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mechsupply.co.uk&#34;&gt;other
websites&lt;/a&gt;. This makes the ergodox a bit easier
to customize than the moonlander, at least currently.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ergodox is great starting board for testing out the
orthlinear+split design. If there were parts of it I really hated over the
next few years, I could always switch to a moonlander or another split board that better fits my needs,
based on what I learn from the ergodox.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, if I instead &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; the ergodox design and want &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; in a few
years for some reason, I still have the option to &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt; one.. and &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt;
scratch that itch XD.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a win-win situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ordered the Ergodox-ez and have had it for a over a month now. If you are
wondering what configuration I selected, and what I think about it so far&amp;hellip;
stay tuned for my next post ;) .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
