<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Application on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/application/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Application on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/application/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaving Notion</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/leaving-notion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/leaving-notion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After using &lt;a href=&#34;https://notion.so&#34;&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt; for my notes and daily planning over
the &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/trying-notion/&#34;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;, there are a few issues with it that have
worn on me.  Over time, my uneasiness with the application has built up to the
point where I have decided to switch away Notion completely. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/dahsboard.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;my notion dashboard&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/dashboard.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My Notion Dashboard Page&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before getting into it, I want to first state that for the most part, I have
&lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; using Notion. It took a few iterations of figuring out how I wanted
everything organized, but after my most recent system overhaul, I have it
arranged perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have everything stored in a handful of databases: Areas, Projects, Tasks, and
Notes.  The items in each of these DBs are all linked. For
example, &lt;em&gt;tasks&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;notes&lt;/em&gt; are usually attached to a
&lt;em&gt;project&lt;/em&gt;, which is all associated with a particular &lt;em&gt;area&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Learning&lt;/code&gt;,
*&lt;code&gt;Social&lt;/code&gt;, and so on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most recent iteration, I moved away from linking tasks to a daily journal
object. Instead, I assigned &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; a date, and created dashboard pages
with date filters to see the &lt;em&gt;Weekly&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Daily&lt;/em&gt; boards of my tasks.  All in
all, it was a remarkably efficient system&amp;hellip; most of the time&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-liked-about-notion&#34;&gt;What I liked about Notion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/project_tasks.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;My tasks of a goal&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/project_tasks.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My linked tasks in a goal project&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll run through these quickly, as many of the statements echo my &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/trying-notion/&#34;&gt;original
notion post&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;easy-to-setup-and-use&#34;&gt;Easy to Setup and Use&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can have Notion easily configured on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my devices. All I have to do for
setup, is install the app and log in. I even have the option to access it in a
web browser, if I cannot install it as an app on a device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flexibility&#34;&gt;Flexibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As described in the &lt;em&gt;Background&lt;/em&gt; section above, the flexibility of Notion
allowed me to tailor it to whatever I needed. Notion wasn&amp;rsquo;t a
&lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; itself, as much as it was a &lt;em&gt;tool&lt;/em&gt; that let me build my own system.
It felt like a modern evolution of emacs org-mode for &amp;lsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; people, which is
a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;templates&#34;&gt;Templates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such a malleable system, it helps when the more intricate components can be
automated and simplified. Luckily, Notion has a template system, which is what
really allowed my to custom system to be &lt;em&gt;usable&lt;/em&gt;. My frequent tasks were all
templated to save time when entering them into the system. Without templates,
Notion would have been a giant pain to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;everything-can-be-linked&#34;&gt;Everything can be linked&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed being able to link everything together. Seeing all the associated
tasks and notes of a project in a dashboard was game changing for how I think
about organizing information in a system. As an example, I would plan out
monthly goals and link each task to it. That way, at the end of a month I was
able to go back and see &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; if and when I had completed each task for that
goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-didn-t-like-about-notion&#34;&gt;What I didn&amp;rsquo;t like about Notion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/exporting_data.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Exporting Notion Data&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/exporting_data.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Exporting Notion Data&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;requires-notion-servers-being-available&#34;&gt;Requires Notion Servers Being Available&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notion is completely hosted online and does not have a true solution for
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notion.so/How-can-I-use-Notion-offline-de55148f97c84de3b6e71aa058906be4&#34;&gt;working
offline&lt;/a&gt;.
While this can be &lt;em&gt;convienient&lt;/em&gt; because I don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about syncing data, it
does mean that if the Notion service goes down&amp;hellip; I can&amp;rsquo;t access &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Notion for my tasks, notes, and everything else. When it went down, I
couldn&amp;rsquo;t do &lt;em&gt;basic&lt;/em&gt; actions like check my TODO list, or jot down a quick note
in my system. I had to record everything somewhere else, and then go back later to
transfer it into Notion &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the service was available. While &lt;em&gt;Notion&lt;/em&gt;
didn&amp;rsquo;t go down often, I still faced this problem whenever my internet went
out, or I was traveling and didn&amp;rsquo;t have a connection. Combined, this happened
often enough to be annoyed by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;access-to-the-data&#34;&gt;Access to the data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, all of the data and content resides on Notion servers, and in
a non-standard format. As a result, any important data-related responsibility
fall&amp;rsquo;s entirely on their shoulders, and I have to accept whatever level of
security they choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While data security is very important, my biggest concern is that the
database data is in a weird format. The page content is in markdown-ish,
but the only way to view everything organized properly in the databases (without
hassle, as far as I know), is within Notion.  There are no raw files I can
easily open or convert. They have an exporting system, but every time I tried to
use it, it froze. So even while in theory you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; export everything to &lt;code&gt;md&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;csv&lt;/code&gt; files&amp;hellip;  I couldn&amp;rsquo;t. (&lt;em&gt;Update on this below&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, I am most worried about data formatting. If Notion ever disbands
as a company, or is acquired by a company that slowly shifts direction (or
honestly, if Notion themselves shift the product over time)&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m stuck. If I
want to move to a different system, I can&amp;rsquo;t easily reformat/import the data into
a new system. This alone has been a nagging hesitancy in the back of my head,
the entire time I&amp;rsquo;ve used Notion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/export_in_obsidian.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Exported data in Obsidian&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/export_in_obsidian.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Exported Notion Data in Obsidian Notes&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while taking screenshots, I tried again to export the data. This time, it
made it all the way through the process successfully. I was then able to take
the output and run it through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/connertennery/Notion-to-Obsidian-Converter&#34;&gt;Notion-to-Obsidian-Converter
script&lt;/a&gt; (spoiler
for what I&amp;rsquo;m using now 😆), and import it into an Obsidian vault. While this is
nice to have as an archive, by default it isn&amp;rsquo;t useful in how it&amp;rsquo;s formatted and
would be a lot of work to truly convert all the data. This is mostly due to how
I&amp;rsquo;ve organized by Notion notes, but still&amp;hellip; it is a mess and I don&amp;rsquo;t even know
where to begin in understanding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;buggy-issues-particularly-with-templates&#34;&gt;Buggy Issues. Particularly With Templates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/templates.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;My Notion templates&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/templates.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My Notion templates when creating a new task&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, what ultimately pushed me to the edge and confirmed my decision to
switch away from Notion, was the annoying bugs and glitches I kept experiencing.
Unfortunately, some of my favorite features of Notion, were also my biggest
obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many times when templates just did not work.  I would create a new
 item and apply a template&amp;hellip; but the content would
 &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; load. This was an issue I experienced very frequently. Considering how
 much I relied on templates, I would have to either wait till a later time when
 it would work again, or manually setup everything. Neither of these choices
 were productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last straw, finally inciting action to switch, happened at the end of a week
not too long ago. I noticed mid-week that all of the database links for my
week&amp;rsquo;s items (linking tasks to their projects, or even the link for what &lt;em&gt;area&lt;/em&gt;
a task belonged to)&amp;hellip; were missing. Nothing was connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, this is set automatically with the templates, so I chalked it up to
 template issues, &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;, and manually connected everything. That Friday, I
 had off from work, so I sat down to plan out my vacation day. I quickly noticed
 that the items weren&amp;rsquo;t linked&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;. That was enough. I spent the rest of
 my vacation day researching alternatives for Notion. (and trying to export my
 data&amp;hellip; but I already stated how that (originally) went 😖).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/task_board.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Notion task board&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/task_board.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My Notion Task Board&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Notion is a great product, but with several trade-offs.  I recognize
that many of the items I feel strongly about, won&amp;rsquo;t be concerns for others.
In fact, I was able to overlook many of them &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of how great a tool it
was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year however, my concerns about access to the data have really
been nagging in the back of my mind. Every day that passed, I felt the guilt of
having an ever-growing collection of notes that was equally growing in how
painful it would be to loose/convert if I switched away from Notion. On top of
that, every time I experienced issues with my templates, I wanted to replace
Notion. So now I finally have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a great year using a great tool. Notion is an excellent tool if you
can manage not always having access to it, and if you are okay with the chance
it might all go away someday. But for my planning and notes system, I just can&amp;rsquo;t
afford to use something that doesn&amp;rsquo;t give me ownership of the raw files it uses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using kid3 Audio Tag Editor</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/using-kid3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/using-kid3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I set out to finally clean up and organize my music library.
My goal was to get rid of all the random files, and ensure that every item was
properly tagged so that it would accurately self-organize in the music players I
use. This would not have been possible without the open source tool,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://kid3.kde.org&#34;&gt;kid3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to clean up my music library, I needed a method to edit the metadata
tags of the files. Music applications use these tags to grab information about a
song. For example, a song&amp;rsquo;s title, artist, album name, and release year are all
contained in the a music file&amp;rsquo;s tags.  Using this information, the music
player is able to organize and sort the music by artist, album, year, genre, or
by any other bit of data it knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, I used a tool called &lt;code&gt;easytag&lt;/code&gt; to edit the metadata of my files.
However, after not being able to initially find it (I had the wrong name 😆), I
started to look for a new tool. I needed something easy to use, as I did not
want to waste a bunch of time learning a complicated new tool. After very
little searching, I found &lt;a href=&#34;https://kid3.kde.org&#34;&gt;kid3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kid3&#34;&gt;Kid3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/using-kid3/kid3.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;kid3 window&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/using-kid3/kid3.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;kid3 window&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a &lt;a href=&#34;https://spins.fedoraproject.org/kde/&#34;&gt;Fedora Plasma&lt;/a&gt; user, I was happy to
learn that kid3 appears to be maintained directly by the KDE team.  To use kid3,
just drag and drop the files into it, add/edit any of the tag info, and save.
New tags can also be added if they aren&amp;rsquo;t listed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started using kid3 on my Linux desktop&amp;hellip; but one night I decided to work in
the other room on my macBook. I sadly assumed I would have to find a different
tool to use on macOS. However, while searching a new tool, I learned that kid3
has a macOS build! In fact, in addition to Linux, the KDE team has official kid3
builds for macOS, Windows, and Android! I love a good cross-platform tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;efficiently-editing-album-tags&#34;&gt;Efficiently Editing Album Tags&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/using-kid3/multi-edit.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Editing multiple files in kid3&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/using-kid3/multi-edit.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Editing multiple files in kid3&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After using kid3 it for a bit, I fell into a workflow that made the tedious task
of grouping multiple files into single albums easier to manage. Specifically, I
learned that I could select multiple files, and edit a field to apply to all of
the selected items at one time.  Using this technique, I was able to write the
artist, album, and year only once, instead of 10+ times for each album. This
made it &lt;em&gt;much more&lt;/em&gt; efficient than methods I had previously used while editing
metadata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/using-kid3/tagged_music.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A custom album tagged in kid3&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/using-kid3/tagged_music.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;A &amp;lsquo;home-made&amp;rsquo; file tagged in kid3, now properly sorted in my music player&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all I have. This was a short post, but I think it was worth it. I love
when I find a great open source, cross platform tool that does &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what I
need. Kid3 is a gem application. If you need to edit some audio
tags, check it out. It certainly made my life much easier 🙂.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
