<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fedora on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/fedora/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fedora on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/fedora/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to Solus</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-to-solus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-to-solus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well, that was faster than I expected. This past weekend, I wiped the Fedora installation on my main computer, and replaced it with Solus. My Fedora install broke, and I needed to use a Fedora Live CD to fix it. I thought that if I had to use a live CD to fix the issue, I might as well just do a clean install. With the idea of a clean install in my head&amp;hellip; I thought (possibly influenced by my recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/posts/dabbling-with-go/#motivation&#34;&gt;motivation&lt;/a&gt; to play with Go), that I might as well do the clean install with &lt;a href=&#34;solus-project.com/&#34;&gt;Solus&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nvidia-issues&#34;&gt;Nvidia Issues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;video-container&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IVpOyKCNZYw?start=101&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Linus Torvalds famously flipped off Nvidia during a Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, what I think happened was that my Nvidia drivers got messed up during an update. When I rebooted my computer, my screens were black. This happened no matter which kernel I booted into from Grub. I assumed it was a graphics problem and preceded to switch to another tty to login and fix the problem. I was able to get to a CLI login screen (with the normal &lt;code&gt;user:&lt;/code&gt; prompt) and tried login in. However, after typing in my user name and hitting enter, instead of being promoted for a password, I received an &amp;ldquo;Error Logging In&amp;rdquo; message. So, I tried the same thing with the root user account. Same thing. After typing in a user name, it yelled at me. There was no way to log in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I jumped into the IRC chat and started asking around for advice. As always, everyone was very helpful and tried to help me troubleshoot. They shared my bewilderment. We came to the conclusion that it must of been something with the Nvidia drivers. I was told that it is common to have issues when installing the drivers from Nvidia&amp;rsquo;s web site instead of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://rpmfusion.org/&#34;&gt;RPM Fusion Repos&lt;/a&gt; (I intended to install from the RPM fusion repos, but I went to the nvidia site to find out what version to should use&amp;hellip; and then just downloaded it from there. My bad :P).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I quickly realized that at the very least, I would have to boot up and log into a Live CD to fix the problem. As stated in the intro paragraph, while waiting for the ISO image to download I thought that if I have to load up the CD, I might as well just do a clean Fedora 26 install. A couple minutes later as I was booting up the Live CD, I through that as long as I was reinstalling my OS&amp;hellip; l should consider installing&amp;hellip; Solus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;installed-solus&#34;&gt;Installed Solus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Installing Solus&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-to-solus/install.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Installing Solus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Fedora live environment all booted and ready, I started downloading the latest Solus ISO (Budgie) on my other laptop. Once the ISO image was mounted to a drive, I booted it up and started installing Solus. After the install, I immediately updated because I knew there have been a TON of updates since the last ISO snapshot (mid-April). When I rebooted, I absolutely loved what I saw. It is amazing how much Solus and Budgie have improved, even during my short distro-hopping vacation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at my post history, it may appear as though I used Fedora for a few days, became fed up with it, and came running back to Solus. That is not entirely true. The reality is that I sat on writing my &lt;a href=&#34;../solus-to-fedora/&#34;&gt;Fedora post&lt;/a&gt; for a long time. I used Fedora for about a month, and it was generally a great experience. If it didn&amp;rsquo;t break, I probably would have stayed for a bit longer. When considering a new install though, I realized that I had missed Solus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of now, my plan is to keep using Solus, at least on my main computer. I am also hoping to get more involved with the project, and start packing up some software again. Maybe I can even help with some debugging and development. We shall see&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating from Solus to Fedora for now</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/solus-to-fedora/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/solus-to-fedora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For awhile, I have been debating the idea of switching back to Fedora (from Solus). At least on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../pages/homelab/#alakazam&#34;&gt;main computer&lt;/a&gt;. First, let me state this right up front: I am still &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; satisfied with Solus. I think it is one of the best current Linux distros, and I want to still contribute to the project. However, there are a few reasons why Solus isn&amp;rsquo;t the best fit for my needs &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;, and I will highlight them below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-switch&#34;&gt;Why Switch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Solus and Fedora Logos&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/solus-to-fedora/logos.png&#34;  style=&#34;max-width: 85%;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The Solus (Left) and Fedora (right) Project Logos&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phrase stated on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://solus-project.com&#34;&gt;Solus Project homepage&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;ldquo;Solus is an operating system that is designed for &lt;strong&gt;home computing&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;rdquo; I find this to be true, and Solus does a great job at it. The Linux community needs a few good, focused, distros. While I have been using Solus for my &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;home&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; computing, the computing tasks I&amp;rsquo;ve focused on recently do not fall into the category of standard &lt;em&gt;home computing&lt;/em&gt; use. Recently, my main top computing activities and goals are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing (okay&amp;hellip; but still)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running all sorts of VMs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying various Server Technologies

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ZFS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KVM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Containerization Technologies (LXC, Docker, &amp;hellip;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ansible and other automation tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning about Clustering

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenMP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Availability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Distributed File systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying to get involved with some other Open Source Projects

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fedora (Infrastructure, Dev)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NixOS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, many of the above items are not desktop based, but really
&lt;em&gt;server&lt;/em&gt; based operations. Solus is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a server distribution, as it doesn&amp;rsquo;t
&lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to be one. Which is a good thing. It is focused on its audience. I
just happen to not be in that audience at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, one of my goals for the near future is to transform my long-time Proxmox server into a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.centos.org/&#34;&gt;CentOS&lt;/a&gt; box. Using Fedora on my main workstation does help me get accustom to that environment. It also allows me to more accurately test out ideas before I plan the big move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I had been eyeing up the Plasma desktop, and wanted to try that out again. At the time of writing this post, Solus doesn&amp;rsquo;t fully support the Plasma desktop (yet). However, Fedora &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://spins.fedoraproject.org/kde/&#34;&gt;KDE Plasma Desktop Spin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-switch&#34;&gt;The Switch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Solus and Fedora Logos&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/solus-to-fedora/fedora25.png&#34;  style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Screenfetch on my new Fedora Install&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I eventually (and somewhat sporadically), made the switch to Fedora. I switched
the week before the 26 release, so I decided to start with 25, and then upgrade
later (although I did test out 26 on my other laptop). This let me ensure that
the 26 issues were ironed out before upgrading. I also got to test out the &lt;code&gt;dnf&lt;/code&gt;
system upgrade process. I recorded &lt;em&gt;post-switch&lt;/em&gt; notes during the last few weeks
to document how everything went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Well&amp;hellip; I did it. I switched to Fedora on Alakazam yesterday. I went with the
Fedora 25 KDE spin and did all of the hoops to get that up and going. Not only
is it taking some time to get used to Fedora again, but I am needing to
reacquaint myself with the KDE environment&amp;hellip; it does seem different that other
Plasma setups I&amp;rsquo;ve used in the past&amp;hellip; But I like it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got used to it in no time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alakazam is doing well on Fedora. I&amp;rsquo;ve been enjoying it and think I will stay on
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;updates&#34;&gt;Updates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran some updates that I thought &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be problematic, based
on &lt;a href=&#34;../back-on-arch/#fedora&#34;&gt;previous issues&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered with Fedora. I
made sure to note the results as well. The first notable update was from the
first time I updated the kernel, and the second was  upgrading from
Fedora 25 to 26. Both updates went very smoothly without any issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;kernel-upgrade&#34;&gt;Kernel Upgrade&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am about to do my first Kernel update since being on Fedora again (on
Alakazam). We&amp;rsquo;ll see how the video drivers respond&amp;hellip; To note, I am still on 25
so it hopefully won&amp;rsquo;t be too bad&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;hellip;reboot&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No issues whatsoever :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;upgrade-to-fedora-26&#34;&gt;Upgrade to Fedora 26&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/solus-to-fedora/fedora26-upgrade.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Solus and Fedora Logos&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/solus-to-fedora/fedora26-upgrade.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I upgraded my Fedora 25 Plasma Install to Fedora 26&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than some odd issues with the GUI tool, the upgrade from 25 to 26 was
smooth and uneventful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just upgraded Alakazam from Fedora 25 KDE, to Fedora 26 this morning. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t really get the
graphical installer to start, but that could be because I have several desktop environments setup
(Plasma &amp;amp; Gnome), so it may have been confused (I was using the Gnome Software App in Plasma&amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just did the upgrade using the (command line) dnf upgrade tool, like I normally use, and it worked
wonderfully. It even looks like my nvidia drivers stayed and my monitors were configured correctly
after rebooting. The only difference is I don&amp;rsquo;t seem to have the same Plasma animations I had
before, but that is fine, and likely part of the update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that it. Those are my reasons for switching (for now), and the results of my
switch. I am still happy with Fedora, at least on Alakazam, and will likely
remain on it until I have a convincing reason to leave.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
