<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Organization on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/organization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Organization on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/organization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Back On org-mode For Work</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-on-org-mode-for-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-on-org-mode-for-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month, I wrote about my &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/switched-to-joplin-notes/&#34;&gt;switch to Joplin&lt;/a&gt;
for both my personal and work notes. While I enjoyed many features in Joplin, I
also had a few concerns about using the system long-term for all my notes.
As of last week, I am still using Joplin for all of my personal notes, but have switched
back to &lt;code&gt;org-mode&lt;/code&gt; for my notes at work. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-cases&#34;&gt;Use Cases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To better understand why Joplin works well for me at home but can&amp;rsquo;t effectively
replace org-mode at work, lets first list some different features between Joplin and
emacs org-mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joplin-features&#34;&gt;Joplin Features&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;notes-style-focused&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Notes&amp;rdquo;-Style Focused&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-gui.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-gui.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Joplin uses a traditional &amp;ldquo;note&amp;rdquo; layout, with blank text
boxes organized into notebooks.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joplin organizes notes in a traditional &amp;ldquo;notes&amp;rdquo; style. Each note starts as a
big, blank text-box that the user fills in. These notes are further organized
into &amp;ldquo;notebooks&amp;rdquo;, which are simply a list of one or more notes. The notes are
formatted with markdown, but the application doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to support features
like collapsible sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;simple-markdown-format-sharable&#34;&gt;Simple Markdown Format &amp;ndash; Sharable&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The markdown editor in Joplin may not support collapsing sections, but it does
a great job at supporting other features, like simple code highlighting and web
links. Additionally, being formated in markdown, the note contents can be easily
exported, transferred, or even shared with other applications and/or people.
This is handy when grabbing snippets from the web, which may already be in a
markdown friendly format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;shared-across-computer-and-mobile-devices&#34;&gt;Shared across Computer and Mobile Devices&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-android.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin Android GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-android.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Notebook and Notes views on the Android client.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the Joplin application is available on all platforms (including
mobile), and manages the system to sync the notes across all devices. This
makes it a breeze to write a note at a computer, and then have it immediately
available on a phone afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;org-mode-use-cases&#34;&gt;Org-mode use cases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;logging-style-notes&#34;&gt;Logging-Style Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By comparison, Emacs&amp;rsquo; org-mode can be very &lt;em&gt;task&lt;/em&gt; oriented, allowing for a more
&amp;lsquo;log-style&amp;rsquo; note-taking system. It encourages outline organization of notes,
organized under &amp;ldquo;tasks&amp;rdquo; which can be collapsed in a hierarchy. The
tasks can be marked &amp;ldquo;TODO&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;DONE&amp;rdquo; using the built in TODO system, or
tagged for organization. While org-mode can be used when writing &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; notes, it really
shines when working as a task/note system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;quick-notes-key-bindings&#34;&gt;Quick Notes, Key-bindings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/note-demo.gif&#39;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Demonstration of logging a quick note.&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/note-demo-pre.png&#34; onmouseover=&#34;this.src=&#39;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/note-demo.gif&#39;&#34; onmouseout=&#34;this.src=&#39;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/note-demo-pre.png&#39;&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Notes and code blocks can be easily added using
key-binding shortcuts.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another feature in org mode is the note drawer. By pressing a key combination
(as one tends to do in Emacs), a new buffer will open up to take a note in. The
contents of the note may be text, or even a code snippet (&lt;em&gt;in the emacs mode of
that language&lt;/em&gt;). When done, I can simply press &lt;code&gt;C-c C-c&lt;/code&gt; and the buffer will
close, inserting the note with a time-stamped entry as part of the &lt;code&gt;logbook&lt;/code&gt;
for the task I opened the note in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quick logging feature, along with the power of all the key-binding
customization, makes note logging fast, efficient, and enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;todo-scrum-board-tasks&#34;&gt;TODO/SCRUM Board tasks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/scrum-board.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin Android GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/scrum-board.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;I wrote a package that lets me view org tasks in a
scrum board.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, org-mode has a powerful
&lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/TODO-items.html&#34;&gt;todo&lt;/a&gt; system. Users can configure
how task items should be grouped beyond just a basic &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;DONE&lt;/code&gt;. Using this
flexability (and some lisp knowledge), I wrote an &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/himmAllRight/ry-org-scrum&#34;&gt;scrum board generator for
org-mode&lt;/a&gt;. This package takes all
of my &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt; items, and organizes them into scrum task board. This feature
helps organize my daily and weekly task lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;exporting-archiving-weekly-logs&#34;&gt;Exporting/Archiving Weekly Logs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big &amp;ldquo;feature&amp;rdquo; org mode has that I find lacking in Joplin, is the
ability to better organize long-term sets of notes. With a logging style of
note-taking, notes are often organized by a specific range in time (day, week,
month). These systems are naturally structured hierarchically and Joplin&amp;rsquo;s notebook/note
organization only allows for systems to be 2 levels deep. However, org files are stored
as text files on a traditional file system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, org files can be linked (and exported as html files), so any note can
still be quickly navigated to, even if the archive spans hundreds of note files over
several years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;home-vs-work-notes&#34;&gt;Home vs Work Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now with some of each note system&amp;rsquo;s features broken down, how do they
fit with my preferences across different note taking use-cases? (mostly personal vs.
work)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;home&#34;&gt;Home&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-travel-notes.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin Android GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-travel-notes.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 350px; float: right; padding: 15px 0px 10px 20px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal notes tend to be organized as more traditional notes. I make large
groups, such as &amp;lsquo;Home&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Tech&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Travel&amp;rsquo;, and stash notes into each. In a note,
I tend to organize information on a topic and store it for later. For example,
I may have a notebook for online classes, and then a note for each class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For another example, I have a notebook called &amp;lsquo;Travel&amp;rsquo; which contains a note
for each trip I plan.  In the note, I store information that I will need, such
as flight numbers, or hotel addresses. Below important information, I jot down
ideas while planning and researching before leaving. This may include places to
to eat, or activities I want to do (with links to the websites).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joplin&amp;rsquo;s mobile platform support is particularly useful here, as I am able to
write up notes on my desktop, and then read them from my phone on the go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;work&#34;&gt;Work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, my work notes are a mix of task-list and logbook for each
week. I plan each week by moving &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt; tasks from one day to
the next, and changing the status as I work on each one. As I work, I log notes
under each task about my progress, as well as any issues/solutions I experience
on the way. While the notes are mostly rambling, logging thoughts as I work
helps me to quickly identify issues, and solve problems faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/exported-notes.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;My notes exported as linked html pages&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/exported-notes.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The index page of my exported weekly work notes.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, due to organizing notes by &lt;em&gt;week&lt;/em&gt; rather than topic, it is
best if I can archive the notes in more of a tree layout. Org notes are plain
text files, so I can save them on my hard drive any way I want. For example, I
have my work notes organized as &lt;code&gt;./work/archive/{YEAR}/{MONTH}{DAY}/week-of-{date}.org&lt;/code&gt;.
Each week, I also export the finished notes to linked html files, which is very
useful for going back and looking at my previous notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. I&amp;rsquo;ve switched back to emacs org-notes for my work tasks,
but remain on Joplin for my personal and home notes. So far&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m loving
it. I think that I switched to Joplin because org-mode wasn&amp;rsquo;t ideal for my
personal notes. However, Joplin was lacking for my work
notes. That&amp;rsquo;s okay. I learned that my home vs. work notes are two completely
different use cases, and as a result should use different tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, moving forward, I plan to keep using Joplin for my personal notes, and
emacs org-mode for my work tasks. Perfect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switched to Joplin Notes</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/switched-to-joplin-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/switched-to-joplin-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/org-babel-setup/&#34;&gt;massive fan&lt;/a&gt; of emacs&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/&#34;&gt;org-mode&lt;/a&gt;, it should be no surprise that I&amp;rsquo;ve been using
it for my personal and work planning/notes over the last few years.  However,
as my daily emacs usage has slowly dropped, and the support for &lt;code&gt;.org&lt;/code&gt; files
outside of emacs remains low (other than &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/himmAllRight/dotfiles/tree/master/emacs&#34;&gt;Github README
files&lt;/a&gt;), I started
to look for a more standard system. The last few months, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using
&lt;a href=&#34;https://joplinapp.org/&#34;&gt;Joplin&lt;/a&gt;. Here are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-system-org-mode&#34;&gt;Previous System - Org-mode&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/org-mode-notes.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Emacs with a note opened in org-mode.&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/org-mode-notes.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Emacs with a note opened in org-mode&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, I had been taking all of my notes using org-mode in emacs. Each
week, I made a new &lt;code&gt;.org&lt;/code&gt; file for my work notes, and another for my personal
planning/notes. I would then list my &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/TODO-items.html&#34;&gt;todo
items&lt;/a&gt;, usually grouped by day,
category, or both. I would also
&lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/Tags.html&#34;&gt;tag&lt;/a&gt; each item, for better organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I worked on each task, I could quickly add time-stamped notes using the
built-in &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/Drawers.html&#34;&gt;logbook drawer&lt;/a&gt; shortcut. In
these notes, I would ramble, or paste a code snippet to save for later. As work
on each item progressed, I could set the &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt; status to &lt;code&gt;Working On&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Finished&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Removed&lt;/code&gt;, or any other state I had pre-defined.  Eventually, I
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/himmAllRight/ry-org-scrum&#34;&gt;wrote an emacs-lisp
script/package&lt;/a&gt; that took the
&lt;code&gt;todo&lt;/code&gt; items in my &lt;code&gt;org&lt;/code&gt; file, and dumped them into a SCRUM board at the top of
the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/org-notes-export-pages.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Pictured of org notes exported to HTML&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/org-notes-export-pages.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;org-notes allowed me to link and export my notes to
HTML&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, org files can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/Exporting.html&#34;&gt;exported&lt;/a&gt;
to all sorts of file types (md, html, pdf, latex). By combining the export
feature with &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/Internal-links.html&#34;&gt;internal
linking&lt;/a&gt;, I was able to create
an organized system for my archived notes. I created an &lt;code&gt;index.org&lt;/code&gt; file which
linked to each week&amp;rsquo;s notes. Every week, I would archive the html export of a
note, and add it to the index list. This meant I could browse my old notes as a
website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-liked&#34;&gt;What I liked&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;org-mode&lt;/code&gt; is great.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could take all of my notes in a simple markdown language (org)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good code-block support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note linking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exported to html (or txt, md, pdf, or anything really)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My previous notes were all exported to an archive website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;issues&#34;&gt;Issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to use emacs for any edits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not supported on mobile devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As I used more &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; syntax for other applications, I found myself fumbling between &lt;code&gt;org&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;md&lt;/code&gt; syntax often.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syncing issues (mostly Nextcloud issues. Seafile helped, but it still occurred)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I loved taking notes in org-mode. However, I wanted something that
could be used on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my devices, and was more easily translatable outside of
&amp;ldquo;emacsOS&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-switch-joplin&#34;&gt;The Switch - Joplin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/joplin-window.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Window of the Joplin GUI application&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/joplin-window.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Joplin GUI window (in &amp;lsquo;split mode&amp;rsquo;)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-joplin&#34;&gt;About Joplin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joplin is an open source note-taking and to-do application. It synchronizes and
organizes markdown notes into notebooks, across many platforms (Android, iOS,
macOS, Linux, and Windows). It even has both a GUI &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; terminal client.  So,
I decided to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-setup&#34;&gt;My Setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When configuring joplin, a sync system has to be defined (well, &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;. Notes
can also be saved locally). There are a few supported options including using
Nextcloud. I had previously synced my org notes using Nextcloud, but eventually
moved away from it due to repeated file conflict issues. So I wanted to try
something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/fastmail_logo.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Window of the Joplin GUI application&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/fastmail_logo.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 70%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Joplin GUI window (in &amp;lsquo;split mode&amp;rsquo;)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While researching Joplin, I learned that I could sync notes to the WebDav
server on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fastmail.com&#34;&gt;fastmail&lt;/a&gt; account I have for email. I
wasn&amp;rsquo;t using any of the account&amp;rsquo;s file storage, so I figured I this would be a
good way to get use out of a service I&amp;rsquo;m already paying for. It works great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-like&#34;&gt;What I like&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;syncs-on-all-my-devices&#34;&gt;Syncs on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my devices&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I have enjoyed most about this setup is that my notes sync to all of my
devices. Most importantly, I can &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; the notes on every device. With
previous systems, the files would sync everywhere, but I still couldn&amp;rsquo;t always
easily read them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cli-and-gui-versions&#34;&gt;CLI and GUI versions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I like that Joplin has both a GUI and CLI client. I
mostly use the GUI, but enjoy having the CLI as an option because it means I
can always ssh into a machine and take notes. Additionally, the
cli client allows me to take/edit notes using my own terminal editors such as
emacs &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; vim. This is quite convenient, and I should probably start using
Joplin this way more often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;markdown-note-exports&#34;&gt;Markdown Note Exports&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/export-options.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin cli application&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/export-options.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Export options in Joplin GUI&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that notes are formatted in markdown. This provides some
consistency when writing, but ensures that my notes are in a format that is
standardized. Additionally, joplin allows easy exporting of
the notes to other formats such as &lt;code&gt;json&lt;/code&gt; or as &lt;code&gt;pdf&lt;/code&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;easy-enough-to-use&#34;&gt;Easy enough to use&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, Joplin has been easy to use. After setup, I just have to open the app,
and start typing away (maybe with a sync or two). While my last setup required
the user to be somewhat of an emacs/org guru&amp;hellip; this doesn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;issues-i-m-still-figuring-out-anticipate&#34;&gt;Issues I&amp;rsquo;m still figuring out/Anticipate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/joplin-cli.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin cli application&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/joplin-cli.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Joplin CLI window &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;setup-is-a-pain&#34;&gt;Setup is a pain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While configuring sync can be a pain, it&amp;rsquo;s not my biggest gripe with the Joplin
setup process. It&amp;rsquo;s adding a new system. By default, if I configure a new
device with my sync solution (my laptop or phone for example) and then sync, it
will load up all of the crap default example tags and notes, which then pull
down to all of my systems. This is extremely frustrating because I have to keep
deleting them.  This is multiplied by the fact that it happens with &lt;em&gt;each
client&lt;/em&gt; I setup. So if I setup the gui and cli on my laptop, it will happen
&lt;em&gt;twice&lt;/em&gt; (2x each default tags/notes will show up on all my systems).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Semi-Solution&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;slight&lt;/em&gt; work-around I have been able to use when setting up a new computer
is to simply copy the config files from an existing system to the new one.
These folders can be found at &lt;code&gt;~/.config/joplin/&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;~/.config/Joplin/&lt;/code&gt;, and/or
&lt;code&gt;~/.config/joplin-desktop/&lt;/code&gt;. This also means that the new system &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have less
it needs to sync down from the server on the first sync.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;long-term-archiving&#34;&gt;Long term archiving&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;big&lt;/strong&gt; problem I have&amp;hellip; and think I will continue to have with Joplin, is
the long-term organization of notes. Part of this is my inability to figure out an
efficient and organized way to handle my &amp;ldquo;log&amp;rdquo; notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem partially stems from Joplin&amp;rsquo;s shallow organizational
structure. There are notebooks, and notes. That&amp;rsquo;s it. Unlike having
a file structure where I can do something like
&lt;code&gt;archive/2019/June/Weekly_Plans/&lt;/code&gt;, I can&amp;rsquo;t really go that deep with Joplin, so
I end up just having a single notebook with &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my weekly plan notes listed
in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One remaining solution might be to get more aggressive with the tagging
feature, and see if I can create a more organized system using that. I might be
able to tag each note with a month/year, and then truncate my log notes each
month. The only problem with this is that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like I can select
&lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt; tags at a time, which would mean &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of my notes for a month
will be shown under the tag. That would be a deal breaker for me :( .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, I think that Joplin &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a great open source notes solution.  If
someone needs a system to keep a bunch of normal notes synced across all their
devices, this is it. I however, might need to try out something else long-term.
On the bright side, there are a bunch of features in Joplin that love and will
definitely look for&amp;hellip; in my next solution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
