<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Organization on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/organization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Organization on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/organization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaving Notion</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/leaving-notion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/leaving-notion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After using &lt;a href=&#34;https://notion.so&#34;&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt; for my notes and daily planning over
the &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/trying-notion/&#34;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;, there are a few issues with it that have
worn on me.  Over time, my uneasiness with the application has built up to the
point where I have decided to switch away Notion completely. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/dahsboard.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;my notion dashboard&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/dashboard.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My Notion Dashboard Page&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before getting into it, I want to first state that for the most part, I have
&lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; using Notion. It took a few iterations of figuring out how I wanted
everything organized, but after my most recent system overhaul, I have it
arranged perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have everything stored in a handful of databases: Areas, Projects, Tasks, and
Notes.  The items in each of these DBs are all linked. For
example, &lt;em&gt;tasks&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;notes&lt;/em&gt; are usually attached to a
&lt;em&gt;project&lt;/em&gt;, which is all associated with a particular &lt;em&gt;area&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Learning&lt;/code&gt;,
*&lt;code&gt;Social&lt;/code&gt;, and so on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most recent iteration, I moved away from linking tasks to a daily journal
object. Instead, I assigned &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; a date, and created dashboard pages
with date filters to see the &lt;em&gt;Weekly&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Daily&lt;/em&gt; boards of my tasks.  All in
all, it was a remarkably efficient system&amp;hellip; most of the time&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-liked-about-notion&#34;&gt;What I liked about Notion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/project_tasks.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;My tasks of a goal&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/project_tasks.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My linked tasks in a goal project&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll run through these quickly, as many of the statements echo my &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/trying-notion/&#34;&gt;original
notion post&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;easy-to-setup-and-use&#34;&gt;Easy to Setup and Use&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can have Notion easily configured on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my devices. All I have to do for
setup, is install the app and log in. I even have the option to access it in a
web browser, if I cannot install it as an app on a device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flexibility&#34;&gt;Flexibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As described in the &lt;em&gt;Background&lt;/em&gt; section above, the flexibility of Notion
allowed me to tailor it to whatever I needed. Notion wasn&amp;rsquo;t a
&lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; itself, as much as it was a &lt;em&gt;tool&lt;/em&gt; that let me build my own system.
It felt like a modern evolution of emacs org-mode for &amp;lsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; people, which is
a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;templates&#34;&gt;Templates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such a malleable system, it helps when the more intricate components can be
automated and simplified. Luckily, Notion has a template system, which is what
really allowed my to custom system to be &lt;em&gt;usable&lt;/em&gt;. My frequent tasks were all
templated to save time when entering them into the system. Without templates,
Notion would have been a giant pain to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;everything-can-be-linked&#34;&gt;Everything can be linked&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed being able to link everything together. Seeing all the associated
tasks and notes of a project in a dashboard was game changing for how I think
about organizing information in a system. As an example, I would plan out
monthly goals and link each task to it. That way, at the end of a month I was
able to go back and see &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; if and when I had completed each task for that
goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-didn-t-like-about-notion&#34;&gt;What I didn&amp;rsquo;t like about Notion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/exporting_data.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Exporting Notion Data&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/exporting_data.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Exporting Notion Data&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;requires-notion-servers-being-available&#34;&gt;Requires Notion Servers Being Available&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notion is completely hosted online and does not have a true solution for
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notion.so/How-can-I-use-Notion-offline-de55148f97c84de3b6e71aa058906be4&#34;&gt;working
offline&lt;/a&gt;.
While this can be &lt;em&gt;convienient&lt;/em&gt; because I don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about syncing data, it
does mean that if the Notion service goes down&amp;hellip; I can&amp;rsquo;t access &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Notion for my tasks, notes, and everything else. When it went down, I
couldn&amp;rsquo;t do &lt;em&gt;basic&lt;/em&gt; actions like check my TODO list, or jot down a quick note
in my system. I had to record everything somewhere else, and then go back later to
transfer it into Notion &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the service was available. While &lt;em&gt;Notion&lt;/em&gt;
didn&amp;rsquo;t go down often, I still faced this problem whenever my internet went
out, or I was traveling and didn&amp;rsquo;t have a connection. Combined, this happened
often enough to be annoyed by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;access-to-the-data&#34;&gt;Access to the data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a similar note, all of the data and content resides on Notion servers, and in
a non-standard format. As a result, any important data-related responsibility
fall&amp;rsquo;s entirely on their shoulders, and I have to accept whatever level of
security they choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While data security is very important, my biggest concern is that the
database data is in a weird format. The page content is in markdown-ish,
but the only way to view everything organized properly in the databases (without
hassle, as far as I know), is within Notion.  There are no raw files I can
easily open or convert. They have an exporting system, but every time I tried to
use it, it froze. So even while in theory you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; export everything to &lt;code&gt;md&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;csv&lt;/code&gt; files&amp;hellip;  I couldn&amp;rsquo;t. (&lt;em&gt;Update on this below&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, I am most worried about data formatting. If Notion ever disbands
as a company, or is acquired by a company that slowly shifts direction (or
honestly, if Notion themselves shift the product over time)&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m stuck. If I
want to move to a different system, I can&amp;rsquo;t easily reformat/import the data into
a new system. This alone has been a nagging hesitancy in the back of my head,
the entire time I&amp;rsquo;ve used Notion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/export_in_obsidian.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Exported data in Obsidian&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/export_in_obsidian.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Exported Notion Data in Obsidian Notes&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while taking screenshots, I tried again to export the data. This time, it
made it all the way through the process successfully. I was then able to take
the output and run it through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/connertennery/Notion-to-Obsidian-Converter&#34;&gt;Notion-to-Obsidian-Converter
script&lt;/a&gt; (spoiler
for what I&amp;rsquo;m using now 😆), and import it into an Obsidian vault. While this is
nice to have as an archive, by default it isn&amp;rsquo;t useful in how it&amp;rsquo;s formatted and
would be a lot of work to truly convert all the data. This is mostly due to how
I&amp;rsquo;ve organized by Notion notes, but still&amp;hellip; it is a mess and I don&amp;rsquo;t even know
where to begin in understanding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;buggy-issues-particularly-with-templates&#34;&gt;Buggy Issues. Particularly With Templates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/templates.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;My Notion templates&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/templates.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My Notion templates when creating a new task&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, what ultimately pushed me to the edge and confirmed my decision to
switch away from Notion, was the annoying bugs and glitches I kept experiencing.
Unfortunately, some of my favorite features of Notion, were also my biggest
obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many times when templates just did not work.  I would create a new
 item and apply a template&amp;hellip; but the content would
 &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; load. This was an issue I experienced very frequently. Considering how
 much I relied on templates, I would have to either wait till a later time when
 it would work again, or manually setup everything. Neither of these choices
 were productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last straw, finally inciting action to switch, happened at the end of a week
not too long ago. I noticed mid-week that all of the database links for my
week&amp;rsquo;s items (linking tasks to their projects, or even the link for what &lt;em&gt;area&lt;/em&gt;
a task belonged to)&amp;hellip; were missing. Nothing was connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, this is set automatically with the templates, so I chalked it up to
 template issues, &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;, and manually connected everything. That Friday, I
 had off from work, so I sat down to plan out my vacation day. I quickly noticed
 that the items weren&amp;rsquo;t linked&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;. That was enough. I spent the rest of
 my vacation day researching alternatives for Notion. (and trying to export my
 data&amp;hellip; but I already stated how that (originally) went 😖).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/task_board.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Notion task board&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/leaving-notion/task_board.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My Notion Task Board&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Notion is a great product, but with several trade-offs.  I recognize
that many of the items I feel strongly about, won&amp;rsquo;t be concerns for others.
In fact, I was able to overlook many of them &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of how great a tool it
was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year however, my concerns about access to the data have really
been nagging in the back of my mind. Every day that passed, I felt the guilt of
having an ever-growing collection of notes that was equally growing in how
painful it would be to loose/convert if I switched away from Notion. On top of
that, every time I experienced issues with my templates, I wanted to replace
Notion. So now I finally have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a great year using a great tool. Notion is an excellent tool if you
can manage not always having access to it, and if you are okay with the chance
it might all go away someday. But for my planning and notes system, I just can&amp;rsquo;t
afford to use something that doesn&amp;rsquo;t give me ownership of the raw files it uses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying out Notion</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/trying-notion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/trying-notion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past year or two, my notes and planning systems have been a bit of a
jumble.  It started when I attempted to switch everything to &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/switched-to-joplin-notes/&#34;&gt;joplin
notes&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip; only to eventually switch &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/back-on-org-mode-for-work/&#34;&gt;back to
org-mode (for my work notes)&lt;/a&gt; a few months
later. Around that same time, I also started using &lt;a href=&#34;https://trello.com&#34;&gt;trello&lt;/a&gt;
to organize my personal and home life task boards. This system has worked well, but
feels very disjointed. My notes, goals, and tasks are spread all over the place.
This might all be about to change. I&amp;rsquo;ve started using
&lt;a href=&#34;https://notion.so&#34;&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;quick-history&#34;&gt;Quick History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving into my experience with Notion, lets first describe in more
detail the system I&amp;rsquo;m coming from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;previous-system&#34;&gt;Previous System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-notion/trello_weekly_board.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Trello Weekly Board&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-notion/trello_weekly_board.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My Trello Weekly Task Board&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most recently, my personal and professional notes, and task planning systems
have consisted of three applications: Trello, Emacs (org-mode), and Joplin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trello&lt;/strong&gt;: I had several boards for planning my weekly, monthly, and
multi-month personal tasks (including household ones). I also maintained a few
boards to keep track of goals and projects ideas (ex: future website posts, books to
read, training courses to take, etc).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emacs org-mode&lt;/strong&gt;: For my professional work life, I completed all the same tasks I
listed under the trello section, using emacs instead.  I would write down my
tasks, and log quick notes and thoughts under each one while I was working on
it. Logging helps me think through problems, and serves as a reference
later. While I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; log notes into Trello cards, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t nearly as easy to
quickly open up and record a stream of consciousness, as it is was in org mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joplin&lt;/strong&gt;: I previously attempted to make Joplin my universal planning system,
but it failed. It was a bit messy for a universal system, and lacked a
board style layout for  my goals and task planning (what Trello or even my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/himmAllRight/ry-org-scrum&#34;&gt;ry-org-scrum&lt;/a&gt;
package provide). That said, it was a great cross-platform notes application&amp;hellip;
so I continued to use it for that. Any personal or work &lt;em&gt;note&lt;/em&gt; that wasn&amp;rsquo;t
directly related to a single task card was stored in Joplin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;issues-with-the-system&#34;&gt;Issues with the system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/scrum-board.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Emacs org mode&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/scrum-board.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My Emacs org-mode task/notes, using the task-board
package I wrote.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this system &lt;em&gt;worked&lt;/em&gt;, it does some issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;couldn-t-share-items-across-applications&#34;&gt;Couldn&amp;rsquo;t share items across applications&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest issue I had with this framework was that it was made from several
&lt;em&gt;disconnected&lt;/em&gt; systems. This meant that my notes and information were spread
all over the place, and not linkable. I tried to keep notes and task logs
separate, but while working on projects I often wanted to create longer,
stand-alone, reference &lt;em&gt;notes&lt;/em&gt; related to a task. With this setup, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t
easily have the two items reference each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;had-to-configure-each-application-on-every-device&#34;&gt;Had to configure each application&amp;hellip; on every device&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have &lt;a href=&#34;http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/org-babel-setup/&#34;&gt;automated my emacs
setup&lt;/a&gt;, but both joplin and
emacs still required me to manually configure their sync solutions.
Additionally, while Trello&amp;rsquo;s minimal setup of &amp;lsquo;just login&amp;rsquo; seems simple enough,
even this can quickly become tedious when doing it for multiple applications at a
time&amp;hellip; on several devices&amp;hellip; some of them phones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;not-accessible-beyond-my-computers&#34;&gt;Not accessible beyond my computers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, my main issue was that apart from Trello, these systems weren&amp;rsquo;t really
accessable from devices beside my own. In fact Emacs wasn&amp;rsquo;t even available on
my mobile devices. While good from a security standpoint, I don&amp;rsquo;t like having
all my notes and information only available when I sit down at a desktop. If
I&amp;rsquo;m working on a family member&amp;rsquo;s machine, or in a fresh VM (without a shared
clipboard), I want to be able to access my notes from a private browser tab. I
also like to move cards across my task board from my phone as I complete them
throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;desires&#34;&gt;Desires&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these issues defined, what is it that I actually want to see in my note
taking and task organization system?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-gui.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-gui.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Joplin Notes&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consolidated into one system&lt;/strong&gt;: I don&amp;rsquo;t want to setup multiple apps
and logins on all my systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross platform&lt;/strong&gt;: Despite only wanting a single system, I want it supported
on all my devices, including mobile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Task board support&lt;/strong&gt;: I really enjoy moving and displaying  my task items
in a board view.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Normal notes too&lt;/strong&gt;: In addition to task cards, I also want support for
traditional, stand-alone notes. Ideally tasks &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be linked to
notes, but the notes don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to be task-bound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easy to jump in, add a log note, and get out&lt;/strong&gt;: I love this in org-mode. I need
the ability to quickly jump into a task, hit a keyboard shortcut to auto-insert
a time-stamp, and write a log note.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notion&#34;&gt;Notion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-notion/notion_window.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Notion in iOS&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-notion/notion_window.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Notion window in macOS, displaying my page for this post. The UI looks the same on the web and in my &amp;lsquo;Nativfier&amp;rsquo; app in Linux.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notion might be my solution. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://notion.so&#34;&gt;Notion website&lt;/a&gt; states
that it is an &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;All-in-one workspace.  Write, plan, collaborate, and get
organized — all in one tool&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. Having used it as my lone system over the
past several weeks, I think agree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-like-so-far&#34;&gt;What I like so far&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FLEXIBLE&lt;/strong&gt;: This cannot be emphasized enough. Notion is &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt;
flexible, providing the &lt;em&gt;tools&lt;/em&gt; to setup your own system, rather than being
a defined system itself. Want just a pile of markdown-ish notes? Fine. Want
to create endless clusters  of relational databases? Go ahead. This endless
flexibility makes Notion what I would consider to be the Emacs org-mode for
&lt;del&gt;normal&lt;/del&gt; &lt;em&gt;reasonable&lt;/em&gt; people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easy logging using &lt;code&gt;@now&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-notion/now_timestamp.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;logging using @now&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-notion/now_timestamp.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Easy logging using &lt;code&gt;@now&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Notion has the &amp;lsquo;easy logging&amp;rsquo; feature I
wanted. I just have to type &lt;code&gt;@now&lt;/code&gt;, hit enter, and it auto auto-inserts a
dynamic date and time (the &amp;lsquo;today&amp;rsquo; changes to &amp;lsquo;yesterday&amp;rsquo;, and eventually
the date as time passes).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Databases&lt;/strong&gt;: Databases are a compelling tool that are the backbone of a
powerful notion setup. They allow collections of data to be linked, sorted,
and filtered. Databases themselves have several notable features worth
mentioning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multiple view methods for the same data&lt;/strong&gt;: Database items can be displayed in
different &lt;em&gt;views&lt;/em&gt;. These include tables, boards, galleries,
calendar, and lists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Views can be filtered and sorted using property rules&lt;/strong&gt;:
Properties can be also marked as hidden, and any custom
changes to the data view can be saved. This makes it easy to flip
through different views to get a better picture of the information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linkable&lt;/strong&gt;: A database can be embedded in a page as a &amp;lsquo;linked database&amp;rsquo;.
This is a database that points to an already existing
one, and any changes to it also occur in the original DB. However,
the linked databases have their own saved and default views.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Templates&lt;/strong&gt;: Templates are another convenient feature. A specific page
layout can be defined as a template, which new pages can then be created
from. For example, I have weekly templates that
contain all the tasks and linked databases for that week automatically
configured. So when setting up a new week, I can simply create a new page
from the template and fill in some information. Done.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessible from all my devices&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-notion/ios_notion.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Notion in iOS&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-notion/ios_notion.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Notion views in iOS. Navigation, my &amp;lsquo;Areas&amp;rsquo; card view,
a daily log page&amp;rsquo; properties, and a task &amp;lsquo;board&amp;rsquo; view.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notion has desktop applications for macOS and Windows, as well as
mobile apps for iOS and Andriod. Additionally, it functions well as a webapp, which
made it easy for me to create a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jiahaog/nativefier&#34;&gt;nativefier&lt;/a&gt; build of it to run on my Linux
systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Free, and affordable for pro&lt;/strong&gt;: When I started using notion, the free tier
was limited to 1000 blocks, but since then they have made the personal tier
free &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; a use limit! There is still a Pro version with fancy features
(like revision history), but even that is offered at a reasonable price.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;downsides-concerns&#34;&gt;Downsides/Concerns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-notion/notion-export.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Notion in iOS&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/trying-notion/notion-export.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Notion makes it easy to export an entire workspace.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All my eggs in one basket&lt;/strong&gt;: My biggest concern with Notion, is that I am
throwing everything into a single service which I now rely on. That is a &lt;em&gt;huge risk&lt;/em&gt;. Fortunately,
Notion does make it extremely easy to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notion.so/Workspace-settings-security-b0a64a148cad461cb6e9df74f7372ecf#23a9194abf324cb7a222ede243fdcb5b&#34;&gt;export&lt;/a&gt; a workspace, which eases
my fears a bit. I need to test this out, and maybe make it a habit to
periodically do it as a backup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A bit of a steep learning curve&lt;/strong&gt;: All the flexibility
and power means it can take a bit of trial and error to setup a system that
works for you. While overwhelming at first, I don&amp;rsquo;t find it to be not that
big of an problem. I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; coming from using mostly emacs after all :P&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lacks a cheaper &amp;lsquo;Family&amp;rsquo; Plan&lt;/strong&gt;: I&amp;rsquo;m ecstatic that they made the personal plan
free, but I would still love to see a &amp;lsquo;Family&amp;rsquo; plan that would allow my
wife and I to have shared collaborative pages. I know this is what the
teams version provides, but we don&amp;rsquo;t need all the other advanced features,
and the price ends up being a bit steep for what we would want.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, I&amp;rsquo;ve found Notion to be amazing. I&amp;rsquo;ve had to redo my setup twice
already as I&amp;rsquo;ve started to better understand more powerful features, but every
time it has been worth it. Notion appears to be fitting my needs perfectly, and
it keeps getting better every day as I continue to tweak and perfect it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back On org-mode For Work</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-on-org-mode-for-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/back-on-org-mode-for-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month, I wrote about my &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/switched-to-joplin-notes/&#34;&gt;switch to Joplin&lt;/a&gt;
for both my personal and work notes. While I enjoyed many features in Joplin, I
also had a few concerns about using the system long-term for all my notes.
As of last week, I am still using Joplin for all of my personal notes, but have switched
back to &lt;code&gt;org-mode&lt;/code&gt; for my notes at work. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-cases&#34;&gt;Use Cases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To better understand why Joplin works well for me at home but can&amp;rsquo;t effectively
replace org-mode at work, lets first list some different features between Joplin and
emacs org-mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joplin-features&#34;&gt;Joplin Features&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;notes-style-focused&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Notes&amp;rdquo;-Style Focused&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-gui.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-gui.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Joplin uses a traditional &amp;ldquo;note&amp;rdquo; layout, with blank text
boxes organized into notebooks.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joplin organizes notes in a traditional &amp;ldquo;notes&amp;rdquo; style. Each note starts as a
big, blank text-box that the user fills in. These notes are further organized
into &amp;ldquo;notebooks&amp;rdquo;, which are simply a list of one or more notes. The notes are
formatted with markdown, but the application doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to support features
like collapsible sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;simple-markdown-format-sharable&#34;&gt;Simple Markdown Format &amp;ndash; Sharable&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The markdown editor in Joplin may not support collapsing sections, but it does
a great job at supporting other features, like simple code highlighting and web
links. Additionally, being formated in markdown, the note contents can be easily
exported, transferred, or even shared with other applications and/or people.
This is handy when grabbing snippets from the web, which may already be in a
markdown friendly format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;shared-across-computer-and-mobile-devices&#34;&gt;Shared across Computer and Mobile Devices&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-android.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin Android GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-android.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Notebook and Notes views on the Android client.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the Joplin application is available on all platforms (including
mobile), and manages the system to sync the notes across all devices. This
makes it a breeze to write a note at a computer, and then have it immediately
available on a phone afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;org-mode-use-cases&#34;&gt;Org-mode use cases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;logging-style-notes&#34;&gt;Logging-Style Notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By comparison, Emacs&amp;rsquo; org-mode can be very &lt;em&gt;task&lt;/em&gt; oriented, allowing for a more
&amp;lsquo;log-style&amp;rsquo; note-taking system. It encourages outline organization of notes,
organized under &amp;ldquo;tasks&amp;rdquo; which can be collapsed in a hierarchy. The
tasks can be marked &amp;ldquo;TODO&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;DONE&amp;rdquo; using the built in TODO system, or
tagged for organization. While org-mode can be used when writing &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; notes, it really
shines when working as a task/note system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;quick-notes-key-bindings&#34;&gt;Quick Notes, Key-bindings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/note-demo.gif&#39;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Demonstration of logging a quick note.&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/note-demo-pre.png&#34; onmouseover=&#34;this.src=&#39;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/note-demo.gif&#39;&#34; onmouseout=&#34;this.src=&#39;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/note-demo-pre.png&#39;&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Notes and code blocks can be easily added using
key-binding shortcuts.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another feature in org mode is the note drawer. By pressing a key combination
(as one tends to do in Emacs), a new buffer will open up to take a note in. The
contents of the note may be text, or even a code snippet (&lt;em&gt;in the emacs mode of
that language&lt;/em&gt;). When done, I can simply press &lt;code&gt;C-c C-c&lt;/code&gt; and the buffer will
close, inserting the note with a time-stamped entry as part of the &lt;code&gt;logbook&lt;/code&gt;
for the task I opened the note in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quick logging feature, along with the power of all the key-binding
customization, makes note logging fast, efficient, and enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;todo-scrum-board-tasks&#34;&gt;TODO/SCRUM Board tasks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/scrum-board.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin Android GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/scrum-board.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;I wrote a package that lets me view org tasks in a
scrum board.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, org-mode has a powerful
&lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/TODO-items.html&#34;&gt;todo&lt;/a&gt; system. Users can configure
how task items should be grouped beyond just a basic &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;DONE&lt;/code&gt;. Using this
flexability (and some lisp knowledge), I wrote an &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/himmAllRight/ry-org-scrum&#34;&gt;scrum board generator for
org-mode&lt;/a&gt;. This package takes all
of my &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt; items, and organizes them into scrum task board. This feature
helps organize my daily and weekly task lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;exporting-archiving-weekly-logs&#34;&gt;Exporting/Archiving Weekly Logs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big &amp;ldquo;feature&amp;rdquo; org mode has that I find lacking in Joplin, is the
ability to better organize long-term sets of notes. With a logging style of
note-taking, notes are often organized by a specific range in time (day, week,
month). These systems are naturally structured hierarchically and Joplin&amp;rsquo;s notebook/note
organization only allows for systems to be 2 levels deep. However, org files are stored
as text files on a traditional file system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, org files can be linked (and exported as html files), so any note can
still be quickly navigated to, even if the archive spans hundreds of note files over
several years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;home-vs-work-notes&#34;&gt;Home vs Work Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now with some of each note system&amp;rsquo;s features broken down, how do they
fit with my preferences across different note taking use-cases? (mostly personal vs.
work)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;home&#34;&gt;Home&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-travel-notes.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin Android GUI&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/joplin-travel-notes.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 350px; float: right; padding: 15px 0px 10px 20px&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal notes tend to be organized as more traditional notes. I make large
groups, such as &amp;lsquo;Home&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Tech&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Travel&amp;rsquo;, and stash notes into each. In a note,
I tend to organize information on a topic and store it for later. For example,
I may have a notebook for online classes, and then a note for each class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For another example, I have a notebook called &amp;lsquo;Travel&amp;rsquo; which contains a note
for each trip I plan.  In the note, I store information that I will need, such
as flight numbers, or hotel addresses. Below important information, I jot down
ideas while planning and researching before leaving. This may include places to
to eat, or activities I want to do (with links to the websites).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joplin&amp;rsquo;s mobile platform support is particularly useful here, as I am able to
write up notes on my desktop, and then read them from my phone on the go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;work&#34;&gt;Work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, my work notes are a mix of task-list and logbook for each
week. I plan each week by moving &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt; tasks from one day to
the next, and changing the status as I work on each one. As I work, I log notes
under each task about my progress, as well as any issues/solutions I experience
on the way. While the notes are mostly rambling, logging thoughts as I work
helps me to quickly identify issues, and solve problems faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/exported-notes.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;My notes exported as linked html pages&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/back-on-org-mode-for-work/exported-notes.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The index page of my exported weekly work notes.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, due to organizing notes by &lt;em&gt;week&lt;/em&gt; rather than topic, it is
best if I can archive the notes in more of a tree layout. Org notes are plain
text files, so I can save them on my hard drive any way I want. For example, I
have my work notes organized as &lt;code&gt;./work/archive/{YEAR}/{MONTH}{DAY}/week-of-{date}.org&lt;/code&gt;.
Each week, I also export the finished notes to linked html files, which is very
useful for going back and looking at my previous notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. I&amp;rsquo;ve switched back to emacs org-notes for my work tasks,
but remain on Joplin for my personal and home notes. So far&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m loving
it. I think that I switched to Joplin because org-mode wasn&amp;rsquo;t ideal for my
personal notes. However, Joplin was lacking for my work
notes. That&amp;rsquo;s okay. I learned that my home vs. work notes are two completely
different use cases, and as a result should use different tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, moving forward, I plan to keep using Joplin for my personal notes, and
emacs org-mode for my work tasks. Perfect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switched to Joplin Notes</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/switched-to-joplin-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/switched-to-joplin-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/org-babel-setup/&#34;&gt;massive fan&lt;/a&gt; of emacs&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/&#34;&gt;org-mode&lt;/a&gt;, it should be no surprise that I&amp;rsquo;ve been using
it for my personal and work planning/notes over the last few years.  However,
as my daily emacs usage has slowly dropped, and the support for &lt;code&gt;.org&lt;/code&gt; files
outside of emacs remains low (other than &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/himmAllRight/dotfiles/tree/master/emacs&#34;&gt;Github README
files&lt;/a&gt;), I started
to look for a more standard system. The last few months, I&amp;rsquo;ve been using
&lt;a href=&#34;https://joplinapp.org/&#34;&gt;Joplin&lt;/a&gt;. Here are my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-system-org-mode&#34;&gt;Previous System - Org-mode&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/org-mode-notes.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Emacs with a note opened in org-mode.&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/org-mode-notes.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Emacs with a note opened in org-mode&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, I had been taking all of my notes using org-mode in emacs. Each
week, I made a new &lt;code&gt;.org&lt;/code&gt; file for my work notes, and another for my personal
planning/notes. I would then list my &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/TODO-items.html&#34;&gt;todo
items&lt;/a&gt;, usually grouped by day,
category, or both. I would also
&lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/Tags.html&#34;&gt;tag&lt;/a&gt; each item, for better organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I worked on each task, I could quickly add time-stamped notes using the
built-in &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/Drawers.html&#34;&gt;logbook drawer&lt;/a&gt; shortcut. In
these notes, I would ramble, or paste a code snippet to save for later. As work
on each item progressed, I could set the &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt; status to &lt;code&gt;Working On&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Finished&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Removed&lt;/code&gt;, or any other state I had pre-defined.  Eventually, I
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/himmAllRight/ry-org-scrum&#34;&gt;wrote an emacs-lisp
script/package&lt;/a&gt; that took the
&lt;code&gt;todo&lt;/code&gt; items in my &lt;code&gt;org&lt;/code&gt; file, and dumped them into a SCRUM board at the top of
the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/org-notes-export-pages.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Pictured of org notes exported to HTML&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/org-notes-export-pages.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;org-notes allowed me to link and export my notes to
HTML&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, org files can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/Exporting.html&#34;&gt;exported&lt;/a&gt;
to all sorts of file types (md, html, pdf, latex). By combining the export
feature with &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/manual/Internal-links.html&#34;&gt;internal
linking&lt;/a&gt;, I was able to create
an organized system for my archived notes. I created an &lt;code&gt;index.org&lt;/code&gt; file which
linked to each week&amp;rsquo;s notes. Every week, I would archive the html export of a
note, and add it to the index list. This meant I could browse my old notes as a
website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-liked&#34;&gt;What I liked&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;org-mode&lt;/code&gt; is great.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could take all of my notes in a simple markdown language (org)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good code-block support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note linking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exported to html (or txt, md, pdf, or anything really)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My previous notes were all exported to an archive website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;issues&#34;&gt;Issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to use emacs for any edits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not supported on mobile devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As I used more &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; syntax for other applications, I found myself fumbling between &lt;code&gt;org&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;md&lt;/code&gt; syntax often.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syncing issues (mostly Nextcloud issues. Seafile helped, but it still occurred)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I loved taking notes in org-mode. However, I wanted something that
could be used on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my devices, and was more easily translatable outside of
&amp;ldquo;emacsOS&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-switch-joplin&#34;&gt;The Switch - Joplin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/joplin-window.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Window of the Joplin GUI application&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/joplin-window.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Joplin GUI window (in &amp;lsquo;split mode&amp;rsquo;)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;about-joplin&#34;&gt;About Joplin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joplin is an open source note-taking and to-do application. It synchronizes and
organizes markdown notes into notebooks, across many platforms (Android, iOS,
macOS, Linux, and Windows). It even has both a GUI &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; terminal client.  So,
I decided to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-setup&#34;&gt;My Setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When configuring joplin, a sync system has to be defined (well, &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;. Notes
can also be saved locally). There are a few supported options including using
Nextcloud. I had previously synced my org notes using Nextcloud, but eventually
moved away from it due to repeated file conflict issues. So I wanted to try
something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/fastmail_logo.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Window of the Joplin GUI application&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/fastmail_logo.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 70%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Joplin GUI window (in &amp;lsquo;split mode&amp;rsquo;)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While researching Joplin, I learned that I could sync notes to the WebDav
server on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fastmail.com&#34;&gt;fastmail&lt;/a&gt; account I have for email. I
wasn&amp;rsquo;t using any of the account&amp;rsquo;s file storage, so I figured I this would be a
good way to get use out of a service I&amp;rsquo;m already paying for. It works great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-i-like&#34;&gt;What I like&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;syncs-on-all-my-devices&#34;&gt;Syncs on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my devices&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I have enjoyed most about this setup is that my notes sync to all of my
devices. Most importantly, I can &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; the notes on every device. With
previous systems, the files would sync everywhere, but I still couldn&amp;rsquo;t always
easily read them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cli-and-gui-versions&#34;&gt;CLI and GUI versions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I like that Joplin has both a GUI and CLI client. I
mostly use the GUI, but enjoy having the CLI as an option because it means I
can always ssh into a machine and take notes. Additionally, the
cli client allows me to take/edit notes using my own terminal editors such as
emacs &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; vim. This is quite convenient, and I should probably start using
Joplin this way more often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;markdown-note-exports&#34;&gt;Markdown Note Exports&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/export-options.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin cli application&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/export-options.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Export options in Joplin GUI&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like that notes are formatted in markdown. This provides some
consistency when writing, but ensures that my notes are in a format that is
standardized. Additionally, joplin allows easy exporting of
the notes to other formats such as &lt;code&gt;json&lt;/code&gt; or as &lt;code&gt;pdf&lt;/code&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;easy-enough-to-use&#34;&gt;Easy enough to use&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, Joplin has been easy to use. After setup, I just have to open the app,
and start typing away (maybe with a sync or two). While my last setup required
the user to be somewhat of an emacs/org guru&amp;hellip; this doesn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;issues-i-m-still-figuring-out-anticipate&#34;&gt;Issues I&amp;rsquo;m still figuring out/Anticipate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/joplin-cli.png&#34;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&#34;Joplin cli application&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/switched-to-joplin-notes/joplin-cli.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Joplin CLI window &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;setup-is-a-pain&#34;&gt;Setup is a pain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While configuring sync can be a pain, it&amp;rsquo;s not my biggest gripe with the Joplin
setup process. It&amp;rsquo;s adding a new system. By default, if I configure a new
device with my sync solution (my laptop or phone for example) and then sync, it
will load up all of the crap default example tags and notes, which then pull
down to all of my systems. This is extremely frustrating because I have to keep
deleting them.  This is multiplied by the fact that it happens with &lt;em&gt;each
client&lt;/em&gt; I setup. So if I setup the gui and cli on my laptop, it will happen
&lt;em&gt;twice&lt;/em&gt; (2x each default tags/notes will show up on all my systems).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Semi-Solution&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;slight&lt;/em&gt; work-around I have been able to use when setting up a new computer
is to simply copy the config files from an existing system to the new one.
These folders can be found at &lt;code&gt;~/.config/joplin/&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;~/.config/Joplin/&lt;/code&gt;, and/or
&lt;code&gt;~/.config/joplin-desktop/&lt;/code&gt;. This also means that the new system &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have less
it needs to sync down from the server on the first sync.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;long-term-archiving&#34;&gt;Long term archiving&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;big&lt;/strong&gt; problem I have&amp;hellip; and think I will continue to have with Joplin, is
the long-term organization of notes. Part of this is my inability to figure out an
efficient and organized way to handle my &amp;ldquo;log&amp;rdquo; notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem partially stems from Joplin&amp;rsquo;s shallow organizational
structure. There are notebooks, and notes. That&amp;rsquo;s it. Unlike having
a file structure where I can do something like
&lt;code&gt;archive/2019/June/Weekly_Plans/&lt;/code&gt;, I can&amp;rsquo;t really go that deep with Joplin, so
I end up just having a single notebook with &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my weekly plan notes listed
in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One remaining solution might be to get more aggressive with the tagging
feature, and see if I can create a more organized system using that. I might be
able to tag each note with a month/year, and then truncate my log notes each
month. The only problem with this is that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like I can select
&lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt; tags at a time, which would mean &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of my notes for a month
will be shown under the tag. That would be a deal breaker for me :( .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, I think that Joplin &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a great open source notes solution.  If
someone needs a system to keep a bunch of normal notes synced across all their
devices, this is it. I however, might need to try out something else long-term.
On the bright side, there are a bunch of features in Joplin that love and will
definitely look for&amp;hellip; in my next solution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
