<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>snapd on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/snapd/</link>
    <description>Recent content in snapd on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/snapd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying out snapd on Arch Linux</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/snapd-on-arch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/snapd-on-arch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The past few weeks I have been listening to all of the buzz about
Ubuntu &amp;ldquo;snaps&amp;rdquo;, but I just recently decided to try this new technology
out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;snapd-install-and-setup&#34;&gt;Snapd Install and Setup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to install snapd on my small netbook (Abra), which is running Arch
Linux. So, installing snapd was as easy as running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;pacaur -S snapd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I use pacaur so that I can install packages from Arch Linux&amp;rsquo;s
main repos, as well as the AUR. However, because snapd has actually
been moved to the community repos, you can install it with vanilla
pacman, without aur support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo pacman -S snapd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After snapd is installed, it needs to be started. To start the snapd
service, just use systemd:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo systemctl start snapd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, If you want to start the snapd service automatically
after a reboot run the command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo systemctl enable snapd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;using-snap&#34;&gt;Using snap&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After snapd was installed and running, I started
playing with the snap application. The first thing I should note is
that to the extent of my knowledge, snap has to be run as root (at
least for now). So my commands all start with &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I wanted to find a snap package. This can be done using the
&lt;code&gt;snap find&lt;/code&gt; command as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo snap find package-name&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(where &lt;strong&gt;package-name&lt;/strong&gt; is the name of the package to search)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like in any standard package manager search, the potential
matches were returned, along with a version number, the developer
name, and a summary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snap has several other commands. To see a full list of available snap
commands and a description for each one, just type:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo snap help&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;testing-a-snap&#34;&gt;Testing a snap&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After learning about the basic snap commands, I wanted to install a
snap to see how well it works. I decided to see if there was a
Telegram snap (I heard there was, so it was a good bet). I ran
&lt;code&gt;sudo snap find telegram&lt;/code&gt;, and a list of my options appeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I choose the last one, and installed it using the command
&lt;code&gt;sudo snap install telegram-serguisens&lt;/code&gt;. A progress bar tracked the download of
the snap, and then the installation. That was it. To my delight,
within a few seconds the Ubuntu &lt;code&gt;snap&lt;/code&gt; application had downloaded the
telegram snap, and installed it on my &lt;em&gt;arch linux&lt;/em&gt; box, without any issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-only-issue&#34;&gt;My Only Issue&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; without any issues. The one problem I did have was
after installing the telegram snap, the executable wasn&amp;rsquo;t in my path so
I couldn&amp;rsquo;t start it from my launcher or even a terminal. I think this
was actually because snapd wasn&amp;rsquo;t setup fully. I rebooted my computer
and telegram now launches just fine. The snap is even identified with
its full name (&lt;em&gt;telegram-serguisens&lt;/em&gt;), so I can be sure it is the
actual snap, and not another Telegram install.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the fact that snaps are easy to package and install for
developers and users alike, I think my favorite feature was something
that I didn&amp;rsquo;t even think about prior to trying it out, and I might not
of realized had I installed snapd on another computer&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This little computer is low power, and tends to heat up and go crazy
when I install certain packages (particularly ones from the
AUR). Sometimes it is so bad that I have to kill the installation and
forego that application for awhile. Telegram is one of them. I think
this is because the aur build pulls down the telegram .deb package and
then has to extract and compile it in order to install it on
Arch. This little computer doesn&amp;rsquo;t like that. The snap however, seems
to of just download and installed itself. It hardly pegged my CPU at
all. If this is true, snaps might have an additional use-case on weaker
hardware, like my netbook. (yes, I know snaps might have a bigger disk
footprint, but honestly that trade-off is fine with me)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the universal application frameworks are a great idea that is
very much needed on Linux. Snapd is very promising and I look forward
to seeing what it and other solutions have in store for the future of
Linux.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
