<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>iPad on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/ipad/</link>
    <description>Recent content in iPad on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/ipad/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Got an iPad</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/getting-an-ipad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/getting-an-ipad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months, I&amp;rsquo;ve been considering getting a tablet device for the
first time since I was in college. After researching all sorts of options, I
had myself convinced that I would likely be picking up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apple.com/ipad-9.7/&#34;&gt;2018 9.7&amp;rdquo;
iPad&lt;/a&gt; at some point. Then I ordered an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apple.com/shop/buy-ipad/ipad-pro-10-5&#34;&gt;iPad
Pro 10.5&amp;rdquo; (2017 model)&lt;/a&gt;.
Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-a-tablet&#34;&gt;Why a Tablet?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I use technology, I try to plan out and use devices which best fit the
tasks I want to accomplish. After evaluating my work habits, I started to
think that a tablet might function well in many of my use cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/keyone.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Blackberry KEYone&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/keyone.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 250px; float: left;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason? I don&amp;rsquo;t like using smart phones. I think modern phones
are a wonderful piece of technology, but they are often misused. While some
smart phone apps can greatly enhance one&amp;rsquo;s life, many are convenient
distractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My phone is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; with me, so I keep the set of apps installed on it to a
minimum. I try to use apps that are most needed &amp;ldquo;on the go&amp;rdquo; (maps/lyft,
music/podcasts, and various communication apps). I find that this helps prevent
me from easily distracting myself throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I realized that the experience of some tasks on the phone isn&amp;rsquo;t
great, and that they would likely be best completed on a tablet. Additionally,
setting up a tablet for these apps meant I could still enjoy them in a more
portable way, but maintain a clean, distraction-free phone. Some of the
activities I intended to offload from my phone are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;portable-media-consumption&#34;&gt;Portable Media Consumption&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/youtube-logo.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Youtube Logo&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/youtube-logo.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 200px; float: right; margin: 15px 15px 15px 15px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually consume the majority of my media either on our TV, or at my computer.
That being said, I did start to notice myself watching Youtube, Hulu, and
Netflix, more often from my phone. This usually occurred when the TV was in use,
or I simply wanted to watch from a different location (ex: my bed). Having a
small screen and tinny speakers, watching video on a phone is terrible.
This is especially true on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gsmarena.com/blackberry_keyone-8508.php&#34;&gt;Blackberry
KEYone&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;even
smaller&lt;/em&gt; screen (Which I choose because it is a great &lt;em&gt;communication device&lt;/em&gt;, with a long
battery life. Regardless, even on a large, bezel-less phone screen, watching video
on a smart phone is still sub-optimal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I used my previous tablet (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asus_Eee_Pad_Transformer&#34;&gt;an Asus Transformer
T101&lt;/a&gt;, with no dock) to
watch videos in my dorm or around campus. I loved it&amp;rsquo;s convenient, but yet
still enticing viewing experience. I assumed that with a modern tablet,
it would only be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;reading&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being such a visual learner, I tend to gravitate towards visual media. Reading
however, is much less passive than video. When watching a movie, it will
continue to progress whether the viewer is paying attention or not. Reading is
much more &lt;em&gt;self-driven&lt;/em&gt;, which I find helps to build my concentration. As a
result, reading is something I am always trying to do more of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/leanyouahaskell.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Learn You A Haskell for Great Good Book&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/leanyouahaskell.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 260px; float: left; margin: 25px 25px 25px 25px; &#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have owned a kindle paperwhite for years, and it is perfect for reading
books.  However, there are some types of reading material that my kindle falls
simply does not handle well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.humblebundle.com/books/&#34;&gt;Humble Book
Bundles&lt;/a&gt;, I have acquired a collection of
programming, DevOps, system administration, and general technology ebooks. You
know&amp;hellip; the type of book that is &lt;em&gt;technically&lt;/em&gt; classified as a &amp;ldquo;textbook&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;
but does not sound nearly as cool when I call it that&amp;hellip;  Anyway the point
is&amp;hellip; they are &lt;em&gt;horrendous&lt;/em&gt; to read on the kindle. I would love the ability
to flip through a &lt;em&gt;textbook&lt;/em&gt; on a large, color screen, and a tablet enables that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/pocket-logo.svg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pocket Logo&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/pocket-logo.svg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 175px; float: right; margin: 15px 15px 15px 15px; &#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the internet is full of all sorts of &amp;ldquo;articles&amp;rdquo;. News stories, blog posts,
product announcements, opinion pieces, tutorials, reviews&amp;hellip; all litter the
internet. Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been starting to corral this craziness by using tools
such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://getpocket.com/&#34;&gt;pocket&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;em&gt;save&lt;/em&gt; articles I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to read.
Then, I can come back and batch-read them later. This helps me break the
endless rabbit-hole of digging through, and semi-reading &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;related&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; articles
(half of which aren&amp;rsquo;t even good).  This practice has worked &lt;em&gt;alright&lt;/em&gt; on my
computer, but I do think it would be &lt;em&gt;ideal&lt;/em&gt; to sit down in an
armchair with a tablet in my lap, for my batch reads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;offload-some-of-my-smart-phone-use&#34;&gt;Offload &lt;em&gt;Some&lt;/em&gt; of My Smart Phone Use&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously stated, my biggest motivation for buying a tablet is to offload
my phone usage to it. This is particularly true for apps which I am &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;
to use&amp;hellip; but don&amp;rsquo;t need to have access to at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best example of this? Banking and other financial apps. I appreciate the
ease of modern banking, and love that I can simply take a picture to deposit a
check. However, I don&amp;rsquo;t need this on my phone. Not only am I unlikely to be
scanning checks and moving money around my bank accounts in public&amp;hellip; it is not
really safe to be doing so. I&amp;rsquo;d rather just wait until I get home on my own
network, and do my banking from a tablet (which stays at home much more
frequently than my phone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-options&#34;&gt;Other Options&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;android-tablets&#34;&gt;Android Tablets&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started looking at tablets, I quickly noticed that the market had
changed &lt;em&gt;dramatically&lt;/em&gt; from a just few years ago. While there are still android
tablets &lt;em&gt;available&lt;/em&gt;, the future of Google &lt;em&gt;supporting&lt;/em&gt; android on tablets is a
bit unclear. They appear to be trying to shift everything to ChromeOS, as
demonstrated with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://store.google.com/us/product/pixel_slate?hl=en-US&#34;&gt;Pixel
Slate&lt;/a&gt;.
Additionally, Android still tends to treat tablets as just a large screened phone, and
applications are often not optimized for it. Understandably, I was a little leery about
Android tablets. As for ChromOS tablets, the Slate is currently the only real
contender, but with it&amp;rsquo;s high price point, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2jsqZMCPJts&#34;&gt;lack-luster
reviews&lt;/a&gt;, it was out of the
running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;amazon-fire-tablets&#34;&gt;Amazon Fire Tablets&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/firetablet.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Amazon Fire Tablet&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/firetablet.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 300px; float: right; margin: 15px 15px 15px 15px; &#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the pixel slate, at the low end of the tablet market was the
Amazon fire tablet family.  These devices are quite affordable and would work
well for anyone that just wants to read/watch video on a tablet (especially
Amazon content). However, I just felt that the Fire tablet might be a bit too
limiting for me, as I tend to push technology as far as I can.  Beyond that,
the cheaper iterations of each tablet are the &amp;ldquo;special offers&amp;rdquo; ones, which show
amazon ads on the tablet. By the time I had selected a 10&amp;rdquo; tablet &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt;
special offers, the price point started approaching (well&amp;hellip; almost) another
contender&amp;hellip; the 2018 iPad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-an-ipad&#34;&gt;Why an iPad?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/ipod-video.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pocket Logo&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/ipod-video.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 200px; float: left; margin: 20px 20px 10px 10px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;my-apple-device-history&#34;&gt;My Apple Device History&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally wanted to do a full &lt;em&gt;multi-paragraph section&lt;/em&gt; detailing my limited
use of apple products throughout my life, and how I only really buy them when
they &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; stand out above the competition. But that would be
pretentious, extremely boring, and quite honestly, annoying. So in short: the
only Apple devices that I have owned are 1) an iPod Video, and 2) iPod Touch.
So why am I willing to get an iPad as my tablet device?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ipad&#34;&gt;iPad&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While researching, I found that the Apple &lt;em&gt;iPad&lt;/em&gt; was consistently
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GD1zTrs2EMw&#34;&gt;recommended&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e7eNq6hTm5E&#34;&gt;as
a&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sGkr6Cjr0TI&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;great-value&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y3PFt1Y8ZgA&#34;&gt;tablet-device&lt;/a&gt; on the market
today. Most notably, the 2018 entry-level iPad, which
sold for $330 USD, but could often be found on sale for under $300.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aimed at the education market, the 2018 iPad saw a cpu upgrade, and support for
the Apple pencil. The only con I ran into people reporting was that because it
didn&amp;rsquo;t have a laminated screen, there was a bit of a &amp;ldquo;gap&amp;rdquo; between it and the
glass. Despite the minor screen issue, this was still the best device I could find
around that price range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;why-the-10-5-pro&#34;&gt;Why the 10.5&amp;rdquo; Pro?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/ipadpro.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#39;iPad 10.5&#34; Pro&#39; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/ipadpro.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 350px; float: right; margin: 20px 20px 10px 10px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So&amp;hellip; why did I end up with the 10.5&amp;rdquo; iPad Pro? The switch happened last minute
the morning I ended up ordering it. My upgrade happened because of
two factors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sale&lt;/strong&gt;: The iPad Pro 10.5&amp;rdquo; had gone on a sale at BestBuy, and the
configuration I liked dropped to $499 (from $650). While this was a bit
more expensive, I thought it was still a good deal, and the 2018 iPad
wasn&amp;rsquo;t on sale anywhere so it was the full $330.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Features&lt;/strong&gt;: Essentially, the Pro had a slightly larger and &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better display, better speakers, and double the storage space (64GB compared to 32GB). These are features that I don&amp;rsquo;t think most people need to care about, I knew I would really appreciate those features, especially now that I could get them for only a ~$170 increase over the iPad, compared to the normal $310 difference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that&amp;rsquo;s the history and reasoning as to &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I decided to
get a tablet device, and why that device ultimately ended up being an iPad
10.5&amp;rdquo; Pro. It arrived a couple weeks ago, and I have been enjoying it so far. I
think I&amp;rsquo;ll give myself a bit more time with it, before I even &lt;em&gt;attempt&lt;/em&gt; to write any
sort of review.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
