<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>iPad on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</title>
    <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/ipad/</link>
    <description>Recent content in iPad on λ ryan. himmelwright. net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://ryan.himmelwright.net/tags/ipad/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title> Upgrading My iPad Pro</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/getting-an-ipad/&#34;&gt;I purchased my first iPad&lt;/a&gt;, a 10.5&amp;rdquo;
iPad Pro. I use it just about every day. With the release of the newest 2021
iPad Pro, I decided it was finally time to trade mine in for an upgrade. Here&amp;rsquo;s
why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/10.5_pro_box.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The box of my 10.5 iPad Pro&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/10.5_pro_box.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The box of my 10.5&amp;rdquo; iPad Pro&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got my 10.5&amp;rdquo; iPad Pro, the 2018 11&amp;rdquo; iPad Pro had already been released.
At the time, I didn&amp;rsquo;t think the extra features justified the increased
price of the new iPad. The discount price on the &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt; pro was more appealing to
me. I was already upselling myself, after originally looking into the base
(non-pro) iPad, so the discounted 10.5&amp;rdquo; seemed like a good compromise between
features and price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 10.5&amp;rdquo; pro was a good starting point for my first iPad. It was a great
device, but not too over the top in case I ended up not using it much. If I
&lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; use it, I could always upgrade/swap it out in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-upgrade&#34;&gt;Why upgrade?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/apple_pencil_tall.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Apple Pencil&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/apple_pencil_tall.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 250px; float: right;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having my ipad for several months, I started to understand how the
improved features of the 2018 pro could be nice to have. In particular, the
USB-C port, smaller bezels, and FaceID were all very appealing to me.  Still, my
10.5&amp;rdquo; suited my needs just fine. I did decide though that I &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; likely
upgrade my iPad sometime in the future. I enjoyed having it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to the one thing I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; want to add to my iPad: the Apple
Pencil.  Being able to hand draw is a special feature unique to tablet computers
that I cannot easily reproduce on my other devices. It&amp;rsquo;s a foundational reason
to even &lt;em&gt;consider&lt;/em&gt; owning a tablet. Additionally, in the years since I purchased
my iPad, new iPadOS releases have started to polish the use of the &amp;lsquo;magic&amp;rsquo;
pencil with the iPad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, my 10.5&amp;rdquo; ipad only supported the 1st generation Apple Pencil.
Knowing that I would &lt;em&gt;eventually&lt;/em&gt; upgrade my iPad, I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to buy an old
pencil, only to have to &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; replace it when I upgraded. So, I decided to wait
to get the Pencil until it was time to upgrade my device. Now feels like a good
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-generation&#34;&gt;Why this generation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/front_camera.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;new ipad pro cameras&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/front_camera.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The 2021 iPad Pro includes a ultra wide front camera, to use with the new center stage feature&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few factors that pushed me to upgrade to &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; generation of the
iPad Pro. First, I can still get a decent trade-in value for it.  Considering
it&amp;rsquo;s been about 4 years since the 10.5&amp;rdquo; model was released, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how
long that value last with my iPad. Second, if I want to trade it in with Apple
(and I do, it&amp;rsquo;s probably the easiest method), I am limited to spending the
credit value in their store. While I could try to get a refurbished device,
there hasn&amp;rsquo;t been many used iPad Pros in stock since the pandemic started. So
the latest model is my best bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond ease of trade-in, there are a few new features in this latest generation
that I am interested in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The M1 chip is complete overkill, but I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t mind having one in my iPad
considering how much I love it  &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/m1-air-initial-thoughts/&#34;&gt;my MacBook
Air&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, it provides more
computational overhead (and increased RAM) incase Apple ever decides to finally
push the capabilities of iPadOS further (which they need to do).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;While I thought it was a bit of a gimmick at first, the wide-angle
front-facing camera paired with the new &amp;ldquo;Center Stage&amp;rdquo; feature on the 2021 iPad
Pro could actually be useful.  My wife and I use FaceTime to video chat with my
family (we live in another state from everyone), and my ipad is usually what we
use to do it. Being able to more easily fit the two of us in frame, and have it
self-adjust as my wife comes and goes would be delightful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lastly, while USB-C is great, Thunderbolt is better. I already have all of my
periphery gear hooked up to a thunderbolt dock to connect my work and personal
laptops to. The increased bandwidth also helps to &amp;ldquo;future proof&amp;rdquo; (again,
assuming Apple can improve the OS).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-the-11-over-the-12-9&#34;&gt;Why the 11&amp;rdquo; over the 12.9&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/size_and_weight.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;iPad Pro Size Comparison&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/size_and_weight.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The iPad Pro Size Comparison&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I would think about upgrading my iPad Pro, I always figured I would
switch to a 12.9&amp;rdquo; version. So why then have I instead opted for the 11&amp;rdquo; when the
12.9&amp;rdquo; is clearly the more exciting option this year, having the new &amp;ldquo;Liquid
Retina XDR&amp;rdquo; display? Well, as much as I&amp;rsquo;d enjoy seeing that new display, that
price bump makes it a bit more unreasonable for a feature I &lt;em&gt;truly do not need&lt;/em&gt;.
I don&amp;rsquo;t do any visual work, and the display on the 11&amp;rdquo; Pro is more than enough
for anything I need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real reason for the 11&amp;rdquo;, is that I now have a great portable laptop.  I was
previously looking at the bigger ipad to be my travel/portable device, but now
that I have an m1 air, a 12.9&amp;rdquo; ipad with a keyboard would actually weigh &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt;.
I want my ipad to be more portable than my mac. As a bonus, if
the combined size and weight remains low, it&amp;rsquo;s easy enough to travel with &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt;
devices. For reference, a 11&amp;rdquo; iPad Pro (without a case) and my macbook Air have
a &lt;em&gt;combined weight&lt;/em&gt; of only 3.6 lbs, whereas my previous &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/new-2019-16inch-mbp/&#34;&gt;16&amp;rdquo; Macbook
Pro&lt;/a&gt; alone weighed 4.3lbs! I would like to keep this portability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-not-the-new-ipad-air&#34;&gt;Why not the new iPad Air?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/buy_ipad_air_colors.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;iPad Air Colors&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/buy_ipad_air_colors.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The iPad Air Color Options&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, if I am contemplating getting the 11&amp;rdquo; iPad Pro, why not consider the
2020 iPad Air? I struggled with this decision for awhile, particularly before
the latest generation pro was announced. In general, I think the air would be
&lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt; and meet all of my needs. The reality is that &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; of these devices
are currently overkill for most iPad tasks. &lt;em&gt;With that said&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip; I think the
additional features of the 2021 pro are actually worth the $200 difference (in
my case). Here are a few of those feature differences, and my justification for
the pro:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Display&lt;/strong&gt;: I like the 120hz pro-motion display. I read all the time on
my ipad, and I love how smooth it is. In addition, if my plan is to get an Apple
pencil right away, the high refresh rate can help &lt;em&gt;the pencil&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; responsiveness also feel better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(furthermore, while not a &lt;em&gt;big&lt;/em&gt; deal, the screen is a little brighter
on the pro, which is appreciated when I want to read outside)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cameras&lt;/strong&gt;: As I said above, the ultra wide front camera is great for
FaceTime, as it is my FaceTime device.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better speakers&lt;/strong&gt;: I love having nice speakers on my systems, especially
my travel devices. I&amp;rsquo;ve already downgraded my laptop speakers going &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/trading-mbp16-for-m1air/&#34;&gt;from the
16&amp;rdquo; to the m1 air&lt;/a&gt;, and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do it
again. (The pro has 4 speakers, whereas the air only has 2).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FaceID&lt;/strong&gt;: TouchID is great, but my finger tips tend to peel due to
allergies, and FaceID simply works more consistently for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thunderbolt&lt;/strong&gt;: Not a deal breaker, but if I want to play around with testing an
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.macstories.net/stories/modular-computer/&#34;&gt;ipad as a modular
computer&lt;/a&gt; at all, I
already have TB3 docks setup to use.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Storage&lt;/strong&gt;: The base version pro has twice as much storage as the air. I
didn&amp;rsquo;t think this was an issue, but then I looked at the usage on my ipad and
saw I had consumed 60/64GB. I expect my usages will only continue to grow if I
begin to sketch diagrams and notes more often. The air also starts at 64GB,
where the pro begins with 128GB of storage. To upgrade the air, you need to jump
to all the way up to the 256gb hard drive.  After that upgrade, the air is less
than $50 away from the price of the pro.  Considering everything else I listed
above, I think it is definitely worth that additional cost.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LiDar&lt;/strong&gt; (seriously 😆): This is more of a novelty than a feature for most
people. Still, as someone that likes to play with AR, uses their iPad to scan
floor plans of their house, or to take rough measurements&amp;hellip; the LiDar would
help the iPad improve all those tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/order_status.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;My ipad pro order status: processing&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/upgrading-ipad-pro-2021/order_status.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;My iPad Pro order status: Processing&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you go. Those were &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; of my reasons for why I concluded to finally
trade in my 10.5&amp;rdquo; iPad Pro, for a new 11&amp;rdquo; model. I have ordered the 2021
11&amp;rdquo; iPad Pro (in silver), along with an Apple Pencil 2, and selected to trade in
my old one with the purchase. Now, all I can do is wait for it to ship. It&amp;rsquo;s
been stuck
&lt;em&gt;processing&lt;/em&gt; for over a week, but
could &lt;em&gt;arrive&lt;/em&gt; as early as two days ago 😐. Hopefully it ships soon&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Got an iPad</title>
      <link>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/getting-an-ipad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ryan.himmelwright.net/post/getting-an-ipad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months, I&amp;rsquo;ve been considering getting a tablet device for the
first time since I was in college. After researching all sorts of options, I
had myself convinced that I would likely be picking up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apple.com/ipad-9.7/&#34;&gt;2018 9.7&amp;rdquo;
iPad&lt;/a&gt; at some point. Then I ordered an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apple.com/shop/buy-ipad/ipad-pro-10-5&#34;&gt;iPad
Pro 10.5&amp;rdquo; (2017 model)&lt;/a&gt;.
Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-a-tablet&#34;&gt;Why a Tablet?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I use technology, I try to plan out and use devices which best fit the
tasks I want to accomplish. After evaluating my work habits, I started to
think that a tablet might function well in many of my use cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/keyone.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Blackberry KEYone&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/keyone.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 250px; float: left;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason? I don&amp;rsquo;t like using smart phones. I think modern phones
are a wonderful piece of technology, but they are often misused. While some
smart phone apps can greatly enhance one&amp;rsquo;s life, many are convenient
distractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My phone is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; with me, so I keep the set of apps installed on it to a
minimum. I try to use apps that are most needed &amp;ldquo;on the go&amp;rdquo; (maps/lyft,
music/podcasts, and various communication apps). I find that this helps prevent
me from easily distracting myself throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I realized that the experience of some tasks on the phone isn&amp;rsquo;t
great, and that they would likely be best completed on a tablet. Additionally,
setting up a tablet for these apps meant I could still enjoy them in a more
portable way, but maintain a clean, distraction-free phone. Some of the
activities I intended to offload from my phone are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;portable-media-consumption&#34;&gt;Portable Media Consumption&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/youtube-logo.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Youtube Logo&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/youtube-logo.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 200px; float: right; margin: 15px 15px 15px 15px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually consume the majority of my media either on our TV, or at my computer.
That being said, I did start to notice myself watching Youtube, Hulu, and
Netflix, more often from my phone. This usually occurred when the TV was in use,
or I simply wanted to watch from a different location (ex: my bed). Having a
small screen and tinny speakers, watching video on a phone is terrible.
This is especially true on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gsmarena.com/blackberry_keyone-8508.php&#34;&gt;Blackberry
KEYone&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;even
smaller&lt;/em&gt; screen (Which I choose because it is a great &lt;em&gt;communication device&lt;/em&gt;, with a long
battery life. Regardless, even on a large, bezel-less phone screen, watching video
on a smart phone is still sub-optimal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I used my previous tablet (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asus_Eee_Pad_Transformer&#34;&gt;an Asus Transformer
T101&lt;/a&gt;, with no dock) to
watch videos in my dorm or around campus. I loved it&amp;rsquo;s convenient, but yet
still enticing viewing experience. I assumed that with a modern tablet,
it would only be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;reading&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being such a visual learner, I tend to gravitate towards visual media. Reading
however, is much less passive than video. When watching a movie, it will
continue to progress whether the viewer is paying attention or not. Reading is
much more &lt;em&gt;self-driven&lt;/em&gt;, which I find helps to build my concentration. As a
result, reading is something I am always trying to do more of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/leanyouahaskell.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Learn You A Haskell for Great Good Book&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/leanyouahaskell.jpg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 260px; float: left; margin: 25px 25px 25px 25px; &#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have owned a kindle paperwhite for years, and it is perfect for reading
books.  However, there are some types of reading material that my kindle falls
simply does not handle well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.humblebundle.com/books/&#34;&gt;Humble Book
Bundles&lt;/a&gt;, I have acquired a collection of
programming, DevOps, system administration, and general technology ebooks. You
know&amp;hellip; the type of book that is &lt;em&gt;technically&lt;/em&gt; classified as a &amp;ldquo;textbook&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;
but does not sound nearly as cool when I call it that&amp;hellip;  Anyway the point
is&amp;hellip; they are &lt;em&gt;horrendous&lt;/em&gt; to read on the kindle. I would love the ability
to flip through a &lt;em&gt;textbook&lt;/em&gt; on a large, color screen, and a tablet enables that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/pocket-logo.svg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pocket Logo&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/pocket-logo.svg&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 175px; float: right; margin: 15px 15px 15px 15px; &#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, the internet is full of all sorts of &amp;ldquo;articles&amp;rdquo;. News stories, blog posts,
product announcements, opinion pieces, tutorials, reviews&amp;hellip; all litter the
internet. Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been starting to corral this craziness by using tools
such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://getpocket.com/&#34;&gt;pocket&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;em&gt;save&lt;/em&gt; articles I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to read.
Then, I can come back and batch-read them later. This helps me break the
endless rabbit-hole of digging through, and semi-reading &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;related&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; articles
(half of which aren&amp;rsquo;t even good).  This practice has worked &lt;em&gt;alright&lt;/em&gt; on my
computer, but I do think it would be &lt;em&gt;ideal&lt;/em&gt; to sit down in an
armchair with a tablet in my lap, for my batch reads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;offload-some-of-my-smart-phone-use&#34;&gt;Offload &lt;em&gt;Some&lt;/em&gt; of My Smart Phone Use&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As previously stated, my biggest motivation for buying a tablet is to offload
my phone usage to it. This is particularly true for apps which I am &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;
to use&amp;hellip; but don&amp;rsquo;t need to have access to at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best example of this? Banking and other financial apps. I appreciate the
ease of modern banking, and love that I can simply take a picture to deposit a
check. However, I don&amp;rsquo;t need this on my phone. Not only am I unlikely to be
scanning checks and moving money around my bank accounts in public&amp;hellip; it is not
really safe to be doing so. I&amp;rsquo;d rather just wait until I get home on my own
network, and do my banking from a tablet (which stays at home much more
frequently than my phone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-options&#34;&gt;Other Options&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;android-tablets&#34;&gt;Android Tablets&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started looking at tablets, I quickly noticed that the market had
changed &lt;em&gt;dramatically&lt;/em&gt; from a just few years ago. While there are still android
tablets &lt;em&gt;available&lt;/em&gt;, the future of Google &lt;em&gt;supporting&lt;/em&gt; android on tablets is a
bit unclear. They appear to be trying to shift everything to ChromeOS, as
demonstrated with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://store.google.com/us/product/pixel_slate?hl=en-US&#34;&gt;Pixel
Slate&lt;/a&gt;.
Additionally, Android still tends to treat tablets as just a large screened phone, and
applications are often not optimized for it. Understandably, I was a little leery about
Android tablets. As for ChromOS tablets, the Slate is currently the only real
contender, but with it&amp;rsquo;s high price point, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2jsqZMCPJts&#34;&gt;lack-luster
reviews&lt;/a&gt;, it was out of the
running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;amazon-fire-tablets&#34;&gt;Amazon Fire Tablets&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/firetablet.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Amazon Fire Tablet&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/firetablet.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 300px; float: right; margin: 15px 15px 15px 15px; &#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the pixel slate, at the low end of the tablet market was the
Amazon fire tablet family.  These devices are quite affordable and would work
well for anyone that just wants to read/watch video on a tablet (especially
Amazon content). However, I just felt that the Fire tablet might be a bit too
limiting for me, as I tend to push technology as far as I can.  Beyond that,
the cheaper iterations of each tablet are the &amp;ldquo;special offers&amp;rdquo; ones, which show
amazon ads on the tablet. By the time I had selected a 10&amp;rdquo; tablet &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt;
special offers, the price point started approaching (well&amp;hellip; almost) another
contender&amp;hellip; the 2018 iPad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-an-ipad&#34;&gt;Why an iPad?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/ipod-video.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pocket Logo&#34; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/ipod-video.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 200px; float: left; margin: 20px 20px 10px 10px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;my-apple-device-history&#34;&gt;My Apple Device History&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally wanted to do a full &lt;em&gt;multi-paragraph section&lt;/em&gt; detailing my limited
use of apple products throughout my life, and how I only really buy them when
they &lt;em&gt;obviously&lt;/em&gt; stand out above the competition. But that would be
pretentious, extremely boring, and quite honestly, annoying. So in short: the
only Apple devices that I have owned are 1) an iPod Video, and 2) iPod Touch.
So why am I willing to get an iPad as my tablet device?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ipad&#34;&gt;iPad&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While researching, I found that the Apple &lt;em&gt;iPad&lt;/em&gt; was consistently
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GD1zTrs2EMw&#34;&gt;recommended&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e7eNq6hTm5E&#34;&gt;as
a&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sGkr6Cjr0TI&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;great-value&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y3PFt1Y8ZgA&#34;&gt;tablet-device&lt;/a&gt; on the market
today. Most notably, the 2018 entry-level iPad, which
sold for $330 USD, but could often be found on sale for under $300.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aimed at the education market, the 2018 iPad saw a cpu upgrade, and support for
the Apple pencil. The only con I ran into people reporting was that because it
didn&amp;rsquo;t have a laminated screen, there was a bit of a &amp;ldquo;gap&amp;rdquo; between it and the
glass. Despite the minor screen issue, this was still the best device I could find
around that price range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;why-the-10-5-pro&#34;&gt;Why the 10.5&amp;rdquo; Pro?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/ipadpro.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#39;iPad 10.5&#34; Pro&#39; src=&#34;../../img/posts/getting-an-ipad/ipadpro.png&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; width: 350px; float: right; margin: 20px 20px 10px 10px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So&amp;hellip; why did I end up with the 10.5&amp;rdquo; iPad Pro? The switch happened last minute
the morning I ended up ordering it. My upgrade happened because of
two factors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sale&lt;/strong&gt;: The iPad Pro 10.5&amp;rdquo; had gone on a sale at BestBuy, and the
configuration I liked dropped to $499 (from $650). While this was a bit
more expensive, I thought it was still a good deal, and the 2018 iPad
wasn&amp;rsquo;t on sale anywhere so it was the full $330.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Features&lt;/strong&gt;: Essentially, the Pro had a slightly larger and &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better display, better speakers, and double the storage space (64GB compared to 32GB). These are features that I don&amp;rsquo;t think most people need to care about, I knew I would really appreciate those features, especially now that I could get them for only a ~$170 increase over the iPad, compared to the normal $310 difference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that&amp;rsquo;s the history and reasoning as to &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I decided to
get a tablet device, and why that device ultimately ended up being an iPad
10.5&amp;rdquo; Pro. It arrived a couple weeks ago, and I have been enjoying it so far. I
think I&amp;rsquo;ll give myself a bit more time with it, before I even &lt;em&gt;attempt&lt;/em&gt; to write any
sort of review.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
